      <text xml:space="preserve">{{otheruses}}
{| {{prettyinfobox}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
&lt;big&gt;''' Kosovo '''&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/big&gt;&lt;br&gt;
|-
| style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Image:Citys of Kosova.PNG|160px]] 
|-
|-

| [[Official language]]s
| [[Albanian language|Albanian]], [[Serbian language|Serbian]], [[Turkish language|Turkish]]
|-
| [[Capital]]
| [[Priština|Prishtinë / Priština / Priştine]]
|-
| [[President of Kosovo]]
| [[Fatmir Sejdiu]]
|-
| [[Prime Minister of Kosovo]]
| [[Agim Çeku]]
|-
| [[Area]]&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; Total&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; % water
| &lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;[[1 E10 m²|10,912]] km²&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;4,213&amp;nbsp;[[square mile|sq.&amp;nbsp;mi]]&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;n/a
|-
| valign=top | [[Population]]&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; Total ([[2003]])&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; [[Population density|Density]]&lt;br/&gt;
| &lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;2.1 million (est.)&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;220/km² (approx)&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;570/sq.&amp;nbsp;mi
|-
| valign=top | [[List of ethnic groups|Ethnic groups]]&lt;br/&gt;([[2003]])
| [[Albanians]]: 88%&lt;br/&gt;[[Serbs]]: 7%&lt;br/&gt;Turks: 1%&lt;br/&gt;Others: 4%
|-
| [[Time zone]]
| [[UTC+1]]
|-
| [[Currency]]
| [[Euro]] (Official and [[Serbian dinar]] (the latter is used exclusively in Serbian-populated areas)
|-
|}
'''Kosova''' ([[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Kosovë''/''Kosova'', [[Serbian language|Serbian]]: ''Косово ''/Kosovo '') is &quot;an entity under interim international administration which, with its people, has unique historical, legal, cultural and linguistic attributes&quot; [http://www.unmikonline.org/constframework.htm]. It is located in the south-eastern Europe and borders [[Albania]], [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]] and [[Montenegro]]. The mountainous province's capital and largest city is [[Priština]]. Kosovo has a population of around two million people, predominately ethnic [[Albanians]], with smaller populations of [[Serbs]] and other ethnic groups.  

The province is the subject of a long-running political and territorial dispute between the Serbian (and before then, the [[Yugoslavia|Yugoslav]]) government and Kosovo's Albanian population. Although the UN Security Resolution 1244 ''[[de jure]]'' considers Kosovo a part of Former Yugoslav Republic of Yugoslavia (now Serbia), it has been administered by the [[United Nations]] since the end of the [[Kosovo War]] in [[1999]]. Kosovo is governed by the [[UNMIK|UN Interim Administrative Mission in Kosovo]] (UNMIK) and the locally elected [[Provisional Institutions of Self-Government]], with security maintained by the [[NATO]]-led [[Kosovo Force]] (KFOR) and [[Kosovo Police Service]]. Negotiations began in [[2006]] to determine the final status of Kosovo.

== Geography ==
''For administrative divisions, see [[Municipalities of Kosovo]]''
[[image:UTkosovo rel small 92.jpg|thumb|left|275px|Physical map of Kosovo]]
With an area of [[1 E10 m²|10,912]] [[square kilometre]]s (4,213 [[square mile|sq.&amp;nbsp;mi]]) and a population of over two million on the eve of the 1999 crisis, Kosovo borders [[Montenegro]] to the northwest, [[Central Serbia]] to the North and East, [[Former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia]] to the south and [[Albania]] to the southwest. The largest cities are [[Priština]] (''Prishtinë'', in [[Albanian language|Albanian]]) the capital, with an estimated 500,000 citizens, and [[Prizren]] in the southwest with 120,000 citizens; five other towns have populations in excess of 50,000. The climate in Kosovo is continental with warm summers and cold and snowy winters. 

There are two main plains in Kosovo, located in the western part of the land (''Rrafshi i Dukagjinit'', and the ''plain of Kosovo-Rrafshi i Kosovës.

Kosovo is mainly mountainous and hilly. [[Sar Mountain]] (in Albanian ''Mali i Sharrit'') is located in the south and south-east, bordering [[Macedonia]]. It is one of the most popular tourist and skiing resorts, with [[Brezovica]] and Prevalac (in Albanian Prevallë) as the main tourist centres. Kosovo's mountainous area, including the highest peak ''Gjeravica'' 2656 m above sea level , is located in the south-west, bordering [[Albania]] and [[Montenegro]]. The mountains are known by Albanians as ''Bjeshkët e Nemuna'' (translated in English ''Cursed mountains'') and sometimes as the ''Albanian Alps''. The Kopaonik mountain is located in the north, bordering [[Serbia proper]]. The central region of [[Drenica]], Carraleva and the eastern part of Kosova, named ''Gallap'' are mainly hilly areas. There are several rivers and lakes in Kosova. The main rivers are Drin River in Albanian: Drini i Bardhë,into which several other waterways flow, including the Erenik, and runs towards the [[Adriatic Sea]],  Sitnica, Morava in Gollak area and Ibar (Albanian Ibër) in the north. The main lakes are ''Badovc'' in north-east and ''Gazivoda'' in north-western part.

== History ==
{{History of Kosovo}}
{{main|History of Kosovo}}
:''See also: [[Demographic history of Kosovo]]''
=== Ancient ===
The region of Kosova has been inhabited by [[Illyrians|Illyrian tribes]] since the [[Bronze Age]]. In ancient times, the area was known as [[Dardania (Europe)|Dardania]] and was settled by a tribe with the same name. The south of Kosovo was ruled by [[Macedon|Macedonia]] since [[Alexander the Great]]'s reign in the 4th century BC. The local [[Dardani]] were of [[Illyrian]] stock. Illyrians resisted rule by the [[Greeks]] and [[Ancient Rome|Romans]] for centuries but after the long periods of conflict between Illyrian tribes and invading imperial powers, the region was eventually occupied by the [[Roman Empire]] under Emperor [[Augustus]] in 28 BC and became part of the Roman province of [[Moesia]]. After [[85|AD 85]] it was part of [[Moesia]] Superior. Emperor [[Diocletian]] later c. [[284]] made Dardania into separate province with its capital at Naissus ([[Niš]]). When the Roman Empire split in [[Anno Domini|A.D.]] [[395]], the area of Kosova came under the [[Byzantine Empire|Eastern Roman Empire]], the [[Byzantine Empire]]. Many inhabitants of [[Dardania]] became leaders in Rome and [[Constantinopolis]], including [[Justinian the Great]].

=== Medieval ===
==== Great Migrations and Interregnums ====
[[Slavic peoples|Slavs]] came to the territories and occupied now form modern Kosovo in the [[6th century|6th]]-[[7th century|7th centuries]], with the largest influx of migrants in the 630s. The Slavs were [[Ortodox -Christianized]] in several waves between the [[7th century|7th]] and [[9th century]], with the last wave taking place between [[867]] and [[874]]. The northwestern part of Kosovo. 

In the late 800s, the whole of Kosovo was seized by the [[First Bulgarian Empire|Czardom of the Bulgarians]]. Although [[Serbia]] restored control over [[Kosova]] throughout the 10th century, the rest of Kosovo was returned to the Byzantine Empire after the Bulgarian Empire crumbled in the late 900s. In a [[Slavic]] rebellion led [[Tsar Samuil of Bulgaria]], the whole of Kosovo came under the control of the renewed [[First Bulgarian Empire|Bulgarian Czardom]] from the late 10th century, until the Byzantine restoration of 1018. In 1040-1041, Slavs staged a rebellion against the Eastern Roman Empire that temporarily encompassed Kosovo. After the rebellion was crushed, the Byzantines restored control. 

Throughout the following decades, numerous foreign peoples invading the Byzantine Empire stormed Kosova, among them the [[Cumans]]. 

In 1072, local Slavs under George Voiteh pushed a final attempt to restore Imperial Bulgarian power and invited the last heir of the [[House of Comitopuli]] - [[Duklja]]'s prince [[Constantine Bodin (Peter III)|Konstantin Bodin]] of the [[House of Vojislavljevic]], son of the [[List of Serbian rulers|Serbian King]] [[Mihailo Voislav]] - to assume power. The Serbs decided to conquer the entire Byzantine region of Bulgaria. King Mihailo dispatched his son with 300 elite Serb fighters led by Duke Petrilo. Constantine Bodin was crowned in [[Prizren]] as ''Petar III'' [[List of rulers of Bulgaria|Czar of the Bulgarians]] by Goerge Voiteh and the Slavic Boyars. The Empire swept across Byzantine territories in months, until the significant losses on the south had forced Czar Petar to withdraw. In 1073, the Byzantine forces chased Constantine Bodin, defeated his army at [[Pauni]] and imprisoned him.


In [[1166]], a Serbian nobleman from [[Zeta (state)|Zeta]], [[Stefan Nemanja]], the founder of the [[Nemanjić|House of Nemanja]] ascended to the Rascian Grand Princely throne and conquered most of Kosovo, in an uprising against the Byzantine Emperor [[Manuel I Comnenus]]. He defeated the previous Grand Prince of Rascia Tihomir's army at Pantino, near Pauni. Tihomir, who was Stefan's brother, was drowned in the [[Sitnica]] river. Stefan was eventually defeated and had to return some of his conquests. He pledged to the Emperor that he would not renew hostilies, but in [[1183]], Stefan Nemanja embarked on a new offensive with the [[Hungarians]] after the death of [[Manuel I Comnenus]] in [[1180]], marking the end of Byzantine domination of Kosovo.


=== Ottoman rule ===
{{main|Viyalet of Kosovo}}
The [[Ottoman Empire|Ottomans]] brought [[Islamisation]] with them, particularly in towns, and later also created the [[Viyalet of Kosovo]] as one of the Ottoman territorial entities. Kosovo was taken by the Austrian forces during the Great War of [[1683]] - [[1699]] with help of 5,000 Albanians and their leader, a [[Catholic Archibishop]] [[Pjetër Bogdani]]. The archbishop died of plague during the war, and his grave was later reopened, with his body scattered and given to the dogs by the Ottomans because of his role in the rebellion. In [[1690]], the [[Serbian Patriarch of Peć]] [[Arsenije III]], who previously escaped a certain death, led nearly 37,000 serbs from Kosovo, to evade [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] wrath since Kosovo had just been retaken by the Ottomans. Due to the oppression from the Ottomans, other migrations of Orthodox people from the Kosovo area continued throughout the [[18th century]]. It is also noted that some [[Serbs]] adopted [[Islam]], while some even gradually fused with other groups, predominantly Albanianians, adopting their culture and even language. 

In 1766, the Ottomans abolished the [[Patriarchate of Peć]] and the position of [[Christians]] in Kosovo was greatly reduced. All previous privileges were lost, and the Christian population had to suffer the full weight of the Empire's extensive and losing wars, even having blame forced upon them for the losses.

=== Modern ===

'''League of Prizren'''


The League of Prizren (Albanian: Lidhja e Prizrenit) was created on June 10, 1878 in a mosque in Prizren, Kosovo by 300 Albanian nationalist leaders, mostly from Kosovo, Albania, Western part of former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia, and Muslim leaders from Bosnia-Hercegovina and the Sandzak, in order to achieve an autonomous Albanian state, representing the former Ottoman vilayets of Shkodër or Skutari centered near Montenegro, the Illyria region, the Chameria region, Janina or Janjevo centered in Northern Epirus, Bitola in Republic of Macedonia and Kosovo. The League was the first major attempt to create a unified Albanian region since the Middle Ages when Albanian forces under Gjergj Kastrioti, Skanderbeg, had failed.


'''History of the League'''

The league was formed after the Treaty of San Stefano, which had given Albanian-populated lands to Bulgaria, Montenegro and Serbia after the Russo-Turkish war of 1877-1878. Albanian leaders from Peja, Gjakova, Gucia, Luma, and from Dibra and Tetovo met in present-day (former Yugoslav) Republic of Macedonia to discuss how to reclaim their land. Italy sponsored an Italian-Albanian Committee to further Albanian nationalism and gain allies in the Balkans and Turkey did the same with a Central Committee for Defending Albanian Rights in Istanbul in 1877. The Committee's members were Zija Prishtina, Sami Frasheri, Jani Vreto, Pashko Vaso, and Abdyl Bey Frashëri, and its manifesto is contained within the Kanararname, or 'Book of Decisions, the statue of the Leaugue.

The League of Prizren was meant as a political and military organization that would help Albania receive international recognition, though initially as an autonomous region. The San Stefano treaty was superseded by the Treaty of Berlin at the insitence of Austria-Hungary and Britain. This latter Treaty, however, still decided that Albanian lands could be split amongst other nations.

In July of 1878, the 60 member board of the league, led by Abdyl Bey Frashëri, sent a letter to the Great Powers at the Congress of Berlin, asking for the settling of the Albanian issues resulting from the Turkish War. The memorandum was ignored by the congress, which gave territory that Albanians considered theirs to Serbia and Montenegro. The league feared that Albanians would also lose Epirus to Greece, and organized an armed resistance in Guci, Shkodër, Prizren, and Janina.

The Albanian resistance was successful enough to alter the borders established by the Great Powers and regain some of the lost lands, however some lands were still ceded to Greece by 1881.

The Prizren League had 16,000 armed members under its control, who launched a revolution against the Ottoman Empire after the debacle at the Congress of Berlin and the official dissolvement of the League ordered by the Ottomans who feared the League would seek total independence from the empire. The Albanian fighters were able to kill Mehmed Ali Pasha, the Turkish emissary, in Gjakova in August, 1878. The League took over control from the Turks in the Kosovo towns of Vucitërn, Peja, Mitrovica, Prizren, and Djakovica. Guided by the autonomous movement, the League rejected Turkish authority and sought complete secession from Turkey. The Ottoman Empire sought to suppress the League and they dispatched an army led by Turkish commander Dervish Pasha, that by April 1881 had captured Prizren and crushed the resistance at Ulcinj. The leaders of the league and their families were either killed or arrested and deported.

While it was active, the league managed to bring Albanian national interests before the Great Powers and paved the way for the Peja League of 1899, which had greater foreign support from both Italy and the Austria-Hungarian Empire, and the Second League of Prizren which formed with help from Nazi Germany and Fascist Italy in 1943.



'''Second League of Prizren'''

The Second League of Prizren was an organisation founded by leading Albanian officials in Kosovo in 1943 to campaign for the ethnic unification of Albanians in Albania and Kosovo, as part of the Greater Albania ideology.

From 1918, Kosovo was integrated into the newly formed Kingdom of Yugoslavia and ethnic Albanians in Kosovo faced forced evacuation by the Yugoslav government to Albania or Turkey. As a result, the Italian occupation of Albania in 1939 led many leading Albanians to lobby the Italians to incoporate the surrounding Albanian speaking areas like Kosovo into Albania and were encouraged by Mussolini's support of the Greater Albania ideology. However, the Italian surrender on 3 September 1943 stymied these dreams temporarily and attention was turned to the Germans who had occupied Debar and Western Macedonia.

Bedri Pejani, a militant and extremist supporter of Greater Albania, wrote to Reichsfuehrer SS Heinrich Himmler to request his assistance in establishing a Greater Albania and in return offered to raise an Albanian fighting force to work with the German Wehrmacht to achieve this aim. Himmler agreed to the request and ordered the formation of two ethnic Albanian Waffen SS Divisions and sponsored the foundation of the Albainian nationalist organisation which became the Second League of Prizren.

Named in honour of the original League of Prizren, founded in 1878 to fight for Kosovo independence, the aim of the Second League of Prizren was to ensure the formation of a greater Albania containing Albania, Kosovo and areas like Debar containing significant Albanian populations. Pejani was appointed President of the League and Albanian Prime Minister Rexhep Mitrovica as chairman of the central committee.

While the League portrayed itself as purely an anti-communist nationalist organisation, many of the League's membership, which reached as many as 15 000 at its peak, held extremist views similar to that of Nazi Germany, including anti-democratic, anti-Orthodox and anti-Slavic views and the League collaborated openly with the Axis powers.

The League campaigned unsuccessfully for the transfer of the northern tip of Kosovo to Albania but raised volunteers against Četnik raids on Albanian villages and maintained the Albanian Ljuboten battalion initially formed by the Italian occupation forces. In conjunction with the Waffen SS, the Second League of Prizren also formed the Albanian Skanderbeg SS Division to maintain the military occupation of the Macedonian and Serbian Orthodox Slavic populations. As a result, 6,491 ethnic Albanians were drafted into the Waffen SS, as well as an additional 300 ethnic Albanians who were serving with the Bosnian Muslim 13th Waffen Gebirgs Division who were transferred to the Skanderbeg Division.

The Skanderbeg Division however were poorly trained and illsuited to warfare and performed poorly. On 30 August 1944, the Skanderbeg Division was forced to retreat from Debar and the League began to lose any influence it had with Germany. The Communist liberation of Albania ensured the end of the League, although Communist officials were methodical in their retribution against League members.



==== Kosovo in the Second Yugoslavia ====
The Province of Kosovo was formed in 1945 as an autonomous region to protect its regional [[Albanians|Albanian]] majority within the [[History of Serbia|People's Republic of Serbia]] as a member of the [[SFRJ|Federal People's Republic of Yugoslavia]] under the leadership of the former Partisan leader, [[Josip Broz Tito]], but with no factual autonomy. After Yugoslavia's name change to the [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia]] and Serbia's to the [[History of Serbia|Socialist Republic of Serbia]] in [[1953]], Kosovo gained inner autonomy in the 1960s. In the [[1974]] constitution, the Socialist Autonomous Province of Kosovo's government received higher powers, including the highest governmental titles — President and Premier and a seat in the Federal Presidency which made it a ''de facto'' Socialist Republic within the Federation, but remaining as a Socialist Autonomous Region within the Socialist Republic of Serbia. [[Serbo-Croatian]] and [[Albanian language|Albanian]] were defined as official languages on the provincial level marking the two largest linguistic Kosovan groups: Serbs and Albanians. In the 1970s, an Albanian nationalist movement pursued full recognition of the Province of Kosovo as another Republic within the Federation, while the most extreme elements aimed for full-scale independence. Tito's arbitrary regime dealt with the situation swiftly, but only giving it a temporary solution.Albanian population was over 88% and other was serb,muslims,turks,roma etc. 

Beginning in March [[1981]], Kosovar Albanian students organized protests seeking that Kosovo become a republic within Yugoslavia. Those protests rapidly escalated into violent riots &quot;involving 20,000 people in six cities&quot; &lt;ref name=&quot;nyt19810419&quot;&gt;New York Times 1981-04-19, &quot;One Storm has Passed but Others are Gathering in Yugoslavia&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; that were harshly contained by the Yugoslav government. 

In [[1986]], the Serbian Academy of Sciences and Arts (SANU) was working on a document which later would be known as the [[SANU Memorandum]], a warning to the Serbian President and Assembly of the existing crisis and where it would lead. An unfinished edition was filtered to the press. In the essay, SANU criticised the state of Yugoslavia and made remarks that the only member state contributing at the time to the development of Kosovo and Macedonia (by then, the poorest territories of the Federation) was Serbia. According to SANU, Yugoslavia was suffering of ethnic strives and the disintegration of the Yugoslav economy into separate economic sectors and territories, which was transforming the federal state into a loose confederation&lt;ref&gt;SANU (1986): [http://www.balkan-archive.org.yu/kosta/memorandum/contents.html Serbian Academy of Sciences and Arts Memorandum]. GIP Kultura. Belgrade.&lt;/ref&gt;. On the other hand, some think that [[Slobodan Milošević]] used the discontent reflected in the SANU memorandum for his own political goals, during his rise to power in [[Serbia]] at the time&lt;ref&gt;http://www.opendemocracy.net/articles/ViewPopUpArticle.jsp?id=2&amp;articleId=3361 Julie A Mertus: &quot;Slobodan Milosevic: Myth and Responsibility&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;.

By the end of the 1980s, calls for increased federal control in the crisis-torn autonomous province were getting louder. [[Slobodan Milošević]] pushed for constitutional change amounting to suspension of autonomy for both Kosovo and [[Vojvodina]] &lt;ref name=&quot;reuters19880730&quot;&gt;Reuters 1988-07-30, &quot;Yugoslav Leaders Call for Control in Kosovo, Protests Loom&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;.

==== Kosovo War ====
{{main|Kosovo War}}
One of the events that contributed to Milošević's rise of power was the ''Gazimestan Speech'', delivered in front of 100,000 Serb citizens at the central celebration marking the 600th anniversary of the [[Battle of Kosovo]], held at [[Gazimestan]] on 28 June, 1989. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.balkanpeace.org/cib/kam/kams/kams19.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; In the speech, Milošević criticised the &quot;dramatical national divisions&quot; and called Yugoslavia &quot;a multinational community [which] can survive only under the conditions of full equality for all nations that live in it.&quot; 

Soon afterwards, as approved by the Assembly in 1990, the autonomy of Kosovo was reduced. After [[Slovenia]]'s secession from Yugoslavia in 1991, Milošević used the seat to attain dominance over the Federal government, outvoting his opponents. 

Many Albanians organized a peaceful separatist movement. State institutions and elections were boycotted and separate Albanian schools and political institutions were established. On [[July 2]], [[1990]] an unconstitutional Kosovo parliament declared Kosovo an independent country, this was not recognized by the Government or any foreign states. In September of that year, the unofficial parliament, meeting in secrecy in the town of [[Kaçanik]], adopted the ''Constitution of the Republic of Kosovo''. Two years later, in 1992, the parliament organized an unofficial referendum which was observed by international organisations {{citation needed}} but was not recognized internationally. With an ''80%'' turnout, ''98%'' voted for Kosovo to be independent.

With the events in [[Bosnia]] and [[Croatia]] coming to an end, the Serb government started relocating Serbian refugees from Croatia and Bosnia all over Serbia, including in Kosovo. In a number of cases, Albanian families were expelled from their apartments to make room for the refugees{{citation needed}}.
[[Image:Kosovo_pisg_logo.PNG|thumb|right|200px|The Coat of Arms of the [[Provisional Institutions of Self-Government]]]]
After the [[Dayton]] Agreement in 1995, some Albanians organized into the [[Kosovo Liberation Army]] (KLA), employing guerilla-style tactics against Serbian police forces and civilians. Violence escalated in a series of KLA attacks and Serbian reprisals into the year 1999, with increasing numbers of civilian victims. In 1998 western interest increased and the Serbian authorities was forced to sign a unilateral cease-fire and partial retreat. Under an agreement led by [[Richard Holbrooke]], [[OSCE]] observers moved into Kosovo to monitor the ceasefire, while Yugoslav military forces partly pulled out of Kosovo. However, the ceasefire was systematically broken shortly thereafter by KLA forces, which again provoked harsh counterattacks by the Serbs. On 16 January 1999, the bodies of 45 Albanian civilians were found in the town of [[Racak]]. The victims had been executed by Serb forces &lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/1812847.stm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hrw.org/press/1999/jan/yugo0129.htm&lt;/ref&gt;. The so-called Racak Massacre was instrumental in increasing the pressure on Serbia in the following conference at [[Rambouillet]]. After more than a month of negotations Yugoslavia refused to sign the prepared agreement, primarily, it has beeen argued, because of a clause giving NATO forces access rights to not only Kosovo but to all of Yugoslavia (which the Yugoslav side saw as tantamount to military occupation).

This triggered a 78-day [[NATO]] campaign in [[1999]]. At first limited to military targets in Kosovo proper, the bombing campaign was soon extended to cover targets all over Yugoslavia, including bridges, power stations, factories, broadcasting stations, post offices, and various government buildings. 

During the conflict, several thousand were killed, the numbers and the ethnic distribution of the casualties are uncertain and highly disputed. An estimated 10,000-12,000 ethnic Albanians and 3,000 Serbs are believed to have been killed during the conflict, including military personnel and civilians, primarily as a result of the ground war in Kosovo between the KLA and the Yugoslav military, Serbian police and Serbian paramilitary forces. Some 3000 people are still missing,of which 2,500 are Albanian, 400 Serbs and 100 Roma&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/781310.stm&lt;/ref&gt;. According to OSCE numbers and Kosovar Albanian sources on population size and distribution, an estimated ''45.7%'' of the Albanian population and ''59.5%'' of the Serb population had fled Kosovo during the bombings (i.e. from 23 March to 9 June 1999). 

With the arrival of NATO, a large number of Serbs fled the region, estimated at 100,000 by the UNHCR. Around 120,000 remain in Kosovo. Many Serbs fear to return to their homes since they perceive not to be safe for them, even with [[UNMIK]] protection, notably the [[2004 unrest in Kosovo|unrest in 2004]], when 900 Serbian houses were burned and other property destroyed{{citation needed}} while the Serbian populace was closed into enclaves and had to concentrate to the north of Kosovo until today, causing a wave of 3,500 Serbian refugees.


During the Kosovo War, Serbs also engaged in a deliberate campaign of cultural destruction and rampage. According to a report compiled by the Kosovo Cultural Heritage Project, Serbian forces tried to wipe out all Albanian culture and traditions. Of the 500 mosques that were in use prior to the war, 200 of them were completely destroyed or desecrated. The report concludes that most mosques were deliberately set on fire with no sign of fighting around the area. Among numerous other things, the following important objects were destroyed because they represented Albanian as well as Muslim and Catholic cultures:

Sinan Pasha Mosque in Prizren, the Prizren League Museum, the Hadum Mosque complex in Gjakova (Serbian: Djakovica); the historic bazaars in Gjakova and Pec (Albanian: Peja); the Roman Catholic church of St. Anthony in Gjakova; and two old Ottoman bridges, Ura e Terzive (Terzijski most) and Ura e Tabakeve (Tabacki most), near Gjakova.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.haverford.edu/relg/sells/kosovo/herscherriedlmayer.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

== Politics ==
&lt;!--Please add new information into relevant articles of the series--&gt;
{{morepolitics|country=Kosovo}}

The talks on the future status of Kosovo between the government of Serbia, which wants the territory to remain part of Serbia albeit with a high degree of autonomy, and the provisional government of Kosovo, which wants independence for the province, have started in [[Vienna]], on February 20, [[2006]]. According to the UN Envoy to the status talks the status will be resolved by the end of year [[2006]].

== Economy ==

Kosovo is one of the poorest economies in Europe, with a per capita income estimated at 964 [[Euro]] (2004).&lt;ref&gt;http://ec.europa.eu/comm/enlargement/serbia_montenegro/kosovo_economical_profile.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Despite substantial development subsidies from all Yugoslav republics, Kosovo was the poorest province of Yugoslavia &lt;ref&gt;Christian Science Monitor 1982-01-15, &quot;Why Turbulent Kosovo has Marble Sidewalks but Troubled Industries&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;. Additionally, over the course of the 1990s, poor economic policies, international sanctions, weak access to external trade and finance, and ethnic conflict severely damaged the economy.&lt;ref&gt;http://web.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/COUNTRIES/ECAEXT/KOSOVOEXTN/0,,menuPK:297775~pagePK:141159~piPK:141110~theSitePK:297770,00.html&lt;/ref&gt;

Kosovo's economy remains weak. After a jump in 2000 and 2001 [[GDP]] growth was negative in 2002 and 2003 and is expected to be around 3 percent 2004-2005, with domestic sources of growth unable to compensate for the declining foreign assistance. [[Inflation]] is low, while the budget posted a deficit for the first time in 2004. Kosovo has high external deficits. In 2004, the deficit of the balance of goods and services was close to 70 percent of [[GDP]]. Remittances from Kosovars living abroad accounts for an estimated 13 percent of [[GDP]], and foreign assistance for around 34 percent of [[GDP]].&lt;ref&gt;http://ec.europa.eu/economy_finance/publications/enlargement_papers/2005/elp26en.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

Most economic development since 1999 has taken place in the trade, retail and the construction sectors. The private sector that has emerged since 1999 is mainly small-scale. The industrial sector remains weak and the electric power supply remains unreliable, acting as a key constraint. Unemployment remains pervasive, at around 40-50% of the labor force.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.eciks.org/english/lajme.php?action=total_news&amp;main_id=386&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://ec.europa.eu/economy_finance/publications/enlargement_papers/2005/elp26en.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; 

UNMIK introduced ''de-facto'' an external trade regime and customs administration on September 3, 1999 when it set customs border controls in Kosovo. All goods imported in Kosovo face a flat 10% customs duty fee.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.buyusa.gov/kosovo/en/doingbusinessinkosovo.html&lt;/ref&gt; These taxes are collected from all Tax Collection Points installed at the borders of Kosovo, including those between Kosovo and  Serbia.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.seerecon.org/kosovo/documents/wb_econ_report/wb-kosovo-econreport-2-2.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;. UNMIK and Kosovo institutions have signed Free Trade Agreements with [[Bosnia and Hercegovina]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.euinkosovo.org/upload_press/4.06%20-%20UNMIK%20and%20Bosnia%20and%20Herzegovina%20Initial%20Free%20Trade%20Agreement%2017.2.06.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;, [[Albania]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.kosovo-eicc.org/oek/index.php?page_id=64&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Macedonia]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.buyusa.gov/kosovo/en/doingbusinessinkosovo.html&lt;/ref&gt;. 

The [[Euro]] is the official currency of Kosovo and used by UNMIK and the government bodies&lt;ref&gt;http://www.euinkosovo.org/uk/invest/invest.php&lt;/ref&gt;. The Serbian [[Dinar]] is used in the Serbian populated parts.

== Demographics ==
According to the 2000 Living Standard Measurement Survey of the Statistical Office of Kosovo&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sok-kosovo.org/pdf/population/Kosovo_population.pdf 2000 Living Standard Measurement Survey of the Statistical Office of Kosovo&lt;/ref&gt;, Kosovo's total population is estimated between 1,8 and 2,0 million in the following ethnic proportions:
* ''88%'' [[Albanians]] (between 1,584,000 and 1,733,600) 
* ''7%'' [[Serbs]] (between 126,000 and 140,000)	
* ''1.9%'' [[Bosniaks]] (between 34,200 and 38,000) 
* ''1.7%'' [[Roma people|Roma]] (between 30,600 and 34,000) (see also [[Roma in Mitrovica Camps]])
* ''1%'' [[Turkish people|Turks]] (between 18,000 and 20,000)

However, the figures are highly disputable. Some estimates are that there is an Albanian majority well above 90 percent. The population census is set to take place in the near future. Others give much higher figures for Roma and Turks &lt;ref&gt;http://www.salon.com/news/1999/03/31newsa.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.serbianunity.net/news/world_articles/Dragnich1098.html&lt;/ref&gt;. There was also a small minority of [[Circassians]] in [[Kosovo Polje]] but they were repatriated to the [[Republic of Adygea]], in Southern [[Russia]]. The ethnic Albanian Kosovo Liberation Army is thought to have threatened the Adygs.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/143667.stm BBC News: ''Circassians flee Kosovo conflict''. Sunday, August 2, 1998 Published at 01:01 GMT 02:01 UK&lt;/ref&gt;

== Subdivisions ==

''Main article: [[Subdivisions of Kosovo]], also see: [[Municipalities of Kosovo]].''

Kosovo is divided into 7 districts:
*[[Mitrovica District|Mitrovica/Kosovska Mitrovica District]]
*[[Prishtina District|Prishtina/Priština District]]
*[[Gjilani District|Gjilani/Gnjilane District]]
*[[Peja District|Peja/Peć District]]
*[[Gjakova District|Gjakova/Đakovica District]]
*[[Prizreni District|Prizreni/Prizren District]]
*[[Ferizaji District|Ferizaji/Uroševac District]]

== Cities ==
[[Image:Prishtina maj 2005.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Prishtina]]/[[Priština]]]]
List of largest cities in Kosovo (with population figures in 2006)&lt;ref&gt;http://www.world-gazetteer.com/wg.php?x=&amp;men=gcis&amp;lng=en&amp;dat=32&amp;srt=npan&amp;col=aohdq&amp;geo=-244&lt;/ref&gt;:
*[[Prishtina]]/[[Priština]] (262,686)
*[[Prizreni]]/[[Prizren]] (165,227)
*[[Ferizaji]]/[[Uroševac]] (97,741)
*[[Gjakova]]/[[Đakovica]] (97,156)
*[[Peja]]/[[Peć]] (95,190)
*[[Gjilani]]/[[Gnjilane]] (91,595)
*[[Mitrovica (Kosovo)|Mitrovica]]/[[Kosovska Mitrovica]] (86,359)
*[[Podujeva]]/[[Podujevo]] (48,526)

== Culture ==

* [[Music of Kosovo]]

== List of Presidents ==
List of the presidents of Kosovo &lt;ref&gt;http://www.worldstatesmen.org/Yugoslavia.html#Kosovo&lt;/ref&gt;:
* [[Fatmir Sejdiu]], [[10 February]] [[2006]] - present
* Nexhat Daci (acting), [[21 January]] 2006 - 10 February 2006 
* [[Ibrahim Rugova]], [[4 March]] [[2002]] - 21 January 2006

== List of Prime Ministers ==
* [[Bajram Rexhepi]], [[2002]]-[[2004]]
* [[Ramush Haradinaj]], [[2004]]-[[2005]]
* [[Bajram Kosumi]], [[2005]]-[[2006]]
* [[Agim Çeku]], [[2006]]-present

== Gallery ==
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Kosovo_government.jpg|The building of the [[Government of Kosovo]] in [[Prishtina]]/[[Priština]]
Image:Prizen kosovo.jpg|[[Prizreni]]/[[Prizren]]
Image:Gjakova.jpg|[[Gjakova]]/[[Đakovica]]
Image:French Peugeot P4 dsc06852.jpg|[[KFOR]]
Image:Airprishtinagren0.jpg|[[Priština International Airport|Prishtina/Priština International Airport]]
Image:Rahoveci.jpg|[[Rahovec]]/[[Orahovac]]
Image:Ne Udhetim 132.jpg|Center of [[Prishtina]]/[[Priština]], monument to [[Skenderbeg]]
Image:Decani.jpg|A 14th-century fresco in [[Visoki Dečani monastery]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== See also ==
* [[History of Kosovo]]
* [[Assembly of Kosovo]]
* [[Government of Kosovo]]
* [[Prime Minister of Kosovo]]
* [[President of Kosovo]]
* [[Albanians in Kosovo]]
* [[Kosovo war]]
* [[Serbs in Kosovo]]
* [[Post and Telecom of Kosovo]]
* [[Battle of Kosovo|Battle of Kosovo (1389)]]
* [[Subdivisions of Kosovo]]
* [[National awakening and the birth of Albania]]
* [[Demographic history of Kosovo]]
* [[Unrest in Kosovo]] (during March 2004)
* [[Sexual trafficking in Kosovo]]
* [[Metohija]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

== External links ==
{{sisterlinks|Kosovo}}
* [http://ec.europa.eu/economy_finance/publications/enlargement_papers/2005/elp26en.pdf EU Commission report on economic development in Accession countries, including Kosovo]
* [http://www.balkanforums.com Kosovo and the Balkans] - Discussion Forum
* [http://ec.europa.eu/comm/enlargement/serbia_montenegro/kosovo_economical_profile.htm European Commission information on Kosovo] 
* [http://www.ks-gov.net/esk/index_english.htm Kosovo Statistical Office (SOK)]
* [http://digital.library.unt.edu/govdocs/crs/search.tkl?q=kosovo&amp;search_crit=fulltext&amp;search=Search&amp;date1=Anytime&amp;date2=Anytime&amp;type=form  Congressional Research Service (CRS) Reports regarding Kosovo]
* {{wikitravel}}
* [http://www.rtklive.com  RTK - Kosova's public television - news in Albanian, Serbian, Turkish and Roma]
* [https://www.osce.org/documents/mik/1999/11/1620_en.pdf Human Rights in Kosovo: As Seen, As Told. Volume I, October 1998 - June 1999].
* [http://www.lib.utexas.edu/maps/kosovo.html Kosovo maps from the Perry-Castañeda Library Map Collection]
* [http://www.kosovakosovo.com/ KosovaKosovo] A source of information reflecting both sides’ claims in the dispute
* [http://www.nato.int/kosovo/ KFOR] [[NATO]] led peacekeeping force in Kosovo.
* [http://www.unmikonline.org/ UNMIK] [[UN]] led civilian administration in Kosovo.
* [http://www.euinkosovo.org/index.php EU] EU Pillar in Kosovo. 
* [http://www.kpaonline.org/ KPA] [[Kosovo Property]] Kosovo Property Agency - KPA.
* [http://www.hpdkosovo.org/ Housing and Property Directorate] Housing and Property Directorate - HPD.
* [http://www.chmouel.com/geeklog/gallery/gallery_individual.php/mkosovo/ A collection of photos from Kosovo]
* [http://www.otvoreno.org.yu/ Otvoreno ] A place where Serbian politicians speak openly on the Kosovo issue
* [http://www.iom.ipko.org/ IOM ] International Organization for Migration 
* [http://www.crisisgroup.org/home/index.cfm?id=1243&amp;l=1 (ICG)] International Crisis Group, a source of independent analysis on Kosovo issues.
* [http://www.xhakli.com/2004/05/kosovo-search-challenge-helping-people_25.php?show_id=108543905534062634 Kosovo Blog] Search Challenge: Helping people find information from Kosovo
* [http://www.eciks.org/english/index.php ECIKS] Economic Initiative for Kosova, information on investment opportunities. 

=== Pro-Albanian ===
* [http://www.savekosova.org/ Save Kosova] American Council for Kosovo, increasing the awareness of the recognition of Kosovo's independence in the American society.
* [http://BalkanUpdate.com Balkan Update]- A blog with news, analysis and the lates updates from Balkans
* [http://www.eciks.org Economic Initiative for Kosovo] - &quot;...latest news, analysis and publications from the Kosovar economy&quot;
* [http://www.albanian.com/main/countries/kosova Albanian.com] - general information
* [http://www.kosovaelire.com/ Kosova e lirë] (Free Kosova) -- Material about Kosovars and Albanians in Albanian language. 
* [http://www.alb-shkenca.org/images/stories/Why%20Independence.pdf Why Independence for Kosovo?] A summary of the case for an independent Kosovo by two Prishtina intellectuals
* [http://www.newkosovo.org/news.htm Alliance for New Kosovo] A policy resource on Kosovo Independence
* [http://kosovareport.blogspot.com/ Kosovareport] A collection of news on Kosovo, in English, gathered from many agencies.
* [http://www.alb-net.com/index.htm Kosova Crisis Center] A collection of articles on Kosovo, in English.
* [http://www.aacl.com/indexmain.html AACL] Albanian American Civic League.
* [http://vetevendosje.org/ Vetëvendosje] (in translation Self-determination) a movement which fights for the recognition of Kosovo people's right for self-determination on the status of Kosovo.
* [http://www.kosovalive.com/?cid=2 KosovaLive] Kosovo Albanian independent news agency (this section in English).

=== Pro-Serbian ===
* [http://www.srbija.sr.gov.yu/kosovo-metohija/ Serbian Government Kosovo-Metohija site]
* [http://www.kosovo.net/ Kosovo.net] Serbian Orthodox Church's official website on Kosovo
* [http://www.rastko.org.yu/kosovo/crucified/default.htm Account of destroyed Serbian Orthodox churches in Kosovo and Metohija]
* [http://groups.yahoo.com/group/decani/ Kosovo Newsgroup archive]
* [http://www.kc.gov.yu/ Coordination Center of SCG and the Republic of Serbia for Kosovo]
* [http://www.tserkovnost.org/srbija/ Eastern Orthodox Resource Centre]
* [http://www.axisglobe.com/article.asp?article=689 Southern Serbia: The second Kosovo?]
* [http://serbo.blogspot.com Kosovo News blog]
* [http://www.b92.net/english/news/index.php?style=headlines&amp;nav_category=19 B92] Serbian Independent news agency
* [http://www.kosovo.net/sk/history/kosovo_origins/default.htm Hugo Roth, ''Kosovo Origins'']: a historian's comprehensive overview
* [http://www.americansforkosovo.org The American Council for Kosovo]

{{Kosovo}}

[[Category:Disputed territories]]
[[Category:Kosovo]]
[[Category:UN peacekeeping missions and operations]]

[[ar:قوصوة]]
[[ast:Kosovo]]
[[zh-min-nan:Kosovo]]
[[bs:Kosovo]]
[[bg:تîٌîâî]]
[[ca:Kosovo]]
[[cs:Kosovo]]
[[da:Kosovo]]
[[de:Kosovo]]
[[et:Kosovo]]
[[es:Kosovo]]
[[eo:Kosovo]]
[[fr:Kosovo]]
[[ko:코소보]]
[[hr:Kosovo]]
[[id:Kosovo]]
[[it:Kosovo]]
[[he:קוסובו ומטוחיה]]
[[lt:Kosovas]]
[[hu:Koszovó]]
[[mk:Косово]]
[[nl:Kosovo]]
[[ja:コソボ]]
[[no:Kosovo]]
[[nn:Kosovo]]
[[nds:Kosovo]]
[[pl:Kosowo]]
[[pt:Kosovo]]
[[ro:Kosovo]]
[[ru:Косово]]
[[sq:Kosova]]
[[sr:Косово]]
[[fi:Kosovo]]
[[sv:Kosovo]]
[[tr:Kosova]]
[[uk:Косово]]
[[zh:科索沃]]</text>
