      <text xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi-protected|small=yes}}
&lt;!--

Please be very careful in editing the introduction of this article. The Arbitration Committee has placed this article on probation. While this occurred in 2006, it was never lifted; thus, this page is still under probation. If any editor makes disruptive edits, they may be banned by an administrator from this and related articles, or other reasonably related pages. See the talk page for more information.

Please also note that the current delicate political situation of Kosovo makes the terms of article probation all the more important. DO NOT ENGAGE IN EDIT-WARRING ON THIS ARTICLE or any related articles. Edit-warring on this article will result in immediate blocking and application of additional sanctions under the terms of probation as administrators and/or the community deem appropriate. Thank you.

--&gt;
{{current related|article|2008 Kosovo declaration of independence|date=February 2008}}
{{otheruses1|the country in Europe}}
{{distinguish|Kosovo (UNMIK)}}
{{redirect|Republic of Kosova||Republic of Kosova (1990–2000)}}
{{Infobox Country
|native_name              = {{nowrap|{{lang|sq|'''''Republika e Kosovës'''''}}&lt;br&gt;{{lang|sr-Cyrl|Република Косово}} / {{lang|sr-Latn|''Republika Kosovo''}}}}
|conventional_long_name   = Republic of Kosovo
|common_name              = Kosovo
|image_flag               = Flag of Kosovo.svg
|image_coat               = Coat_of_arms_of_Kosovo.svg&lt;!-- Avoid changing this,it has a reliable source: http://www.kosovapress.com/ks/repository/images/stema_kosoves_thmb.jpg --&gt;
|image_map                = Kosovo in Europe 2008.png
|map_caption              = Location of Kosovo on the [[Europe|European continent]]

|national_motto           = 
|national_anthem          =  &lt;!-- ''[[European anthem|Ode to Joy]]''{{Fact|date=February 2008}} --&gt;&lt;!-- I have hidden this, as it has no source. Please only restore this when there's a reliable source confirming that this is the anthem of Kosovo. --&gt;
|official_languages       = [[Albanian language|Albanian]], [[Serbian language|Serbian]]
|regional_languages       = [[Turkish language|Turkish]], [[Našinski|Gorani]], [[Romani language|Romani]], [[Bosnian language|Bosnian]]
|ethnic_groups            = 92% [[Albanians]]&lt;br/&gt;{{spaces|2}}5.3% [[Serbs]]&lt;br/&gt;{{spaces|2}}2.7% others &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ks-gov.net/ESK/esk/english/english.htm Enti i Statistikës së Kosovës]&lt;/ref&gt;
|ethnic_groups_year       = 2007
|capital                  = {{nowrap|[[Pristina]]}}&lt;!--

PLEASE DO NOT CHANGE THE CAPITAL'S NAME! Per talkpage, we currently use Pristina, not Prishtina or Priština.

--&gt;
|latd=42 |latm=40 |latNS=N |longd=21 |longm=10 |longEW=E
|largest_city             = capital
|demonym                  = Kosovar
|government_type          = [[Parliamentary system|Parliamentary]]  [[republic]]
|leader_title1            = [[President of Kosovo|President]]
|leader_name1             = [[Fatmir Sejdiu]] ([[Democratic League of Kosovo|LDK]])
|leader_title2            = [[Prime Minister of Kosovo|Prime Minister]]
|leader_name2             = [[Hashim Thaçi]] ([[Democratic Party of Kosovo|PDK]])
|leader_title3            = [[Chair of the Assembly of Kosovo|Chair of the Assembly]]
|leader_name3             = [[Jakup Krasniqi]] ([[Democratic Party of Kosovo|PDK]]) 
|sovereignty_type         = [[Independence]]{{smallsup|1}}
|sovereignty_note         = from [[Serbia]]
|established_event1       = [[2008 Kosovo declaration of independence|Declared]]
|established_date1        = [[17 February]] [[2008]]
|established_event2       = [[International reaction to the 2008 Kosovo declaration of independence|Recognized]]
|established_date2        = by 17 countries &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=[[United States Secretary of State|US Secretary of State]] [[Condoleezza Rice]]|title=U.S. Recognizes Kosovo as Independent State|publisher=[[U.S. Department of State]]|url=http://www.state.gov/secretary/rm/2008/02/100973.htm|date=[[2008-02-18]]|accessdate=2008-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Britain, France recognise Kosovo|publisher=[[Associated Press]]|url=http://ap.google.com/article/ALeqM5jvieojQfAH0lC-MNOQEfGdVlX1XAD8USR0K01|date=[[2008-02-18]]|accessdate=2008-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes u.s. france&quot;&gt;{{cite news|first=Stephen|last=Castle|title=Kosovo is Recognised by U.S., France and Britain|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/02/19/world/europe/19kosovo.html?ref=world|date=[[2008-02-18]]|accessdate=2008-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|area_rank                = 166
|area_magnitude           = 1 E10
|area_km2                 = 10,887
|area_sq_mi               = 4,203
|percent_water            = n/a
|population_estimate      = 1,900,000&lt;ref&gt;See: [http://enrin.grida.no/htmls/kosovo/SoE/popullat.htm UN estimate], Kosovo’s population estimates range from 1.9 to 2.4 million. The last two population census conducted in 1981 and 1991 estimated Kosovo’s population at 1.6 and 1.9 million respectively, but the 1991 census probably undercounted Albanians. The latest estimate in 2001 by OSCE puts the number at 2.4 Million.&lt;/ref&gt;
|population_estimate_rank = 141
|population_estimate_year = 2007
|population_census        = 1,956,196{{smallsup|3}}
|population_census_year   = 1991
|population_density_km2   = 220
|population_density_sq_mi = 500
|population_density_rank  = 55
|currency                 = [[Euro]] (€){{smallsup|2}}
|currency_code            = EUR
|time_zone                = [[Central European Time|CET]]
|utc_offset               = +1
|time_zone_DST            = [[Central European Summer Time|CEST]]
|utc_offset_DST           = +2
|cctld                    =  ''None assigned''
|calling_code             =  ''None assigned''
|footnote1                = [[International reaction to the 2008 Kosovo declaration of independence|Independence has only been partially recognised internationally.]]
|footnote2                = Unilaterally adopted. Kosovo is not a member of the [[European Monetary Union|EMU]].
|footnote3                = The census is a reconstruction; most of the ethnic Albanian majority boycotted.
}}

'''Kosovo''' &lt;!--Please leave the following language order as Albanian followed by Serbian: this is alphabetical and as neutral as we can get; Albanian is also the primary language of the region--&gt;({{lang-sq|Kosova}} or ''Kosovë'', {{lang-sr|Косово}}, ''Kosovo'', {{lang-tr|Kosova}}, ''see'': [[Names of Kosovo]]), officially the '''Republic of Kosovo''' ({{lang-sq|Republika e Kosovës}}, {{lang-sr|Република Косово}}, ''Republika Kosovo''), is a [[International reaction to the 2008 Kosovo declaration of independence|partially recognized]] [[landlocked]] republic in [[southeastern Europe]], formerly a part of the [[Republic of Serbia]]. It has a population of about two million people, predominantly ethnic [[Albanians]], with smaller populations of  [[Serbs]], [[Romani people]], [[Gorani (ethnic group)|Gorani]]s, [[Bosniaks]], [[Turkish people|Turks]] and other ethnic communities. [[Pristina]] is the capital and largest city. Kosovo borders [[Montenegro]] to the west, [[Albania]] to the southwest, [[Republic of Macedonia]] to the south and [[Serbia]] to the north and east.

Following the [[Kosovo War]] in 1999, [[United Nations]] [[United Nations Security Council|Security Council]] [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 1244|Resolution 1244]] placed Kosovo under the authority of the [[United Nations Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo]] (UNMIK), with security provided by the [[NATO]]-led [[Kosovo Force]] (KFOR), and legally reaffirmed Serbia's [[sovereignty]] over the region and committed the UN Member States to its territorial integrity. After [[Kosovo status process|UN-sponsored negotiations]] failed to reach a consensus on an acceptable [[constitutional status of Kosovo|constitutional status]], [[Provisional Institutions of Self-Government|Kosovo's provisional government]] unilaterally [[declaration of independence|declared independence]] from [[Serbia]] on [[17 February]] [[2008]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/7249034.stm BBC News:  Kosovo MPs proclaim independence - February 17, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt; and receiving [[International reaction to the 2008 Kosovo declaration of independence#States that formally recognise the independent Republic of Kosovo|partial international recognition]] as a [[sovereign state]] (notably from the [[United States]] and some major [[Europe]]an countries). 

Kosovo's sovereignity is disputed by [[Serbia]], [[Russia]], [[China]], [[Spain]], [[Romania]], [[Slovakia]], [[Greece]], [[Cyprus]]  and  other nations.  The official position of these countries is that Kosovo is a Serbian province under ad interim  [[UN]] control , formally known as [[Autonomous Province of Kosovo and Metohija]] ({{lang-sr|Аутономна покрајина Косово и Метохија}}, ''Autonomna pokrajina Kosovo i Metohija'', also Космет, ''Kosmet''; {{lang-sq|Krahina Autonome e Kosovës dhe Metohisë}}).

== History ==
{{main|History of Kosovo}}
===Ancient and medieval periods===
Kosovo was known in antiquity and up to the 19th century as [[Dardania]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.albanianhistory.net/texts/AH1883.html Arthur Evans, “Some Observations on the Present State of Dardania,” R. Elsie ed., ''Albanian History'']&lt;/ref&gt; (from Albanian word ''dardhë'' = pear; literally ''Pearland'') after the Illyrian tribe [[Dardani]].&lt;ref&gt;Noel Malcolm, ''Kosovo: A Short History'' (UP: New York, 2003) 31.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Aleksandar Stipcevic, ''Iliri'', 30; Mirdita, ''Studime dardane'', 7-46; Papazoglu, ''Central Balkan Tribes'', 210-69 &amp; &quot;Dardanska onomastika&quot;; Katicic, ''Ancient Languages'', 179-81&lt;/ref&gt; Historical sources mention a Kingdom of Dardania as early as 4th century B.C., which included Kosovo and parts of surrounding areas.&lt;ref&gt;Bep Jubani, &quot;Mbretëria Dardane,&quot; ''Historia e popullit shqiptar: për shkollat e mesme'' (Libri Shkollor: Prishtinë, 2002) 26-29.&lt;/ref&gt; Prominent kings include [[Longarus]], Monunius, and Bato, who engaged in frequent wars against [[Macedon]] and achieved numerous successful victories.&lt;ref&gt;Bep Jubani, &quot;Mbretëria Dardane,&quot; ''Historia e popullit shqiptar: për shkollat e mesme'' (Libri Shkollor: Prishtinë, 2002) 26-29.&lt;/ref&gt; There is also an account of wars with the Celts. Dardania was well-known for its gold resources and ancient writings describe the Dardani as fine producers of jewels. Major cities included Damastion, Naissus ([[Nis]], [[Serbia]]), Scupi ([[Skopje]], [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]]), and Ulpiana.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.shqiperia.com/kat/m/shfaqart/aid/71.html Historia e Shqipërisë, “Mbretëria e Dardanisë: Territori dhe popullsia,” ''Shqiperia.com'']&lt;/ref&gt; 

Dardania was conquered by Rome in the late 1st century B.C. and gave the [[Roman Empire]] some of its most outstanding emperors, including [[Constantine the Great]]. Christianity was spread in the country in its initial phases, while individuals like [[Nicetas of Remesiana|Niketas Dardani]], authored the early Christian hymnals.

Following the [[Migration Period|barbarian invasions]] between the 5th and 8th century, Dardania became a safe haven for the preservation of Illyrian culture and language as well as the heritage of the Romanized population, and remained part of the Byzantine empire.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=R0tGOdHl7_0 WatchMojo, &quot;The Illyrian Empire,&quot; ''Youtube'']&lt;/ref&gt; In the 9th century, Dardania was conquered by the [[First Bulgarian Empire|Bulgarian empire]].  Later it was briefly returned to the Byzantines, before the [[Serbia]]n invasion in the late 12th century. In the next 100 years, the Serbs established their rule over Kosovo. During this time, the seat of the [[Serbian Orthodox Church]] was moved to [[Peja]],&lt;ref&gt;Noel Malcolm, ''Kosovo: A Short History'' (UP: New York, 2003) 50.&lt;/ref&gt; while the natural resources allowed for a further expansion of the Serbian state. With the creation of a Serbian empire in the 1346 century, Dardania became a central geographical unit of the Serbian state. This fact and the presence of the Serbian Orthodoxy in the region has given rise to the Serbian cultural belief regarding Kosovo as the “cradle of the Serbian civilization.”

In 1389, in the famous [[Battle of Kosovo]] a coalition of Christian armies including Serbs, Albanians, Bosnians and Hungarians, led by the Serbian prince [[Lazar Hrebljanovic]] was defeated by the [[Ottoman Turks]], who finally took control of the territory in [[1455]].  During the intervening years, some Serbian lords were granted the power to rule as vassals of the Ottoman Sultan, who used them as a means of quelling liberation movements from any of the Balkan nations.  In the [[Battle of Kosovo (1448)|Second Battle of Kosovo]], the Turkish vassal, [[Djuradj Brankovic]], barricaded the Albanian leader [[Gjergj Kastrioti]] from joining with the Hungarian army of [[Janos Hunyadi]], who faced a weighty defeat.

===Ottoman rule===
{{seealso|Vilayet of Kosovo}}
[[Image:Kosovo02.png|thumb|Kosovo Vilayet, 1875-1878.]]
The Ottoman conquest of Kosovo was a major achievement for the Turks, as the Kosovar rich minerals would prove a great asset to their empire. The establishment of Ottoman institutions in Kosovo brought about a new era. Heavy religiously-selective taxation and education of the Kosovar aristocracy in Ottoman schools led to a mass conversion of the Christian population into [[Islam]]. The new religion was embraced by approximately two-thirds of the Albanians and a portion of the Slavs. While it slightly improved their status by ruling out threats of annihilation, it did not eliminate the struggle against the Ottoman regime.&lt;ref&gt;Ferid Duka, &quot;Ndryshime në strukturën fetare të popullit shqiptar,&quot; ''Historia e popullit shqiptar: për shkollat e mesme'' (Libri Shkollor: Prishtinë, 2002) 117-118.&lt;/ref&gt;

Kosovo was a typical redoubt of defiant people who fought against the new regime in quest for their national liberty. As a result, many Albanian highlanders retained some autonomy and were allowed to apply their customary law (mainly the [[Kanun|Kanun of Lekë Dukagjini]]). Nevertheless, examples of Ottoman attempts to give an end to this practice are abundant; the heroine Nora of the Kelmendi clan earned a distinguished place in Kosovar history by assassinating the Ottoman leader in Kosovo.&lt;ref&gt;Ferid Duka, &quot;Lufta çlirimtare kundër sundimit osman (shek. XVI-XVII),&quot; ''Historia e popullit shqiptar: për shkollat e mesme'' (Libri Shkollor: Prishtinë, 2002) 111.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the Ottoman period, nonetheless, there was recorded a great amount of endeavors to promote the Albanian language and culture. The Catholic cleric who authored the earliest known Albanian book, [[Gjon Buzuku]], is believed to have been of Kosovar origin. Moreover, the Catholic bishop, [[Pjetër Bogdani]], a native of Kosovo, published his classic ''Band of the Prophets'' in 1686, and later headed the anti-Ottoman movement. His engagement in the national cause culminated in 1689, when he raised a 20,000-member army comprised of Christian and Muslim Albanians, who joined the Austrians in their war against Turkey. The campaign resulted in a brief liberation of Kosovo, but after a plague breakout among Austrians and Kosovars, the Turks soon recovered all their lost areas. Bogdani himself died in December 1689, while his remains were inhumanely exhumed by Turks and Tatars and fed to dogs.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.albanianliterature.net/authors1/AA1-01.html Pjetër Bogdani, biography by R. Elsie, ''Albanian Literature'']&lt;/ref&gt; The loss had a negative impact on the wellbeing all inhabitants of Kosovo, whose liberation was not realized in an 18th-century Austrian endeavor either.

===Albanian national movement===
 
The Albanian national movement was inspired by various reasons. Besides from the National Renaissance that had been promoted by Albanian activists, political reasons were a contributing factor. In the 1870s the Ottoman Empire experienced a tremendous contraction in territory and defeats in wars against Slavic monarchies of Europe. During the 1877–1878 Russo-Turkish war, the Serbian troops invaded the northeastern part of the province of Kosovo [[Albanian exodus|deporting]] 160,000 ethnic Albanians from 640 localities. Furthermore, the signing of the [[Treaty of San Stefano]] marked the beginning of a difficult situation for the Albanian people in the Balkans, whose lands were to be ceded from Turkey to Serbia, Montenegro and Bulgaria.&lt;ref&gt;Hysni Myzyri, &quot;Kriza lindore e viteve 70 dhe rreziku i copëtimit të tokave shqiptare,&quot; ''Historia e popullit shqiptar: për shkollat e mesme'' (Libri Shkollor: Prishtinë, 2002) 151.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; [http://historia.shqiperia.com/rilindja/kreu_5.php Historia e Shqipërisë, “Kreu V: Lidhja Shqiptare e Prizrenit,” ''Shqiperia.com'']&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/reports/2001/kosovo/undword-11A.html HRW, &quot; Prizren Municipality,&quot; ''UNDER ORDERS: War Crimes in Kosovo'']&lt;/ref&gt;

Fearing the partitioning of Albanian-inhabited lands among the newly founded Balkan kingdoms, the Albanians established their [[League of Prizren]] on [[June 10]], [[1878]], three days prior to the Congress of Berlin that would revise the decisions of San Stefano.&lt;ref&gt;Г. Л. Арш, И. Г. Сенкевич, Н. Д. Смирнова «Кратая история Албании» (Приштина: Рилиндя, 1967) 104-116.&lt;/ref&gt; Though the League was founded with the support of the Sultan who hoped for the preservation of Ottoman territories, the Albanian leaders were quick and effective enough to turn it into a national organization and eventually into a government. The League had the backing of the [[Arbëreshë|Italo-Albanian]] community and had well developed into a unifying factor for the religiously-diverse Albanian people. During its three years of existence the League sought the creation of an Albanian autonomous state within the Ottoman Empire, raised an army and fought a defensive war. In 1881 a provisional government was formed to administer Albania under the presidency of [[Ymer Prizreni]], assisted by prominent ministers such as [[Abdyl Frashëri]] and [[Sulejman Vokshi]]. Nevertheless, military intervention from the Balkan states, the Great Powers as well as Turkey divided the Albanian troops in three fronts, which brought about the end of the League.&lt;ref&gt;Hysni Myzyri, &quot;Kreu VIII: Lidhja Shqiptare e Prizrenit (1878-1881),&quot; ''Historia e popullit shqiptar: për shkollat e mesme'' (Libri Shkollor: Prishtinë, 2002) 149-172.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; [http://historia.shqiperia.com/rilindja/kreu_5.php Historia e Shqipërisë, “Kreu V: Lidhja Shqiptare e Prizrenit” Shqiperia.com]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Г. Л. Арш, И. Г. Сенкевич, Н. Д. Смирнова «Кратая история Албании» (Приштина: Рилиндя, 1967) 104-116.&lt;/ref&gt;

Kosovo was yet home to other Albanian organizations, the most important being the [[League of Peja]], named after the city in which it was founded in 1899. It was led by [[Haxhi Zeka]], a former member of the League of Prizren and shared a similar platform in quest for an autonomous Albania. The League ended its activity in 1900 after an armed conflict with the Ottoman forces. Zeka was assassinated by a Serbian agent in 1902 with the backing of the Ottoman authorities.&lt;ref&gt;Hysni Myzyri, &quot;Kreu VIII: Lidhja Shqiptare e Prizrenit (1878-1881),&quot; ''Historia e popullit shqiptar: për shkollat e mesme'' (Libri Shkollor: Prishtinë, 2002) 182-185.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Independence of Albania and the Balkan Wars===
The demands of the [[Young Turks]] in early 20th century sparked support from the Albanians, who were hoping for a betterment of their national status, primarily recognition of their language for use in offices and education.&lt;ref&gt;Hysni Myzyri, &quot;Lëvizja kombëtare shqiptare dhe turqit e rinj,&quot; ''Historia e popullit shqiptar: për shkollat e mesme'' (Libri Shkollor: Prishtinë, 2002) 191.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Г. Л. Арш, И. Г. Сенкевич, Н. Д. Смирнова «Кратая история Албании» (Приштина: Рилиндя, 1967) 140-160.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1908, 20,000 armed Albanian peasants gathered in [[Ferizaj]] to prevent any foreign intervention, while their leaders, [[Bajram Curri]] and [[Isa Boletini]], sent a telegram to the sultan demanding the promulgation of a constitution and the opening of the parliament.
The Albanians did not receive any of the promised benefits from the Young Turkish victory. Considering this, an unsuccessful uprising was organized by Albanian highlanders in Kosovo in February 1909. The adversity escalated after the takeover of the Turkish government by an oligarchic group later that year. In April 1910, armies led by [[Idriz Seferi]] and Isa Boletini rebelled against the Turkish troops, but were finally forced to withdraw after having caused many casualties amongst the enemy.&lt;ref&gt;Hysni Myzyri, &quot;Kryengritjet shqiptare të viteve 1909-1911,&quot; ''Historia e popullit shqiptar: për shkollat e mesme'' (Libri Shkollor: Prishtinë, 2002) 195-198.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Refimprove|section|date=February 2008}}

[[Image:Balkan Wars Boundaries.jpg|thumb|Boundaries on the Balkans after the [[First Balkan War|First]] and [[Second Balkan War]].]]

In [[1912]], during the [[Balkan Wars]], most of Kosovo was taken by the [[History of Serbia|Kingdom of Serbia]], while the region of [[Metohija]] ([[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Dukagjini Valley'') was taken by the [[History of Montenegro|Kingdom of Montenegro]]. An exodus of the local Albanian population occurred. This was described by [[Leon Trotsky]], who was a reporter for the ''Pravda'' newspaper at the time. The Serbian authorities planned a recolonization of Kosovo.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.elsie.de/pdf/B2002GatheringClouds.pdf Elsie, R. (ed.) (2002): &quot;''Gathering Clouds. The roots of ethnic cleansing in Kosovo. Early twentieth-century documents''&quot;]. Dukagjini Balkan Books, Peja (Kosovo, Serbia). ISBN 9951-05-016-6&lt;/ref&gt; Numerous colonist Serb families moved into Kosovo, equalizing the demographic balance between Albanians and Serbs. Many Albanians fled into the mountains, and numerous Albanian and Turkish houses were razed. The reconquest of Kosovo was described as retribution for the 1389 [[Battle of Kossovo]]. At the Conference of Ambassadors in London in 1912, presided over by British Foreign Secretary Sir Edward Grey, the Kingdoms of Serbia and Montenegro were granted sovereignty over Kosovo.{{Fact|date=February 2008}}

==== World War I ====
In the winter of [[1915]]-[[1916]], during [[World War I]], Kosovo saw a large exodus of the Serbian army, which became known as the ''Great Serbian Retreat''. Defeated and worn out in battles against [[Austro-Hungarians]], they had no other choice than to retreat, as Kosovo was occupied by [[Third Bulgarian Empire|Bulgarians]] and Austro-Hungarians. The Albanians joined and supported the [[Central Powers]]. As opposed to Serbian schools, numerous Albanian schools were opened during the 'occupation' (the majority Albanian population considered it a liberation). Allied ships were awaiting Serbian people and soldiers at the banks of the Adriatic sea, and the path leading them there went across Kosovo and Albania. Tens of thousands of soldiers died of starvation, extreme weather and Albanian reprisals{{Fact|date=February 2008}} as they were approaching the Allies in [[Corfu]] and [[Thessaloniki]], amassing a total of 100,000 dead retreaters.{{Fact|date=February 2008}} Transported away from the front lines, the Serbian army managed to treat many wounded and ill soldiers and get some rest. Refreshed and regrouped, it decided to return to the battlefield. In 1918, the Serbian Army pushed the Central Powers out of Kosovo. During Serbian control of Kosovo, the Serbian Army committed atrocities against the population in revenge.{{Fact|date=December 2007}} Serbian Kosovo was unified with Montenegrin Metohija, as Montenegro subsequently joined the Kingdom of Serbia. After World War I ended, the Monarchy was then transformed into the [[Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenians]] (Serbo-Croatian: ''Kraljevina Srba, Hrvata i Slovenaca'', Albanian: ''Mbretëria Serbe, Kroate, Sllovene'') on [[1 December]] [[1918]], gathering territories gained in victory.{{Fact|date=February 2008}}

==== Kingdom of Yugoslavia and World War II ====
The 1918&amp;ndash;1929 period of the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenians witnessed a rise of the Serbian population in the region and a decline in the non-Serbian population. Within the Kingdom, Kosovo was split into four counties, three being a part of the entity of Serbia: Zvečan, Kosovo and southern Metohija; and one of Montenegro: northern Metohija. However, the new administration system since [[26 April]] [[1922]] split Kosovo among three Areas of the Kingdom: Kosovo, [[Rascia]] and [[Zeta]]. In 1921 the Albanian elite lodged an official protest of the government to the League of Nations, claiming that 12,000 Albanians had been killed and over 22,000 imprisoned since 1918, and seeking a [[Greater Albania|unification of Albanian-populated lands]]. As a result, an armed ''Kachak'' resistance movement was formed, whose main goal was to unite Albanian-populated areas of the Kingdom with Albania.{{Fact|date=February 2008}} 

In 1929, the Kingdom was transformed into the [[Kingdom of Yugoslavia]] and the territories of Kosovo were reorganised among the [[Zeta Banovina|Banate of Zeta]], the [[Morava Banovina|Banate of Morava]] and the [[Vardar Banovina|Banate of Vardar]]. The Kingdom of Yugoslavia lasted until the [[World War II]] [[Axis powers|Axis]] invasion of 1941.{{Fact|date=February 2008}} 

The greater part of Kosovo became a part of [[Italy|Italian]]-controlled Fascist Albania, and smaller bits by the [[Greater Bulgaria|Tsardom of Bulgaria]] and [[Nazism|Nazi]] [[Germany|German]]-occupied Kingdom of Serbia. During the fascist occupation of Kosovo by Albanians, until [[August]] [[1941]] alone, over 10,000 Serbs were killed and between 80,000 and 100,000 Serbs were expelled, while roughly the same number of Albanians from Albania were brought to settle in these Serbian lands.&lt;ref&gt;Krizman, Serge. &quot;Massacre of the innocent Serbian population, committed in Yugoslavia by the Axis and its Satellite from April 1941 to August 1941&quot;. Map. ''Maps of Yugoslavia at War'', Washington, [[1943]].&lt;/ref&gt;

Mustafa Kruja, the Prime Minister of Albania, was in Kosovo in June 1942, and at a meeting with the Albanian leaders of Kosovo, said: &quot;''We should endeavor to ensure that the Serb population of Kosovo be – the area be cleansed of them and all Serbs who had been living there for centuries should be termed colonialists and sent to concentration camps in Albania. The Serb settlers should be killed.''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Bogdanović, Dimitrije. &quot;The Book on Kosovo&quot;. 1990. Belgrade: ''Serbian Academy of Sciences and Arts'', 1985. page 2428.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Genfer, Der Kosovo-Konflikt, [[Munich]]: Wieser, [[2000]]. page 158.&lt;/ref&gt;

Prior to the surrender of [[History of Italy|Fascist Italy]] in [[1943]], German forces took over direct control of the region. Following numerous uprisings of [[Partisans]] led by [[Fadil Hoxha]], Kosovo was liberated beginning in [[1944]] with the help of the Albanian partisans of the [[Comintern]], and became a province of Serbia within the [[Yugoslavia|Democratic Federal Yugoslavia]].

==== Kosovo in the Second Yugoslavia ====
{{main|Autonomous Province of Kosovo and Metohija (1946-1974)|Socialist Autonomous Province of Kosovo}}
[[Image:SAP Kosovo.png|thumb|Socialist Autonomous Province of Kosovo of [[Socialist Republic of Serbia|Socialist Serbia]] inside [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Socialist Yugoslavia]], 1974-1990]]

The province was first formed in 1945 as the Autonomous Kosovo-Metohian Area to protect its regional Albanian majority within the [[History of Serbia|People's Republic of Serbia]] as a member of the [[SFRJ|Federal People's Republic of Yugoslavia]] under the leadership of the former Partisan leader, [[Josip Broz Tito]], but with no actual autonomy. After Yugoslavia's name change to the [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia]] and Serbia's to the [[History of Serbia|Socialist Republic of Serbia]] in [[1953]], Kosovo gained internal autonomy in the 1960s.

Tito pursued a policy of weakening Serbia, as he believed that a &quot;Weak Serbia equals a strong Yugoslavia&quot;. In the [[1974]] constitution, the [[Socialist Autonomous Province of Kosovo]]'s government received higher powers, including the highest governmental titles — President and Prime Minister - and a seat in the Federal Presidency, which made it a ''de facto'' Socialist Republic within the Federation, but remaining a Socialist Autonomous Province within the Socialist Republic of Serbia. (Similar rights were extended to [[Vojvodina]]. In Kosovo, [[Serbo-Croatian]], [[Albanian language|Albanian]] and [[Turkish language|Turkish]] were defined as official languages on the provincial level. 

In the 1970s, an Albanian nationalist movement pursued full recognition as a Republic within the Yugoslav Federation, while extreme elements aimed for full-scale independence. &lt;!-- Tito's regime dealt with the situation swiftly, but only giving it a temporary solution. What does this mean? --&gt; The ethnic balance of Kosovo tilted as the number of Albanians tripled, rising from almost 75% to over 90%, but the number of Serbs barely increased, dropping from 15% to 8% of the total population. Even though Kosovo was the least developed area of the former Yugoslavia, the living and economic prospects and freedoms were far greater than under the totalitarian [[Enver Hoxha|Hoxha]] regime in Albania.

Beginning in March [[1981]], Kosovar Albanian students organized protests seeking that Kosovo become a republic within Yugoslavia. Those protests rapidly escalated into violent riots &quot;involving 20,000 people in six cities&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt19810419&quot;&gt;New York Times 1981-04-19, &quot;One Storm has Passed but Others are Gathering in Yugoslavia&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; that were harshly contained by the Yugoslav government. During the 1980s, ethnic tensions continued, with frequent violent outbreaks against Serbs and Yugoslav state authorities, resulting in increased emigration of Kosovo Serbs and other ethnic groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;reuters19860527&quot;&gt;Reuters 1986-05-27, &quot;Kosovo Province Revives Yugoslavia's Ethnic Nightmare&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;csm19860728&quot;&gt;Christian Science Monitor 1986-07-28, &quot;Tensions among ethnic groups in Yugoslavia begin to boil over&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The Yugoslav leadership tried to suppress protests of Kosovo Serbs seeking protection from ethnic discrimination and violence.&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt19870627&quot;&gt;New York Times 1987-06-27, &quot;Belgrade Battles Kosovo Serbs&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[1986]], the Serbian Academy of Sciences and Arts (SANU) was working on a document that later would be known as the [[SANU Memorandum]], a warning to the Serbian President and Assembly of the existing crisis and where it would lead. An unfinished edition was filtered to the press. In the essay, SANU criticised the state of Yugoslavia, and made remarks that the only member state contributing at the time to the development of Kosovo and Macedonia (by then, the poorest territories of the Federation) was Serbia. According to SANU, Yugoslavia was suffering from ethnic strife and the disintegration of the Yugoslav economy into separate economic sectors and territories, which was transforming the federal state into a loose confederation.&lt;ref&gt;SANU (1986): [http://www.balkan-archive.org.yu/kosta/memorandum/contents.html Serbian Academy of Sciences and Arts Memorandum]. GIP Kultura. Belgrade.&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, some think that [[Slobodan Milošević]] used the discontent reflected in the SANU memorandum for his own political goals, during his rise to power in Serbia at the time.

==== Kosovo and the breakup of Yugoslavia ====
Inter-ethnic tensions continued to worsen in Kosovo throughout the 1980s. In particular, Kosovo's ethnic Serb community, a minority of Kosovo's population, complained about mistreatment from the Albanian majority.  Miloševic capitalized on this discontent to consolidate his own position in Serbia.  Milošević was sent by Ivan Stabolić to meet with local leaders, because the local Serbs were threatening to organize a demonstration in Belgrade.&lt;ref&gt;The Serbs Tim Judah p162&lt;/ref&gt; However, a large demonstration of Serbian nationalists had been organized to coincide with Milošević's arrival.  When the demonstrators broke through the police cordon, the police got out their batons and the situation began to get ugly. At this point, Milošević went to a window and and declared &quot;Nobody must ever again dare to beat these people.&quot;  Afterwards, he agreed to listen to representatives of the Serbs who aired their grievances; this continued until the next morning. &lt;ref&gt;Yugoslavia's Ethnic Nightmare. Ed Jasminka Udovićka and James Ridgeway p82&lt;/ref&gt; From this moment on, Milošević used the issue of Kosovo in his rise to power.&lt;ref&gt;The Serbs Tim Judah p162&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 28, 1989, Milošević delivered a speech in front of a large number of Serb citizens at the main celebration marking the 600th anniversary of the [[Battle of Kosovo]], held at [[Gazimestan]]. Many think that this speech helped Milošević consolidate his authority in Serbia.&lt;ref&gt;''The Economist'', June 05, 1999, U.S. Edition, 1041 words, &quot;What's next for Slobodan Milošević?&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1989, Milošević, employing a mix of intimidation and political maneuvering, drastically reduced Kosovo's special autonomous status within Serbia. Soon thereafter, Kosovo Albanians organized a non-violent separatist movement, employing widespread civil disobedience, with the ultimate goal of achieving the independence of Kosovo.  Kosovo Albanians boycotted state institutions and elections and established separate Albanian schools and political institutions. On [[July 2]] [[1990]], an unconstitutional Kosovo parliament declared Kosovo an independent country, although this was not recognized by Belgrade or any foreign states. Two years later, in 1992, the parliament organized an unofficial referendum that was observed by international organizations, but was not recognized internationally. With an ''80%'' turnout, ''98%'' voted for Kosovo to be independent.{{Fact|date=February 2008}}

==== The 1990s ====
{{main|Autonomous Province of Kosovo and Metohija (1990-1999)|Republic of Kosova (1990–2000)|Kosovo War}}

The '''Republic of Kosova''' (Albanian: ''Republika e Kosovë'') was a [[secessionist]] state proclaimed in 1991 by a parallel parliament representing the [[Ethnic Albanian]] population of Kosovo. During its peak it established its own parallel political institutions in opposition to the [[Serb]]-dominated institutions of the [[Autonomous Province of Kosovo and Metohija]].  The Republic of Kosova was formally disbanded in 2000 when its institutions were replaced by the [[Joint Interim Administrative Structure]] established by the [[United Nations Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo]] (UNMIK). During its lifetime, the Republic of Kosova was only recognized by [[Albania]].

The [[Kosovo War]] was a conflict between [[Serbs|Serbian]] and [[Yugoslavia|Yugoslav]] security forces and the [[Kosovo Liberation Army]] (KLA), an ethnic [[Albanians|Albanian]] guerilla group, supported by [[NATO]] and the Islamic [[mujahideen]] seeking secession from the former Yugoslavia.

In 1998 western interest increased and the Serbian authorities were forced to sign a unilateral cease-fire and partial retreat. Under an agreement devised by [[Richard Holbrooke]], [[OSCE]] observers moved into Kosovo to monitor the ceasefire, while Yugoslav military forces partly pulled out of Kosovo. However, the ceasefire was systematically broken shortly thereafter by KLA forces, which again provoked harsh counterattacks by the Serbs. 
[[1999 NATO bombing of the Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|NATO intervention]] between [[March 24]] and [[June 10]] [[1999]],&lt;ref name=&quot;nato1&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.nato.int/kosovo/all-frce.htm| title=Operation Allied Force| publisher=[[NATO]]| date=2006-05-26| accessdate=2008-02-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; combined with continued skirmishes between Albanian guerrillas and Yugoslav forces resulted in a massive displacement of population in Kosovo.&lt;ref name=&quot;unhcr1&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.unhcr.org/partners/PARTNERS/3bb051c54.pdf| title=NATO and Humanitarian Action in the Kosovo Crisis| author=Larry Minear, Ted van Baarda, Marc Sommers| year=2000| publisher=[[Brown University]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
During the conflict 850 000 ethnic Albanians fled or were forcefully driven from Kosovo, several thousand were killed (the numbers and the ethnic distribution of the casualties are uncertain and highly disputed). An alleged 12,000-18,000 ethnic Albanians&lt;ref name=&quot;observer1&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/interactive/2008/feb/15/kosovo| title=Kosovo independence| work=The Observer| publisher=Guardian News and Media| date=2008-02-15| accessdate=2008-02-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; and 3,000 Serbs are believed to have been killed during the conflict.According to uncorroborated media report up to 20,000 Kosovo Albanian women were allegedly raped during the Kosovo carnage.&lt;ref name=&quot;observer2&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2000/apr/16/balkans| title=Rape victims' babies pay the price of war| work=The Observer| publisher=Guardian News and Media| date=2000-04-16| accessdate=2008-02-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; 3,368 people are still missing, of which 2,500 are Albanian, 400 Serbs and 100 Roma.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbcnews&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/781310.stm| title=3,000 missing in Kosovo| publisher=BBC News| date=2000-06-07| accessdate=2008-02-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Recent history (1999 to present) ===
{{main|Kosovo (UNMIK)|Kosovo status process}}

After the war ended, the UN Security Council passed Resolution 1244 that placed Kosovo under transitional UN administration ([[UNMIK]]) and authorized [[Kosovo Force|KFOR]], a NATO-led peacekeeping force. Resolution 1244 also delivered that Kosovo will have autonomy within Federal Republic of Yugoslavia&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first= | last= | coauthors= | title=RESOLUTION 1244 (1999) | date=[[1999-06-17]] | publisher=BBC News | url =http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/371562.stm | work = | pages = | accessdate = 2008-02-19 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt; (today legal successor of  Federal Republic of Yugoslavia is Republic of Serbia). 
 
In 2001, UNMIK promulgated a Constitutional Framework for Kosovo that established the [[Provisional Institutions of Self-Government]] (PISG), including an elected Kosovo Assembly, Presidency and office of Prime Minister.  Kosovo held its first free, Kosovo-wide elections in late 2001 (municipal elections had been held the previous year).

In March 2004, Kosovo experienced its worst inter-ethnic violence since the Kosovo War.  The [[2004 unrest in Kosovo|unrest in 2004]] was sparked by a series of minor events that soon cascaded into large-scale attack on Serb life and property. &lt;ref&gt;U.S State Department Report, published in 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
 
International negotiations began in 2006 to determine the final status of Kosovo, as envisaged under [[UN Security Council Resolution 1244]].  The [[UN]]-backed talks, lead by UN Special Envoy [[Martti Ahtisaari]], began in February 2006. Whilst progress was made on technical matters, both parties remained diametrically opposed on the question of status itself.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/6034567.stm UN frustrated by Kosovo deadlock] &quot;, ''BBC News'', October 9, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; 

In February 2007, Ahtisaari delivered a draft status settlement proposal to leaders in Belgrade and Pristina, the basis for a draft UN Security Council Resolution which proposes 'supervised independence' for the province. A draft resolution, backed by the [[United States]], the [[United Kingdom]] and other European members of the [[Security Council]], was presented and rewritten four times to try to accommodate Russian concerns that such a resolution would undermine the principle of state sovereignty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.setimes.com/cocoon/setimes/xhtml/en_GB/newsbriefs/setimes/newsbriefs/2007/06/29/nb-07 |title=Russia reportedly rejects fourth draft resolution on Kosovo status |author=Southeast European Times |date=29/06/2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Russia, which holds a veto in the Security Council as one of five permanent members, had stated that it would not support any resolution which was not acceptable to both Belgrade and Kosovo Albanians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.setimes.com/cocoon/setimes/xhtml/en_GB/newsbriefs/setimes/newsbriefs/2007/07/10/nb-02 |title=UN Security Council remains divided on Kosovo |author=Southeast European Times |date=09/07/07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Whilst most observers had, at the beginning of the talks, anticipated independence as the most likely outcome, others have suggested that a rapid resolution might not be preferable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/985caa90-de5a-11db-afa7-000b5df10621.html?nclick_check=1 |title=A long reconciliation process is required |author=James Dancer |date=30/03/07 |publisher=Financial Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After many weeks of discussions at the UN, the [[United States]], [[United Kingdom]] and other European members of the Security Council formally 'discarded' a draft resolution backing Ahtisaari's proposal on [[20 July]] [[2007]], having failed to secure Russian backing. Beginning in August, a &quot;[[Troika (triumvirate)|Troika]]&quot; consisting of negotiators from the [[European Union]] (Wolfgang Ischinger), the [[United States]] (Frank Wisner)  and [[Russia]] (Alexander Botsan-Kharchenko) launched a new effort to reach a status outcome acceptable to both Belgrade and Pristina.  Despite Russian disapproval, the [[U.S.]], [[United Kingdom|Britain]], and [[France]] appeared likely to recognize Kosovar independence&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/international/story/0,,2209907,00.html |title=Bosnian nightmare returns to haunt EU |author=Simon Tisdall |date=13/11/07 |publisher=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt;. A declaration of independence by Kosovar Albanian leaders was postponed until the end of the Serbian presidential elections (4 February 2008). Most EU members and the US had feared that a premature declaration could boost support in Serbia for the ultra-nationalist candidate, Tomislav Nikolic.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/6386467.stm&lt;/ref&gt;

====Declaration of Independence====
{{main|2008 Kosovo declaration of independence|International reaction to the 2008 Kosovo declaration of independence}}
The [[Assembly of Kosovo|Kosovar Assembly]] approved a declaration of independence on [[17 February]] [[2008]].&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc_proclaim&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/7249034.stm Kosovo MPs proclaim independence]&quot;, BBC News Online, [[17 February]] [[2008]]&lt;/ref&gt; In a following day several countries ([[United States]], [[Turkey]], [[Albania]], [[Austria]], [[Germany]], [[Italy]], [[France]], [[United Kingdom]], [[Australia]], etc.) announced their recognition, despite protests by [[Serbia]] in the [[UN Security Council]].&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc=recog1&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/7251359.stm Recognition for new Kosovo grows]&quot;, BBC News Online, [[18 February]] [[2008]]&lt;/ref&gt; Some countries are either undetermined, or will not recognize independence of Kosovo due to internal interests, or so as not to damage relations with Serbia, or for other reasons.  Most of the these countries are located in the region ([[Croatia]], [[Republic of Macedonia]], [[Bosnia-Herzegovina]], [[Romania]], [[Greece]]), but others are more remote ([[Russia]], [[Spain]], [[Slovakia]], [[Moldavia]], [[South Africa]] Thailand, Argentina, Sri Lanka, and others).

== Geography ==
{{main|Geography of Kosovo}}
[[Image:UTkosovo rel small 92.jpg|thumb|Physical map of Kosovo]]
Kosovo has an area of 10,887 [[square kilometers]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.kosovo-mining.org/kosovoweb/en/home.html |title=Welcome to the Independent Commission for Mines and Minerals (ICMM), Kosovo |author=Independent Commission for Mines and Minerals}}&lt;/ref&gt; (4,203 [[square mile|sq&amp;nbsp;mi]]) and a population of about 2.2 million. The largest cities are [[Priština]], the capital, with an estimated 170,000 inhabitants, [[Prizren]] in the south west with a population of 110,000, [[Peć]] in the west with 70,000, and [[Kosovska Mitrovica]] in the north with 70,000.

The climate in Kosovo is continental, with warm summers and cold and snowy winters. There are two main plains in Kosovo. The [[Metohija]] basin is located in the western part of the Kosovo, and the Plain of Kosovo occupies the eastern part.

Much of Kosovo's terrain is mountainous. The [[Šar Mountains]] are located in the south and south-east, bordering the [[Republic of Macedonia]]. This is one of the region's most popular tourist and skiing resorts, with [[Brezovica, Serbia|Brezovica]] and Prevalac as the main tourist centers. Kosovo's mountainous area, including the highest peak [[Đeravica]], at 2656&amp;nbsp;m above sea level, is located in the south-west, bordering Montenegro and Albania. 

The [[Kopaonik]] mountains are located in the north. The central region of [[Drenica]], [[Crnoljeva]] and the eastern part of Kosovo, known as [[Goljak]], are mainly hilly areas. There are several notable rivers and lakes in Kosovo. The main rivers are the [[White Drin]], running towards the [[Adriatic Sea]], with the [[Erenik]] among its [[Tributary|tributaries]]), the [[Sitnica]], the [[South Morava]] in the Goljak area, and [[IbriRiver|Ibar]] in the north. The main lakes are Gazivoda (380 million m³) in the north-western part, Radonjić (113 million m³) in the south-west part, Batlava (40 million m³) and Badovac (26 million m³) in the north-east part.

[[Image:Prishtina maj 2005.jpg|thumb|[[Priština]]]]
[[Image:BoroRamizi.jpg|thumb|Priština]]
List of largest cities in Kosovo (with population figures for [[2003-12-31]]):&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.citypopulation.de/Kosovo.html |title=Kosovo |author=City Population}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Priština]] (Prishtina): 165,844
*[[Prizren]] : 107,614
*[[Uroševac]] (Ferizaj) : 71,758
*[[Kosovska Mitrovica]] : 68,929
*[[Đakovica]] (Gjakova) : 68,645
*[[Peć]] (Peja) : 68,551
*[[Gnjilane]] (Gjilan): 55,781
*[[Vučitrn]] (Vushtrri) : 39,642
*[[Podujevo]] : 37,203

==Politics and governance==
{{main|Politics of Kosovo}}
{{seealso|United Nations Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo|Provisional Institutions of Self-Government}}
[[Image:Dardania_small.jpg|thumb|The former President of Kosovo, Ibrahim Rugova,  with the &quot;Dardania flag&quot; and Albanian national flag]]
{{Politics of Kosovo}}
In 1999, [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 1244|UN Security Council Resolution 1244]] placed Kosovo under transitional UN administration pending a determination of Kosovo's future status. This Resolution entrusted the [[United Nations Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo]] (UNMIK) with sweeping powers to govern Kosovo, but also directed UNMIK to establish interim institutions of self-governance. Resolution 1244 permits Serbia no role in governing Kosovo and since 1999 Serbian laws and institutions have not been valid in Kosovo. NATO has a separate mandate to provide for a safe and secure environment.

In May 2001, UNMIK promulgated the Constitutional Framework, which established Kosovo's [[Provisional Institutions of Self-Government]] (PISG). The PISG replaced the [[Joint Interim Administrative Structure]] (JIAS) established a year earlier. Since 2001, UNMIK has been gradually transferring increased governing competencies to the PISG, while reserving some powers that are normally carried out by sovereign states, such as foreign affairs. Kosovo has also established municipal government and an internationally-supervised Kosovo Police Service.

According to the Constitutional Framework, Kosovo shall have a 120-member Kosovo Assembly. The Assembly includes twenty reserved seats: ten for Kosovo Serbs and ten for non-Serb minorities (Bosniaks, Roma, etc). The Kosovo Assembly is responsible for electing a President and Prime Minister of Kosovo.

The largest political party in Kosovo, the Democratic League of Kosovo (LDK), has its origins in the 1990s non-violent resistance movement to Miloševic's rule. The party was led by Ibrahim Rugova until his death in 2006. The two next largest parties have their roots in the Kosovo Liberation Army (KLA): the Democratic Party of Kosovo (PDK) led by former KLA leader Hashim Thaci and the Alliance for the Future of Kosovo (AAK) led by former KLA commander Ramush Haradinaj. Kosovo publisher Veton Surroi formed his own political party in 2004 named &quot;Ora.&quot; Kosovo Serbs formed the Serb List for Kosovo and Metohija (SLKM) in 2004, but have boycotted Kosovo's institutions and never taken their seats in the Kosovo Assembly.

In November 2001, the [[OSCE]] supervised the first elections for the Kosovo Assembly. After that election, Kosovo's political parties formed an all-party unity coalition and elected [[Ibrahim Rugova]] as President and Bajram Rexhepi (PDK) as Prime Minister.

After Kosovo-wide elections in October 2004, the LDK and AAK formed a new governing coalition that did not include PDK and Ora. This coalition agreement resulted in [[Ramush Haradinaj]] (AAK) becoming Prime Minister, while Ibrahim Rugova retained the position of President. PDK and Ora were critical of the coalition agreement and have since frequently accused the current government of corruption.

[[Image:Coat_of_arms_of_the_PISG_of_Kosovo.svg|thumb|100px|left|The [[Approved logo of the Provisional Institutions of Self-Government|Approved Logo]] of the [[Provisional Institutions of Self-Government]]]]
Ramush Haradinaj resigned the post of Prime Minister after he was indicted for war crimes by the International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia (ICTY) in March 2005. He was replaced by Bajram Kosumi (AAK). But in a political shake-up after the death of President Rugova in January 2006, Kosumi himself was replaced by former Kosovo Protection Corps commander [[Agim Ceku]]. Ceku has won recognition for his outreach to minorities, but Serbia has been critical of his wartime past as military leader of the KLA and claims he is still not doing enough for Kosovo Serbs. The Kosovo Assembly elected [[Fatmir Sejdiu]], a former LDK parliamentarian, president after Rugova's death. Slaviša Petkovic, Minister for Communities and Returns, was previously the only ethnic Serb in the government, but resigned in November 2006 amid allegations that he misused ministry funds.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.adnki.com/index_2Level_English.php?cat=Politics&amp;loid=8.0.363650179&amp;par=0 Kosovo: Serb minister resigns over misuse of funds] &quot;, Adnkronos international (AKI), November 27, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.reliefweb.int/rw/RWB.NSF/db900SID/LZEG-6VUQUS?OpenDocument Sole Kosovo Serb cabinet minister resigns: PM] &quot;, Agence France-Presse (AFP), November 24, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Today two of the total thirteen ministries in Kosovo's Government have ministers from the minorities. Branislav Grbic, ethnic Serb, leads Minister of Returns and Sadik Idriz, ethnic Bosnjak, leads Ministry of Health&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ks-gov.net/pm/?menuid=2&amp;subid=20&amp;subs=56&amp;lingo=1 Fillimi&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Kosovan parliamentary election, 2007|Parliamentary elections]] were held on [[17 November]] [[2007]]. After early results, [[Hashim Thaçi]] who was on course to gain 35 per cent of the vote, claimed victory for PDK, the [[Democratic Party of Kosovo|Albanian Democratic Party]], and stated his intention to declare independence. Thaci is likely to form a coalition with current [[Fatmir Sejdiu|President Fatmir Sejdiu]]'s [[Democratic League of Kosovo|Democratic League]] which was in second place with 22 percent of the vote. The turnout at the election was particularly low with most Serbs refusing to vote.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.euronews.net/index.php?page=info&amp;article=454473&amp;lng=1 EuroNews: Ex-guerrilla chief claims victory in Kosovo election]. Retrieved 18 November 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Health ==

Access to health care is free for all residents of Kosovo. Currently there is no health insurance, however, the Ministry of Health is in the process of preparing a legislative infrastructure, which is scheduled to be implemented in 2008.

There are hospitals in all major cities. A total of 6 regional hospitals provide tertiary health care, and family centers in small municipalities.

Medical Education is available at the University Clinical Center of Kosovo (UCCK), in Pristina.

== Economy ==
{{main|Economy of Kosovo}}
[[Image:Kosovo stamp.jpg|thumb|100px|[[Postage stamp]] from Kosovo issued after the 1999 Kosovo War]]
Kosovo has one of the most under-developed economies in Europe, with a per capita income estimated at [[Euro|€]]1,565 (2004).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://web.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/COUNTRIES/ECAEXT/KOSOVOEXTN/0,,contentMDK:20629286~menuPK:297777~pagePK:1497618~piPK:217854~theSitePK:297770,00.html |title=Kosovo Brief 2006 |author=The World Bank |date=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite substantial development subsidies from all Yugoslav republics, Kosovo was the poorest province of Yugoslavia.&lt;ref&gt;Christian Science Monitor 1982-01-15, &quot;Why Turbulent Kosovo has Marble Sidewalks but Troubled Industries&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, over the course of the 1990s a blend of poor economic policies, international sanctions, poor external commerce and ethnic conflict severely damaged the economy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://web.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/COUNTRIES/ECAEXT/KOSOVOEXTN/0,,menuPK:297775~pagePK:141159~piPK:141110~theSitePK:297770,00.html |title=World Bank Mission in Kosovo |author=The World Bank |date=2006/2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kosovo's economy remains weak. After a jump in 2000 and 2001, growth in [[Gross Domestic Product]] (GDP) was negative in 2002 and 2003 and is expected to be around 3 percent 2004-2005, with domestic sources of growth unable to compensate for the declining foreign assistance. [[Inflation]] is low, while the budget posted a deficit for the first time in 2004. Kosovo has high external deficits. In 2004, the deficit of the balance of goods and services was close to 70 percent of GDP. Remittances from Kosovars living abroad accounts for an estimated 13 percent of GDP, and foreign assistance for around 34 percent of GDP.

Most economic development since 1999 has taken place in the trade, retail and the construction sectors. The private sector that has emerged since 1999 is mainly small-scale. The industrial sector remains weak and the electric power supply remains unreliable, acting as a key constraint. Unemployment remains pervasive, at around 40-50% of the labor force.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.eciks.org/english/lajme.php?action=total_news&amp;main_id=386 |title=May finds Kosovo with 50% unemployed |author=eciks |date=04/05/06}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

UNMIK introduced ''de-facto'' an external trade regime and customs administration on [[September 3]], [[1999]] when it set customs border controls in Kosovo. All goods imported in Kosovo face a flat 10% customs duty fee.&lt;ref name=&quot;BuyUSA&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.buyusa.gov/kosovo/en/doingbusinessinkosovo.html |title=Doing Business in Kosovo |author=U.S. Commercial Service}}&lt;/ref&gt; These taxes are collected from all Tax Collection Points installed at the borders of Kosovo, including those between Kosovo and Serbia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.seerecon.org/kosovo/documents/wb_econ_report/wb-kosovo-econreport-2-2.pdf |format=PDF |title=External Trade and Customs |author=Economic Reconstruction and Development in South East Europe}}&lt;/ref&gt; UNMIK and Kosovo institutions have signed Free Trade Agreements with [[Croatia]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.b92.net/eng/news/globe-article.php?yyyy=2006&amp;mm=10&amp;dd=02&amp;nav_category=123&amp;nav_id=37090 |title=Croatia, Kosovo sign Interim Free Trade Agreement |author=B92 |authorlink=B92 |date=02/10/06 |publisher=mrt.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.euinkosovo.org/upload_press/4.06%20-%20UNMIK%20and%20Bosnia%20and%20Herzegovina%20Initial%20Free%20Trade%20Agreement%2017.2.06.pdf |format=PDF |title=UNMIK and Bosnia and Herzegovina Initial Free Trade Agreement |author=EU in Kosovo |date=17/02/06 |publisher=UNMIK}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Albania]] and [[Republic of Macedonia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BuyUSA&quot;/&gt;

The [[Republic of Macedonia]] is Kosovo's largest import and export market (averaging €220 million and €9 million, respectively), followed by Serbia-Montenegro (€111 million and €5 million), Germany and Turkey.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://siteresources.worldbank.org/INTKOSOVO/147270-1121700806276/20953280/Kosovo_Economic_Briefing_april.pdf |format=PDF |title=Kosovo Monthly Economic Briefing: Preparing for next winter |author=The World Bank |date=April 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[euro]] is the official currency of Kosovo and used by UNMIK and the government bodies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.euinkosovo.org/uk/invest/invest.php |title=Invest in Kosovo |author=EU in Kosovo}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Serbian dinar]] is used in the Serbian-populated parts.

The economy is hindered by Kosovo's still-unresolved international status, which has made it difficult to attract investment and loans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/business/4509781.stm |title=Brussels offers first Kosovo loan |author=BBC News |date=03/05/05}}&lt;/ref&gt; The province's economic weakness has produced a thriving black economy in which smuggled petrol, cigarettes and cement are major commodities. The prevalence of official corruption and the pervasive influence of organised crime gangs has caused serious concern internationally. The United Nations has made the fight against corruption and organised crime a high priority, pledging a &quot;zero tolerance&quot; approach.

== Demographics ==
{{main|Demographics of Kosovo}}
[[Image:Kosovo ethnic 2005.png|thumb|Ethnic composition of Kosovo in [[2005]] according to the [[OSCE]]]]
According to the Kosovo in Figures 2005 Survey of the Statistical Office of Kosovo,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ks-gov.net/esk/esk/pdf/english/general/kosovo_figures_05.pdf |format=PDF |title=Kosovo in figures 2005 |author=UNMIK |publisher=Ministry of Public Services}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4385768.stm |title=Muslims in Europe: Country guide |author=BBC News |date=23/12/05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/country_profiles/3524092.stm |title=Regions and territories: Kosovo |author=BBC News |date=20/11/07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kosovo's total population is estimated between 1.9 and 2.2 million in the following ethnic proportions:

* 92% [[Albanians]]
* 4% [[Serbs]]
* 2% [[Bosniaks]] and [[Gorani (ethnic group)|Gorans]]
* 1% [[Roma people|Roma]]
* 1% [[Turkish people|Turks]]

[[Islam]] is the predominant [[religion]], professed by most of the majority ethnic Albanian population, the Bosniak, Gorani, and Turkish communities, and some of the Roma/[[Ashkali]]/[[Egyptians (Balkans)|Egyptian]] community, although religion is not a significant factor in public life. Religious rhetoric was largely absent from public discourse in Muslim communities, mosque attendance was low, and public displays of conservative Islamic dress and culture were minimal. The Serb population, estimated at 100,000 to 120,000 persons, is largely [[Serbian Orthodox]]. Approximately 3 percent of ethnic Albanians are [[Roman Catholic]]. Catholic communities are concentrated around Catholic churches in [[Prizren]], [[Klina]], and [[Gjakova]]. [[Protestant]]s make up less than 1 percent of the population and have small populations in most cities, with the largest concentration located in Pristina. There are no synagogues or [[Jewish]] institutions; there are reportedly two families whose members have Jewish roots. The number of [[atheist]]s or those who do not practice any religion are difficult to determine, and estimates are largely unreliable.
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.crisisgroup.org/home/index.cfm?id=1591&amp;l=1 |title=Religion in Kosovo |author=International Crisis Group |date=31/01/01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2007/90198.htm#kosovo International Religious Freedom Report 2007 (U.S. Department of States) - Serbia (includes Kosovo)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2006/71405.htm#kosovo International Religious Freedom Report 2006 (U.S. Department of States) - Serbia and Montenegro (includes Kosovo)]&lt;/ref&gt;

Ethnic Albanians in Kosovo have the largest population growth in Europe.&lt;ref&gt;[http://files.osa.ceu.hu/holdings/300/8/3/text/3-13-10.shtml Albanian Population Growth]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.srpska-mreza.com/Kosovo/demographic-explosion.html Demographic explosion in Kosovo]&lt;/ref&gt; The people’s growth rate in Kosovo is 1.3%. Over an 82-year period (1921-2003) the population grew 4.6 times. If growth continues at such a pace, based on some estimations, the population will be 4.5 million by 2050.&lt;ref&gt;[http://kosovo-hotels.com/index.php?mod=kos_profile Kosovo-Hotels, Prishtina - Kosova-Hotels, Prishtinë]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Administrative divisions ==
{{main|Subdivisions of Kosovo}}
{{see also|Municipalities of Kosovo}}
Kosovo, for administrative reasons, is considered as consisting of seven districts.
[[North Kosovo]] maintains its own government, infrastructure and institutions by its dominant ethnic [[Serb]] population in the [[Mitrovica District]], viz. in the [[Leposavic]], [[Zvecan]] and [[Zubin Potok]] municipalities and the northern part of [[Kosovska Mitrovica]].

Kosovo is also divided into 30 municipalities :

{{Municipalities of Kosovo}}

== Culture ==
===Music===
{{main|Music of Kosovo}}
{{see|Music of Serbia}}

Although in Kosovo the music is diverse (influenced to an extent by the cultures of the various regimes who controlled the region), authentic Albanian music (see ''[[World Music]]'') and [[Serbian music]] do still exist. Albanian music is characterized by the use of the ''[[çiftelia]]'' (an authentic Albanian instrument), ''mandolin'', ''mandola'' and ''percussion''. In Kosovo, [[folk]] music is very popular alongside modern music. There are a number of folk [[singers]] and ensembles (both Albanian and Serbian). [[European classical music|Classical music]] is also well known in Kosovo and has been taught at [[universities]] (at the [[University of Prishtina#Albanian university|University of Priština Faculty of Arts]]  and the [[University of Pristina#Serbian university|University of Priština at Kosovska Mitrovica]]  [[Faculty of Arts of Priština|Faculty of Arts]]) and several pre-[[college]] [[List of pre-college music schools|music school]]s

There are some notable music festivals in Kosovo:
* ''Rock për Rock'' - contains [[Rock (music)|rock]] and [[Heavy Metal music|metal]] music
* ''Polifest'' - contains all kinds of genres (usually [[Hip hop music|hip hop]] and commercial [[Pop (music)|pop]])
* ''Showfest'' - contains all kinds of genres (usually [[Hip hop music|hip hop]] and commercial [[Pop (music)|pop]])
* ''Videofest'' - contains all kinds of genres
* ''Kush Këndon Lutet Dy Herë'' - contains [[Christian music]]
* ''North City Jazz &amp; Blues festival'', an international [[music festival]] held annually in [[Zvečan]] ({{lang-sq|Zveçani}}), near Kosovska Mitrovica,
Kosovo Radiotelevisions like ''RTK'', ''21'' and ''KTV'' have their musical charts.

===Sport===
Several sports federations have been formed in Kosovo within the framework of Law No. 2003/24 &quot;Law on Sport&quot; passed by the Assembly of Kosovo in 2003. The law formally established a national Olympic Committee, regulated the establishment of sports federations and established guidelines for sports clubs. At present only some of the sports federations established have gained international recognition.

Federations that have so far gained membership or recognition by their international governing body:
* [[Handball Federation of Kosovo]]
* [[Table Tennis Federation of Kosovo]]

Federations that have not yet gained international recognition:
* [[Basketball Federation of Kosovo]]
* [[Football Federation of Kosovo]] and the [[Kosovo national football team]]
* [[Olympic Committee of Kosovo]]
* [[Tennis Federation of Kosovo]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
{{cite book
  | last = Malcolm
  | first = Noel
  | authorlink = Noel Malcolm
  | title = Kosovo: A Short History
  | publisher = [[Harper Perennial]]
  | year = 1999
  | isbn = 0060977752 }}

== See also ==
&lt;div style=&quot;-moz-column-count:4; column-count:4;&quot;&gt;
* [[Assembly of Kosovo]]
* [[Government of Kosovo]]
* [[Prime Minister of Kosovo]]
* [[President of Kosovo]]
* [[Serbs in Kosovo]]
* [[Albanians in Kosovo]]
* [[Post and Telecom of Kosovo]]
* [[National awakening and the birth of Albania]]
* [[Demographic history of Kosovo]]
* [[Unrest in Kosovo|Unrest in Kosovo during March 2004]]
* [[Metohija]]
* [[North Kosovo]]
* [[Flag of Kosovo]]
* [[2008 Kosovo declaration of independence]]
&lt;/div&gt;

==External links==
{{portal|Kosovo|Flag of Kosovo.svg}}
{{sisterlinks}}
* {{wikiatlas|Kosovo}}
* [http://www.unmikonline.org/ United Nations Interim Administration in Kosovo]
* [http://www.ks-gov.net/pm/Fillimi/tabid/36/menuid/+/subid/+/lingo/2/language/en-US/Default.aspx The Government of Kosovo]
* [http://www.srbija.sr.gov.yu/kosovo-metohija/?change_lang=en Serbian Government for Kosovo and Metohija]
* [http://www.visitkosova.org/english/index.htm Visit Kosovo - Tourism Website]
* {{wikitravel}}

{{Template group
|title = Geographic locale
|list  =
{{Kosovo}}
}}
{{Municipalities of the Republic of Kosovo}}
{{Template group
|title = International membership and history
|list  =
{{Central European Free Trade Agreement (CEFTA)}}
{{Republics and autonomous provinces of the former Yugoslavia}}
{{Countries of Europe}}
}}

&lt;!--Categories--&gt;
[[Category:Kosovo]]
[[Category:2008 establishments]]

&lt;!--Other languages--&gt;

[[als:Kosovo]]
[[ang:Kosovo]]
[[ar:كوسوفو]]
[[an:Kosovo]]
[[roa-rup:Cosova]]
[[frp:Kosovo]]
[[ast:Kosovo]]
[[az:Kosovo]]
[[zh-min-nan:Kosovo]]
[[be-x-old:Косава]]
[[bn:কসোভো]]
[[bs:Kosovo]]
[[br:Kosovo]]
[[bg:Косово]]
[[ca:Kosovo]]
[[cv:Косово]]
[[cs:Kosovo]]
[[ny:Kosovo]]
[[cy:Kosovo]]
[[da:Kosovo]]
[[de:Kosovo]]
[[et:Kosovo]]
[[el:Κοσσυφοπέδιο]]
[[es:Kosovo]]
[[eo:Kosovo]]
[[eu:Kosovo]]
[[fa:کوزوو]]
[[fr:Kosovo]]
[[ga:An Chosaiv]]
[[gl:Kosovo]]
[[ko:코소보]]
[[hi:कोसोवो]]
[[hsb:Kosovo]]
[[hr:Kosovo]]
[[io:Kosovo]]
[[id:Kosovo]]
[[is:Kosóvó]]
[[it:Kosovo]]
[[he:קוסובו]]
[[jv:Kosovo]]
[[ka:კოსოვო]]
[[kw:Kosova]]
[[lad:Kosovo]]
[[la:Ager Merulensis]]
[[lv:Kosova]]
[[lt:Kosovas]]
[[li:Kosovo]]
[[hu:Kosovo]]
[[mk:Косово]]
[[ms:Kosovo]]
[[nah:Cosovo]]
[[nl:Kosovo]]
[[ja:コソボ]]
[[no:Kosovo]]
[[nn:Kosovo]]
[[oc:Kosova]]
[[pms:Kòsovo]]
[[nds:Kosovo]]
[[pl:Kosowo]]
[[pt:Kosovo]]
[[ro:Kosova]]
[[qu:Kosovo]]
[[ru:Косово]]
[[sq:Kosova]]
[[simple:Kosovo]]
[[sk:Kosovo]]
[[sl:Kosovo]]
[[sr:Косово и Метохија]]
[[sh:Kosovo i Metohija]]
[[fi:Kosovo]]
[[sv:Kosovo]]
[[ta:கொசோவோ]]
[[th:Kosovo]]
[[vi:Kosovo]]
[[tr:Kosova]]
[[uk:Косово]]
[[ur:کوسووہ]]
[[vec:Kosovo]]
[[zh-yue:科索沃]]
[[diq:Kosova]]
[[zea:Kosovo]]
[[bat-smg:Kuosuovs]]
[[zh:科索沃]]</text>
