      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Kosovo-InfoBox}}
:''For other uses of the name Kosovo, see [[Kosovo (disambiguation)]]. For other uses of the name Kosova, see [[Kosova (disambiguation)]].''

&lt;!-- Please be very careful in editing the introduction of this article. It has been the subject of a lot of discussion on the talk page and has been the target of several revert wars. Please discuss any major changes on the talk page first. --&gt;

'''Kosovo''' ([[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Kosovë'' or ''Kosova''; [[Serbian language|Serbian]]: Косово и Метохија or ''Kosovo i Metohija'', also Космет or ''Kosmet'') is a province in southern [[Serbia]] which has been under [[United Nations]] [[United Nations Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo|administration]] since [[1999]]. While Serbia's nominal [[sovereignty]] is recognised by the international community, in practice Serbian governance in the province is virtually non-existent (''see also [[Constitutional status of Kosovo]]''). The province is governed by the [[United Nations Mission in Kosovo]] (UNMIK) and the local [[Provisional Institutions of Self-Government]], with security provided by the [[NATO]]-led [[Kosovo Force]] (KFOR). 

Kosovo borders [[Montenegro]], [[Albania]] and the [[Republic of Macedonia]]. The mountainous province's capital and largest city is [[Priština]]. Kosovo has a population of around two million people, predominately ethnic [[Albanians]], with smaller populations of [[Serbs]], [[Turkish people|Turks]], [[Bosniaks]] and other ethnic groups.
Karlo  killed mr.man


The province is the subject of a long-running political and territorial dispute between the Serbian (and previously, the [[Yugoslavia|Yugoslav]]) government and Kosovo's Albanian population. International negotiations began in [[2006]] to determine the final status of Kosovo; it is widely expected that the talks will lead to some form of independence.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.economist.com/displaystory.cfm?story_id=4489028 Kosovo's status - the wheels grind on]&quot;, ''The Economist'', October 6, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

''See also [[Names of Kosovo]].''

== Geography ==
''For administrative divisions, see [[Municipalities of Kosovo]]''
[[image:UTkosovo rel small 92.jpg|thumb|left|275px|Physical map of Kosovo]]
With an area of [[1 E10 m²|10,912]] [[square kilometre]]s (4,213 [[square mile|sq.&amp;nbsp;mi]]) and a population of over two million on the eve of the 1999 crisis, Kosovo borders [[Montenegro]] to the northwest, [[Central Serbia]] to the North and East, the [[Republic of Macedonia]] to the south and [[Albania]] to the southwest. The province's present borders were established in [[1945]]. The republic of [[Serbia]] has one other autonomous province, [[Vojvodina]], located in the far north of the country.

The largest cities are [[Pristina]], the capital, with an estimated 600,000 citizens, and [[Prizren]] in the southwest with 120,000 citizens; five other towns have populations in excess of 50,000. The climate in Kosovo is continental with warm summers and cold and snowy winters. .

There are two main plains in Kosovo. The [[Metohija]]/Rrafshi i Dukagjinit basin is located in the western part of the province, and the Plain of Kosovo ([[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Rrafshi i Kosovës'', [[Serbian language|Serbian]]: ''Kosovska Dolina'') occupies the central area.

Much of Kosovo's terrain is rugged. The [[Sar Mountain]] (Albanian: ''Mali i Sharrit'', Serbian: ''Šar Planina'') is located in the south and south-east, bordering [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]]. It is one of the region's most popular tourist and skiing resorts, with [[Brezovica]] and Prevalac/Prevallë as the main tourist centres. Kosovo's mountainous area, including the highest peak Deravica/Gjeravica (2656 m above sea level), is located in the south-west, bordering [[Albania]] and [[Montenegro]]. 

The mountain range dividing Kosovo from Albania is known in English as the [[Cursed Mountains]] or Albanian Alps (Albanian: ''Bjeshkët e Nemuna'', Serbian: ''Prokletije''). The Kopaonik mountain is located in the north, bordering [[Central Serbia]]. The central region of [[Drenica]], Carraleva/Crnoljevo and the eastern part of Kosovo, known as Gallap/Golak, are mainly hilly areas. 

There are several notable rivers and lakes in Kosovo. The main rivers are the [[Drin River]] (Albanian: ''Drini i Bardhë'', Serbian: ''Beli Drin''). Several other waterways flow into it, including the Erenik, and the river runs towards the [[Adriatic Sea]], Sitnica, Morava in the Gollak area and Ibar (Albanian Ibër) in the north. The main lakes are Badovc in the north-east and Gazivoda in the north-western part.

== History ==
{{History of Kosovo}}
{{main|History of Kosovo}}
:''See also: [[Demographic history of Kosovo]]''
=== Ancient ===
The region was certainly inhabited in [[prehistory|prehistoric]] times, it appears, by two different cultures: [[bronze age|Bronze]] and [[Iron Age]] [[tomb]]s have been found only in [[Metohia]], and not in Kosovo.&lt;ref name=Jankovic&gt;[[Djordje Janković]]: [http://www.rastko.org.yu/kosovo/istorija/malkolm/djankovic-facts.html Middle Ages in Noel Malcolm's &quot;Kosovo. A Short History&quot; and Real Facts]&lt;/ref&gt; After the Indo-European invasion, Kosovo became inhabited by [[Illyria]]n and [[Thracian]] tribes, such as the [[Dardani]] and the [[Triballi]]; the territory of today's province was a part of [[Dardania (Europe)|Dardania]]. The south of Kosovo was ruled by [[Macedon]] since [[Alexander the Great]]'s reign in the 4th century BC. The local [[Dardani]] were of [[Illyrian]] or [[Thracian]] stock. Illyrians resisted rule by the [[Greeks]] and [[Ancient Rome|Romans]] for centuries but after the long periods of conflict between Illyrian tribes and invading imperial powers, the region was eventually occupied by the [[Roman Empire]] under Emperor [[Augustus]] in 28 BC, although it is not clear whether it was part of the province of [[Moesia]] or was divided between [[Dalmatia]] and Moesia (a view which is supported by some archaeological evidence).&lt;ref name=Jankovic/&gt; Emperor [[Diocletian]] later (c. [[284]]) made Dardania into a separate province with its capital at Naissus ([[Niš]]). When the Roman Empire split in [[Anno Domini|A.D.]] [[395]], the area came under the [[Byzantine Empire|Eastern Roman Empire]], the [[Byzantine Empire]]. Many inhabitants of [[Dardania]] became leaders in Rome and [[Constantinopolis]], including [[Justinian the Great]].

=== Medieval ===
==== Great Migrations and Interregnums ====
[[Serbs]] came to the territories that form modern Kosovo in the [[7th century|7th centuries]] migrations of [[White Serbs]] under the [[Unknown Archont]], with the largest influx of migrants in the 630s; although the region was increasingly populated by Slavs since the 6th or even 5th century. These Slavs were [[Christianization|Christianized]] in several waves between the [[7th century|7th]] and [[9th century]], with the last wave taking place between [[867]] and [[874]]. The northwestern part of Kosovo, [[Hvosno]], became a part of the Byzantine [[Serb]] vassal state the [[Principality of Rascia]], with [[Desnik|Dostinik]] as the principality's capital.

In the late 800s, the whole of Kosovo was seized by the [[First Bulgarian Empire]]. Although [[Serbia]] restored control over [[Metohija]] throughout the 10th century, the rest of Kosovo was returned to the Byzantine Empire in a period of Bulgarian decline. However, Tsar [[Samuil of Bulgaria]] reconquered the whole of Kosovo in the late 10th century until the Byzantines restored their control over the area as they subjugated the Bulgarian Empire. In 1040-1041, Slavs staged a rebellion against the Eastern Roman Empire that temporarily encompassed Kosovo. After the rebellion was crushed, the Byzantine control over the region continued. 

Throughout the following decades, numerous foreign peoples invading the Byzantine Empire stormed Kosovo, among them the [[Cumans]]. 

In 1072, local Slavs under George Voiteh pushed a final attempt to restore Imperial Bulgarian power and invited the last heir of the [[House of Comitopuli]] - [[Duklja]]'s prince [[Constantine Bodin (Peter III)|Konstantin Bodin]] of the [[House of Vojislavljevic]], son of the [[List of Serbian rulers|Serbian King]] [[Mihailo Voislav]] - to assume power. The Serbs decided to conquer the entire Byzantine region of Bulgaria. King Mihailo dispatched his son with 300 elite Serb fighters led by Duke Petrilo. Constantine Bodin was crowned in [[Prizren]] as ''Petar III'', [[List of Bulgarian monarchs|Tsar of the Bulgarians]] by Goerge Voiteh and the Slavic Boyars. The Empire swept across Byzantine territories in months, until the significant losses on the south had forced Czar Petar to withdraw. In 1073, the Byzantine forces chased Constantine Bodin, defeated his army at [[Pauni]], and imprisoned him.

==== Incorporation into Serbia ====
The full Serbian takeover was carried out under a branch of the [[House of Vojislavljević|House of Voislav]] [[Grand Prince]]s of [[Rascia]]. In [[1093]], Prince Vukan advanced on [[Lip</text>
