      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Kosovo-InfoBox}}
{{dablink|For other uses of the name Kosovo, see [[Kosovo (disambiguation)]]. For other uses of the name Kosova, see [[Kosova (disambiguation)]].}}
&lt;!-- Please be very careful in editing the introduction of this article. The Arbitration Committee has placed this article on probation. If any editor makes disruptive edits, they may be banned by an administrator from this and related articles, or other reasonably related pages. See the talk page for more information. --&gt;
'''Kosovo''' ([[Serbian language|Serbian]]: Косово и Метохија or ''Kosovo i Metohija'', also Космет or ''Kosmet''; [[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Kosovë'' or ''Kosova'') is a province in southern [[Serbia]] which has been under [[United Nations]] [[United Nations Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo|administration]] since [[1999]]. While Serbia's nominal [[sovereignty]] is recognised by the international community, in practice Serbian governance in the province is virtually non-existent (''see also [[Constitutional status of Kosovo]]''). The province is governed by the [[United Nations Mission in Kosovo]] (UNMIK) and the local [[Provisional Institutions of Self-Government]], with security provided by the [[NATO]]-led [[Kosovo Force]] (KFOR). 

Kosovo borders [[Montenegro]], [[Albania]] and the [[Republic of Macedonia]]. The mountainous province's capital and largest city is [[Priština]]. Kosovo has a population of around two million people, predominately ethnic [[Albanians]], with smaller populations of [[Serbs]], [[Turkish people|Turks]], [[Bosniaks]] and other ethnic groups.

The province is the subject of a long-running political and territorial dispute between the Serbian (and previously, the [[Yugoslavia|Yugoslav]]) government and Kosovo's Albanian population. International negotiations began in [[2006]] to determine the final status of Kosovo. 

:''See also [[Names of Kosovo]].''

== Geography ==
''For administrative divisions, see [[Municipalities of Kosovo]]''
[[image:UTkosovo rel small 92.jpg|thumb|left|275px|Physical map of Kosovo]]
With an area of [[1 E10 m²|10,912]] [[square kilometre]]s (4,213 [[square mile|sq.&amp;nbsp;mi]]) and a population of over two million on the eve of the 1999 crisis, Kosovo borders [[Montenegro]] to the northwest, [[Central Serbia]] to the North and East, the [[Republic of Macedonia]] to the south and [[Albania]] to the southwest. The province's present borders were established in [[1945]]. The republic of [[Serbia]] has one other autonomous province, [[Vojvodina]], located in the far north of the country.

The largest cities are [[Pristina]], the capital, with an estimated 600,000 citizens, and [[Prizren]] in the southwest with 120,000 citizens; five other towns have populations in excess of 50,000. The climate in Kosovo is continental with warm summers and cold and snowy winters. .

There are two main plains in Kosovo. The [[Metohija]]/Rrafshi i Dukagjinit basin is located in the western part of the province, and the Plain of Kosovo ([[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Rrafshi i Kosovës'', [[Serbian language|Serbian]]: ''Kosovska Dolina'') occupies the central area.

Much of Kosovo's terrain is rugged. The [[Sar Mountain]] (Albanian: ''Mali i Sharrit'', Serbian: ''Šar Planina'') is located in the south and south-east, bordering [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]]. It is one of the region's most popular tourist and skiing resorts, with [[Brezovica]] and Prevalac/Prevallë as the main tourist centres. Kosovo's mountainous area, including the highest peak Deravica/Gjeravica (2656 m above sea level), is located in the south-west, bordering [[Albania]] and [[Montenegro]]. 

The mountain range dividing Kosovo from Albania is known in English as the [[Cursed Mountains]] or Albanian Alps (Albanian: ''Bjeshkët e Nemuna'', Serbian: ''Prokletije''). The Kopaonik mountain is located in the north, bordering [[Central Serbia]]. The central region of [[Drenica]], Carraleva/Crnoljevo and the eastern part of Kosovo, known as Gallap/Golak, are mainly hilly areas. 

There are several notable rivers and lakes in Kosovo. The main rivers are the [[White Drin]] (Albanian: ''Drini i Bardhë'', Serbian: ''Beli Drim'') -several other waterways flow into it, including the [[Erenik]], and the river runs towards the [[Adriatic Sea]]-, [[Sitnica]], [[South Morava]] in the [[Goljak]] area and [[Ibar River|Ibar]] (Albanian: ''Ibër'') in the north. The main lakes are [[Badovc]] in the north-east and [[Gazivoda]] in the north-western part.

== History ==
{{History of Kosovo}}
{{main|History of Kosovo}}
:''See also: [[Demographic history of Kosovo]]''
=== Ancient ===
The region was certainly inhabited in [[prehistory|prehistoric]] times, it appears, by two different cultures: [[bronze age|Bronze]] and [[Iron Age]] [[tomb]]s have been found only in [[Metohia]], and not in other parts of Kosovo.&lt;ref name=Jankovic&gt;[[Djordje Janković]]: [http://www.rastko.org.yu/kosovo/istorija/malkolm/djankovic-facts.html Middle Ages in Noel Malcolm's &quot;Kosovo. A Short History&quot; and Real Facts]&lt;/ref&gt; After the Indo-European invasion, Kosovo became inhabited by [[Illyria]]n and [[Thracian]] tribes, such as the [[Dardani]] and the [[Triballi]]; the territory of today's province was a part of [[Dardania (Europe)|Dardania]]. The south of Kosovo was ruled by [[Macedon]] since [[Alexander the Great]]'s reign in the 4th century BC. The local [[Dardani]] were of [[Illyrian]] or [[Thracian]] stock. Illyrians resisted rule by the [[Greeks]] and [[Ancient Rome|Romans]] for centuries but after the long periods of conflict between Illyrian tribes and invading imperial powers, the region was eventually occupied by the [[Roman Empire]] under Emperor [[Augustus]] in 28 BC, although it is not clear whether it was part of the province of [[Moesia]] or was divided between [[Dalmatia]] and Moesia (a view which is supported by some archaeological evidence).&lt;ref name=Jankovic/&gt; Emperor [[Diocletian]] later (c. [[284]]) made Dardania into a separate province with its capital at Naissus ([[Niš]]). When the Roman Empire split in [[Anno Domini|A.D.]] [[395]], the area came under the [[Byzantine Empire|Eastern Roman Empire]], the [[Byzantine Empire]]. Many inhabitants of [[Dardania]] became leaders in Rome and [[Constantinopolis]], including [[Justinian the Great]].

=== Medieval ===
==== Great Migrations and Interregnums ====
[[Serbs]] came to the territories that form modern Kosovo in the [[7th century|7th centuries]] migrations of [[White Serbs]] under the [[Unknown Archont]], with the largest influx of migrants in the 630s; although the region was increasingly populated by Slavs since the 6th or even 5th century. These Slavs were [[Christianization|Christianized]] in several waves between the [[7th century|7th]] and [[9th century]], with the last wave taking place between [[867]] and [[874]]. The northwestern part of Kosovo, [[Hvosno]], became a part of the Byzantine [[Serb]] vassal state the [[Principality of Rascia]], with [[Desnik|Dostinik]] as the principality's capital.

In the late 800s, the whole of Kosovo was seized by the [[First Bulgarian Empire]]. Although [[Serbia]] restored control over [[Metohija]] throughout the 10th century, the rest of Kosovo was returned to the Byzantine Empire in a period of Bulgarian decline. However, Tsar [[Samuil of Bulgaria]] reconquered the whole of Kosovo in the late 10th century until the Byzantines restored their control over the area as they subjugated the Bulgarian Empire. In 1040-1041, Slavs staged a rebellion against the Eastern Roman Empire that temporarily encompassed Kosovo. After the rebellion was crushed, the Byzantine control over the region continued. 

Throughout the following decades, numerous foreign peoples invading the Byzantine Empire stormed Kosovo, among them the [[Cumans]]. 

In 1072, local Slavs, under George Voiteh, pushed a final attempt to restore Imperial Bulgarian power and invited the last heir of the [[House of Comitopuli]] - [[Duklja]]'s prince [[Constantine Bodin (Peter III)|Konstantin Bodin]] of the [[House of Vojislavljevic]], son of the [[List of Serbian rulers|Serbian King]] [[Mihailo Voislav]] - to assume power. The Serbs decided to conquer the entire Byzantine region of Bulgaria. King Mihailo dispatched his son with 300 elite Serb fighters led by Duke Petrilo. Constantine Bodin was crowned in [[Prizren]] as ''Petar III'', [[List of Bulgarian monarchs|Tsar of the Bulgarians]] by Goerge Voiteh and the Slavic Boyars. The Empire swept across Byzantine territories in months, until the significant losses on the south had forced Czar Petar to withdraw. In 1073, the Byzantine forces chased Constantine Bodin, defeated his army at [[Pauni]], and imprisoned him.

==== Incorporation into Serbia ====
The full Serbian takeover was carried out under a branch of the [[House of Vojislavljević|House of Voislav]] [[Grand Prince]]s of [[Rascia]]. In [[1093]], Prince Vukan advanced on [[Lipljan]], burned it down and raided the neighbouring areas. The Byzantine Emperor himself came to [[Zvečan]] for negotiations. Zvečan served as the Byzantine line-of-defence against constant invasions from the neighboring Serbs. A peace agreement was made, but Vukan broke it and defeated the army of John Comnenus, the Emperor's nephew. Vukan's armies stormed Kosovo. In [[1094]], [[Alexius I Comnenus|Byzantine Emperor Alexius]] attempted to renew peace negotiations in Ulpiana. A new peace agreement was concluded and Vukan handed over hostages to the Emperor, including his two nephews Uroš and Stefan Vukan. Prince Vukan renewed the conflict in [[1106]], once again defeating John Comnenus' army. However, his death halted the total Serb conquest of Kosovo.

In [[1166]], a Serbian nobleman from [[Zeta (state)|Zeta]], [[Stefan Nemanja]], the founder of the [[Nemanjić|House of Nemanja]] ascended to the Rascian Grand Princely throne and conquered most of Kosovo, in an uprising against the Byzantine Emperor [[Manuel I Comnenus]]. He defeated the previous Grand Prince of Rascia Tihomir's army at Pantino, near Pauni. Tihomir, who was Stefan's brother, was drowned in the [[Sitnica]] river. Stefan was eventually defeated and had to return some of his conquests. He pledged to the Emperor that he would not renew hostilies, but in [[1183]], Stefan Nemanja embarked on a new offensive with the [[Hungarians]] after the death of [[Manuel I Comnenus]] in [[1180]], marking the end of Byzantine domination of Kosovo.

Nemanja's son, [[Stefan Prvovenčani|Stefan II]], recorded that the border of the Serbian realm reached the river of Lab. Grand Prince Stephen II completed the inclusion of the Kosovo territories under Serb rule in 1208, by which time he had conquered Prizren and Lipljan, and moved the border of territory under his control to the Šar mountain.

==== Kingdom of the Serbs ====
In [[1217]], the [[History of Serbia|Serbian Kingdom]] achieved recognition. In [[1219]], an autocephalous [[Serbian Orthodox Church]] was created, with [[Hvosno]], Prizren and Lipljan being the Orthodox Christian [[Episcopates]] on Kosovo. By the end of the [[13th century]], the centre of the [[Serbian Orthodox Church|Serbian Church]] was moved to [[Peć]] from [[Žiča]].

In the 13th century, Kosovo became the heart of the Serbian political and religious life, with the Šar mountain becoming the political center of the Serbian rulers. The main chatteu was in Pauni. On an island was [[Svrčin]], and on the coast [[Štimlji]], and in the mountains was the Castle of [[Nerodimlje]]. The Complexes were used for counciling, crowning of rulers, negotiating, and as the rulers' living quarters. After 1291, the Tartars broke all the way to Peć. [[List of Serbian rulers|Serbian King]] [[Stefan Milutin]] managed to defeat them and then chase them further. He raised the Temple of the [[Mother of Christ]] of Ljeviška in Prizren around 1307, which became the seat of the Prizren Episcopric, and the magnificent [[Gračanica]] in 1335, the seat of the Lipljan Episcopric. In 1331, Juvenille King Dušan attacked his father, Serbian King Stefan of Dechani at his castle in Nerodimlje. King Stefan closed in his neighbouring fortress of [[Petrič]], but Dušan captured him and closed him with his second wife Maria Palailogos and their children in Zvečan, where the dethroned King died on [[11 November]] [[1331]].

In 1327 and 1328, Serbian King Stefan of Dechani started forming the vast Dečani domain, although, Serbian King Dušan would finish it in 1335. Stefan of Dechani issued the Dechani Charter in 1330, listing every single citizen in every household under the Church Land's demesne.

==== Serbian Empire and Despotate ====
[[Monarch|King]] [[Stefan Dušan]] founded the vast Monastery of Saint Archaengel near Prizren in [[1342]]-[[1352]]. The Kingdom was transformed into an [[Serbian Empire|Empire]] in 1345 and officially in 1346. Stefan Dušan received [[John VI Cantacuzenus]] in [[1342]] in his Castle in [[Pauni]] to discuss a joint War against the Byzantine Emperor. In [[1346]], the Serbian [[Archbishopric|Archepiscopric]] at Peć was upgraded into a [[Patriarchate]], but it was not recognized before [[1370]]. 

After the Empire fell into disarray prior to Dušan's death in [[1355]], feudal anarchy caught up with the country during the reign of Tsar [[Stefan Uroš V]]. Kosovo became a domain of the [[Vukašin Mrnjavčević|House of Mrnjavčević]], but Prince Voislav Voinović expanded his demesne further into Kosovo. The armies of King [[Vukašin Mrnjavčević]] from [[Pristina]] and his allies defeated Voislav's forces in [[1369]], putting a halt to his advances. After the [[Battle of Marica]] on [[26 September]] [[1371]], in which the Mrnjavčević brothers lost their lives, [[House of Balšić|Đurađ I Balšić]] of [[Zeta (state)|Zeta]] took Prizren and Peć in [[1372]]. A part of Kosovo became the demesne of the [[Prince Lazar|House of Lazarević]].

The [[Ottoman Empire|Ottomans]] invaded and met the Christian coalition under [[Prince Lazar]] on [[28 June]] [[1389]], near [[Pristina]], at Gazi Mestan. The Serbian Army was assisted by various allies. The epic [[Battle of Kosovo]] followed, in which Prince Lazar himself lost his life. Prince Lazar amassed 70,000 men on the battlefield and the Ottomans had 140,000. Through the cunning of [[Miloš Obilić]], [[Sultan]] [[Murad I|Murad]] was murdered and the new Sultan [[Beyazid]] had, despite winning the battle, to retreat to consolidate his power. The Ottoman Sultan was buried with one of his sons at Gazi Mestan. Both [[Prince Lazar]] and [[Miloš Obilić]] were canonised by the [[Serbian Orthodox Church]] for their efforts in the battle. The local House of [[Vuk Branković|Branković]] came to prominence as the local lords of Kosovo, under [[Vuk Branković]], with the temporary fall of the [[History of Serbia|Serbian Despotate]] in [[1439]]. Another great battle occurred between the Hungarian troops supported by the Albanian ruler Gjergj Kastrioti [[Skanderbeg]] on one side, and Ottoman troops supported by the [[House of Branković|Branković]]s in [[1448]]. Skanderbeg's troops that were going to help John Hunyadi were stopped by the Branković's troops, who was more or less a Turkish [[Vassal]]. Hungarian King [[John Hunyadi]] lost the battle after a 2-day fight, but essentially stopped the Ottoman advance northwards. Kosovo then became vassalaged to the Ottoman Empire, until its direct incorporation after the final fall of Serbia in 1459. 

In 1455, new castles rose to prominence in [[Prishtina]] and [[Vučitrn]], centres of the Ottoman vassalaged House of Branković.

=== Ottoman rule ===
{{POV-check}}
{{main|Kosovo Province, Ottoman Empire}}
The [[Ottoman Empire|Ottomans]] brought [[Islamisation]] with them, particularly in towns, and later also created the [[Kosovo Province, Ottoman Empire|Vilayet of Kosovo]] as one of the Ottoman territorial entities. This brought a great shift, as the Orthodox Serb population began to lose its majority when large numbers of [[Turkic peoples|Turks]] and [[Albanians]] moved to Kosovo. During the Islamisation, many Churches and Holy Orthodox Christian places were destroyed or turned into Mosques. The big Monastery of Saint Archangel near Prizren was torn down at the end of the 16th century and the material used to build the Mosque of Sinan-pasha, an Islamized Serb, in Prizren. Although the [[Serbian Orthodox Church]] was officially abolished in 1532, an Islamized Serb from Bosnia, Vizier [[Mehmed-pasha Sokolović]] influenced the restoration of the [[Patriarchate of Peć]] in 1557. Special privileges were provided, which helped the survival of Serbs and other Christians in Kosovo. 

Kosovo was taken by the Austrian forces during the [[Great Turkish War#War of the Holy League (1683–1699)|Great War of 1683-1699]] with help of 5,000 Albanians and their leader, a [[Catholic Archibishop]] [[Pjetër Bogdani]]. The archbishop died of plague during the war, and his grave was later reopened, with his body scattered and given to the dogs by the Ottomans because of his role in the rebellion. In [[1690]], the [[Serbian Patriarch of Peć]] [[Arsenije III Čarnojević]], who previously escaped a certain death, led 37,000 families from Kosovo, to evade [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] wrath since Kosovo had just been retaken by the Ottomans. The people that followed him were mostly [[Serbs]] – 20,000 Serbs abandoned [[Prizren]] alone - but they were likely followed by other ethnic groups. Due to the oppression from the Ottomans, other migrations of Orthodox people from the Kosovo area continued throughout the [[18th century]]. It is also noted that some [[Serbs]] adopted [[Islam]], while some even gradually fused with other groups, predominantly Albanianians, adopting their culture and even language. By the end of the 19th century, [[Albanians]] replaced the Serbs as the dominating nation of Kosovo.

In 1766, the Ottomans abolished the [[Patriarchate of Peć]] and the position of [[Christians]] in Kosovo was greatly reduced. All previous privileges were lost, and the Christian population had to suffer the full weight of the Empire's extensive and losing wars, even having blame forced upon them for the losses.

=== Modern ===
In 1871, a massive Serbian meeting was held in Prizren. The possible retaking and reintegration of Kosovo and the rest of &quot;Old Serbia&quot; was discussed at the meeting, as the [[History of Serbia|Principality of Serbia]] itself had already made plans for expansions towards Ottoman territory, much easier than elsewhere. 

Albanian refugees from the territories conquered in the [[1876]]-[[1877]] Serbo-Turkish war and the [[1877]]-[[1878]] Russo-Turkish are now known as '[[muhajir (Albania)|muhaxher]]' (which means 'refugee', from [[Arabic]] [[muhajir]]) and are the ancestors of many who are still known by their same surnames, ''Muhaxheri''. It is also estimated that 200,000 to 400,000 Serbs were cleansed out of the [[Vilayet of Kosovo]] between [[1876]] and [[1912]], especially during the [[Greco-Turkish War (1897)|Greek-Ottman War]] in [[1897]]. 

In 1878, a Peace Accord was drawn that gave the cities of [[Prishtina]] and [[Kosovska Mitrovica]] under civil Serbian control, outside the Ottoman authorities, while the rest of Kosovo would be under Ottoman control. As a responce, the Albanians formed the nationalistic &amp; conservative [[League of Prizren]] in [[Prizren]] later the same year. Over 300 Albanian leaders from Kosovo and western Macedonia gathered and discussed the urgent issues concerning protection of Albanian populated regions from division among neighbouring countries. The League was supported by the Ottoman Sultan because of its Pan-Islamic ideology and political aspirations of a [[Greater Albania|unified Albanian people]] under the Ottoman umbrella. The movement gradually became anti-Christian and spread great anxiety among Christian Albanians and especially among Christian Serbs. As a result, more and more Serbs left Kosovo northwards. Serbia complained to the World Powers that the promised territories were not being held because the Ottomans were hesitating to do that. The World Powers put pressure to the Ottomans and in 1881, the Ottoman Army started the fighting the Albanian forces. The Prizren League created a Provisional Government with a President, Prime Minister (Ymer Prizreni) and Ministries of War (Sylejman Vokshi) and Foreign Ministry (Abdyl Frashëri). After three years of war, the Albanians were defeated. Many of the leaders were executed and imprisoned. The subsequent Treaty of San Stefano in 1898 restored most Albanian lands to Ottoman control, but the Serbian forces had to retreat from Kosovo along with some Serbs that were expelled as well{{citation needed}}. 

In 1908, the Sultan brought a new democratic decrete that was valid only for Turkish-speakers. As the vast majority of Kosovo spoke Albanian or Serbian, the Kosovar population was very unhappy. The Young Turk movement supported a centralist rule and opposed any sort of autonomy desired by Kosovars, and particularely the Albanians. In 1910, an [[Albanian]] uprising spread from [[Prishtina]] and lasted until the Ottoman Sultan's visit to Kosovo in June of 1911. The Aim of the League of Prizren was to unite the four Albanian Vilayets by merging the majority of Albanian inhabitants within the Ottoman Empire into one Albanian State. However, at that time Serbs have consisted about ''40%'' of the whole Vilayt of Kosovo's overall population and were opposing the Albanian nationalism along with Turks and other Slavs in Kosovo, which disabled the Albanian movements to occupy Kosovo. 

:''See also: [[Serbia in WWI]]''

In [[1912]] during the [[Balkan Wars]], most of Kosovo was taken by the [[History of Serbia|Kingdom of Serbia]], while the region of [[Metohija]] ([[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Dukagjini Valley'') was taken by the [[History of Montenegro|Kingdom of Montenegro]]. An exodus of the local Albanian population occurred. This is best described by [[Leon Trotsky]], who was the reporter for the 'Pravda' newspaper at the time. The Serbian authorities planned a recolonization of Kosovo.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.elsie.de/pdf/B2002GatheringClouds.pdf Elsie, R. (ed.) (2002): ''Gathering Clouds. The roots of ethnic cleansing in Kosovo. Early twentieth-century documents''. Dukagjini Balkan Books, Peja (Kosovo, Serbia). ISBN 9951-05-016-6&lt;/ref&gt; Numerous colonist Serb families moved-in to Kosovo, equalizing the demographic balance between Albanians and Serbs. Many Albanians fled into the mountains and numerous Albanian and Turkish houses were razed. The reconquest of Kosovo was noted as a vengeance for the 1389 [[Battle of Kossovo]]. At the Conference of Ambassadors in London in 1912 presided over by Sir Edward Grey, the British Foreign Secretary, the Kingdoms of Serbia and Montenegro were acknowledged sovereignty over Kosovo. 

&lt;!-- removed unlicensed image [[Image:1Serbian_army_retreat_WW1.jpg|thumb|left|Serbian army retreat]] --&gt;
In the winter of [[1915]]-[[1916]] during [[World War I]] Kosovo saw a large exodus of Serbian army which became known as the ''Great Serbian Retreat''. Defeated and worn out in battles against Austro-Hungarians, they had no other choice than to retreat, as Kosovo was occupied by [[Third Bulgarian Empire|Bulgarians]] and [[Austro-Hungarians]]. The Albanians joined and supported the [[Central Powers]]. As opposed to Serbian schools, numerous Albanian schools were opened during the 'occupation' (the majority Albanian population considered it a liberation). Allied ships were awaiting for Serbian people and soldiers at the banks of the Adriatic sea and the path leading them there went across Kosovo and Albania. Tens of thousands of soldiers have died of starvation, extreme weather and Albanian reprisals as they were approaching the [[Allies]] in [[Corfu]] and [[Thessaloniki]], amassing a total of 100,000 dead retreaters.{{citation needed}} Transported away from the front lines, Serbian army managed to heal many wounded and ill soldiers and get some rest. Refreshed and regrouped, it decided to return to the battlefield. In 1918 the Serbian Army pushed the [[Central Powers]] out of Kosovo. During their re-occupation of Kosovo, the Serbian Army committed atrocities against the population in revenge. Serbian Kosovo was unified with Montengrin as Montenegro subsequently joined the Kingdom of Serbia. After the World War I ended, the Monarchy was then transformed into the [[Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenians]] ''(&quot;Mbretëria Serbe,Kroate,Sllovene&quot; in Albanian, &quot; &quot;Kraljevina Srba, Hrvata i Slovenaca&quot; in Serbo-Croatian)'' on '''1st December 1918''', gathering territories gained in victory. 

==== Kingdom of Yugoslavia and WWII ====
The 1918-1929 period of the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenians witnessed a rise of the Serbian population in the region and a decline in the non-Serbian. In the Kingdom Kosovo was split onto four counties - three being a part of the entity of Serbia: Zvečan, Kosovo and southern Metohija; and one of Montenegro: northern Metohija. However, the new administration system since [[26 April]] [[1922]] split Kosovo among three Areas of the Kingdom: Kosovo, [[Rascia]] and [[Zeta]]. In 1921 the Albanian elite lodged an official protest of the government to the League of Nations, claiming that 12,000 Albanians had been killed and over 22,000 imprisoned since 1918 and seeking a [[Greater Albania|unification of Albanian-populated lands]]. The League of Nations did not respond, as the appeal was found unfounded. As a result, an armed ''Kachak'' resistance movement was formed whose main goal was to unite Albanian-populated areas of the Kingdom to Albania. 

In 1929 the Kingdom was transformed into the [[Kingdom of Yugoslavia]] which the ''[[Yugoslavs|Yugoslav]]'' nationality unifying all Kosovan [[Slavs]]. The territories of Kosovo were split among the [[Zeta Banovina|Banate of Zeta]], the [[Morava Banovina|Banate of Morava]] and the [[Vardar Banovina|Banate of Vardar]]. The Kingdom lasted until the [[World War II]] [[Axis powers|Axis]] invastion of 1941. 

The greatest part of Kosovo became a part of [[Italy|Italian]]-controlled [[Greater Albania|Fascist Albania]], and smaller bits by the [[Nazism|Nazi]]-[[Fascist]] [[Greater Bulgaria|Tsardom of Bulgaria]] and [[Nazism|Nazi]] [[Germany|German]]-occupied [[Serbia|Kingdom of Serbia]]. Since the Albanian Fascist political leadership had decided in the [[Conference of Bujan]] that Kosovo would remain a part of Albania they started an ethnic cleansing campaign of the non-Albanian population in the Kosovo.{{fact}} The infamous [[21st Waffen Mountain Division of the SS Skanderbeg (1st Albanian)|SS Division Skanderbeg]] committed crimes. {{citation needed}}. Tens of thousands of Serbs lost their lives and around 75,000 Serbs fled Kosovo during the war.{{fact}} Hundreds of thousands more would leave in the following decades, following the shift of power in Kosovo. {{fact}}

Prior to the surrender of [[History of Italy|Fascist Italy]] in [[1943]], the German forces took over direct control of the region. After numerous uprisings of [[Serbs|Serbian]] [[Chetniks]] and [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Yugoslav]] [[Partisans]], the latter being lead by [[Fadil Hoxha]], Kosovo was liberated after [[1944]] with the help of the Albanian partisans of the [[Comintern]], and became a province of [[Serbia]] within the [[Yugoslavia|Democratic Federal Yugoslavia]].

==== Kosovo in the Second Yugoslavia ====
The Province of Kosovo was formed in 1945 as an autonomous region to protect its regional [[Albanians|Albanian]] majority within the [[History of Serbia|People's Republic of Serbia]] as a member of the [[SFRJ|Federal People's Republic of Yugoslavia]] under the leadership of the former Partisan leader, [[Josip Broz Tito]], but with no factual autonomy. After Yugoslavia's name change to the [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia]] and Serbia's to the [[History of Serbia|Socialist Republic of Serbia]] in [[1953]], Kosovo gained inner autonomy in the 1960s. In the [[1974]] constitution, the Socialist Autonomous Province of Kosovo's government received higher powers, including the highest governmental titles — President and Premier and a seat in the Federal Presidency which made it a ''de facto'' Socialist Republic within the Federation, but remaining as a Socialist Autonomous Province within the Socialist Republic of Serbia. [[Serbo-Croatian]] and [[Albanian language|Albanian]] were defined as official languages on the provincial level marking the two largest linguistic Kosovan groups: Albanians and Serbs. In the 1970s, an Albanian nationalist movement pursued full recognition of the Province of Kosovo as another Republic within the Federation, while the most extreme elements aimed for full-scale independence. Tito's arbitrary regime dealt with the situation swiftly, but only giving it a temporary solution. The ethnic balance of Kosovo witnessed unproportional increase as the number of [[Albanians]] tripled gradually rising from almost ''65%'' to over ''80%'', but the number of [[Serbs]] barely increased and dropped in the full share of the total population from some ''25%'' down to ''10%''.

Beginning in March [[1981]], Kosovar Albanian students organized protests seeking that Kosovo become a republic within Yugoslavia. Those protests rapidly escalated into violent riots &quot;involving 20,000 people in six cities&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt19810419&quot;&gt;New York Times 1981-04-19, &quot;One Storm has Passed but Others are Gathering in Yugoslavia&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; that were harshly contained by the Yugoslav government. During the 1980s, ethnic tensions continued with frequent violent outbreaks against Serbs and Yugoslav state authorities resulting in increased emigration of Kosovo Serbs and other ethnic groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;reuters19860527&quot;&gt;Reuters 1986-05-27, &quot;Kosovo Province Revives Yugoslavia's Ethnic Nightmare&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;csm19860728&quot;&gt;Christian Science Monitor 1986-07-28, &quot;Tensions among ethnic groups in Yugoslavia begin to boil over&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The Yugoslav leadership tried to suppress protests of Kosovo Serbs seeking protection from ethnic discrimination and violence.&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt19870627&quot;&gt;New York Times 1987-06-27, &quot;Belgrade Battles Kosovo Serbs&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[1986]], the Serbian Academy of Sciences and Arts (SANU) was working on a document which later would be known as the [[SANU Memorandum]], a warning to the Serbian President and Assembly of the existing crisis and where it would lead. An unfinished edition was filtered to the press. In the essay, SANU criticised the state of Yugoslavia and made remarks that the only member state contributing at the time to the development of Kosovo and Macedonia (by then, the poorest territories of the Federation) was Serbia. According to SANU, Yugoslavia was suffering of ethnic strives and the disintegration of the Yugoslav economy into separate economic sectors and territories, which was transforming the federal state into a loose confederation.&lt;ref&gt;SANU (1986): [http://www.balkan-archive.org.yu/kosta/memorandum/contents.html Serbian Academy of Sciences and Arts Memorandum]. GIP Kultura. Belgrade.&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, some think that [[Slobodan Milošević]] used the discontent reflected in the SANU memorandum for his own political goals, during his rise to power in [[Serbia]] at the time.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.opendemocracy.net/articles/ViewPopUpArticle.jsp?id=2&amp;articleId=3361 Julie A Mertus: &quot;Slobodan Milošević: Myth and Responsibility&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

By the end of the 1980s, calls for increased federal control in the crisis-torn autonomous province were getting louder. [[Slobodan Milošević]] pushed for constitutional change amounting to suspension of autonomy for both Kosovo and [[Vojvodina]].&lt;ref name=&quot;reuters19880730&quot;&gt;Reuters 1988-07-30, &quot;Yugoslav Leaders Call for Control in Kosovo, Protests Loom&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Kosovo War ====
{{main|Kosovo War}}
In 1987, Milošević was sent to Kosovo by the Serbian President Ivan Stambolic to &quot;pacify restive Serbs in Kosovo&quot; who wanted to curb the autonomy enjoyed by the province. &quot;Milošević broke away from a meeting with ethnic Albanians to mingle with angry Serbians in a suburb of Pristina. The Serbs protested they were being pushed back by police with batons, and Milošević told them, &quot;Niko ne sme da vas bije&quot; (&quot;No one is allowed to beat you&quot;). &quot;Slobo! Slobo!&quot; the crowd chanted.”&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cnn.com/SPECIALS/2000/kosovo/stories/past/milosevic/&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the events that contributed to Milošević's rise of power was the ''Gazimestan Speech'', delivered in front of 1,000,000 Serb citizens at the central celebration marking the 600th anniversary of the [[Battle of Kosovo]], held at [[Gazimestan]] on 28 June, 1989.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.balkanpeace.org/cib/kam/kams/kams19.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; In the same speech, Milošević also criticised the &quot;dramatical national divisions&quot; and called Yugoslavia &quot;a multinational community [which] can survive only under the conditions of full equality for all nations that live in it.&quot; Milošević also said in the speech, &quot;Six centuries later, now, we are being again engaged in battles and are facing battles. They are not armed battles, although such things cannot be excluded yet.&quot;  However, many analysts - ranging from biographer Lebor to critics of American foreign policy such as [[Jared Israel]] - believe that the speech has been exaggerated beyond all proportion. Much of the speech was aimed at consolidating socialism and racial harmony in an era when Communism was collapsing&lt;ref&gt;http://www.slobodan-milosevic.org/spch-kosovo1989.htm&lt;/ref&gt;.

Soon afterwards, as approved by the Assembly in 1990, the autonomy of Kosovo was reduced. After [[Slovenia]]'s secession from Yugoslavia in 1991, Milošević used Kosovo's seat on the Yugoslavian Presidency to attain dominance over the Federal government, outvoting his opponents. 

Many Albanians organized a peaceful separatist movement. State institutions and elections were boycotted and separate Albanian schools and political institutions were established. On [[July 2]], [[1990]] an unconstitutional Kosovo parliament declared Kosovo an independent country, this was not recognized by the Government or any foreign states. In September of that year, the unofficial parliament, meeting in secrecy in the town of [[Kaçanik]], adopted the ''Constitution of the Republic of Kosovo''. Two years later, in 1992, the parliament organized an unofficial referendum which was observed by international organisations {{citation needed}} but was not recognized internationally. With an ''80%'' turnout, ''98%'' voted for Kosovo to be independent.

With the events in [[Bosnia and Herzegovina|Bosnia]] and [[Croatia]] coming to an end, the Serb government started relocating Serbian refugees from Croatia and Bosnia all over Serbia, including in Kosovo. 
[[Image:Kosovo_pisg_ca.png|thumb|right|200px|Logo of the [[Provisional Institutions of Self-Government]]]]
After the [[Dayton Agreement]] in 1995, some Albanians organized into the [[Kosovo Liberation Army]] (KLA), employing guerilla-style tactics against the Serbian police forces. Violence escalated in a series of KLA attacks and Serbian reprisals into the year 1999, with increasing numbers of civilian victims. In 1998 western interest increased and the Serbian authorities were forced to sign a unilateral cease-fire and partial retreat. Under an agreement led by [[Richard Holbrooke]], [[OSCE]] observers moved into Kosovo to monitor the ceasefire, while Yugoslav military forces partly pulled out of Kosovo. However, the ceasefire was systematically broken shortly thereafter by KLA forces, which again provoked harsh counterattacks by the Serbs. On 16 January 1999, the bodies of 45 Albanian civilians were found in the town of [[Racak]]. The victims had been executed by Serb forces.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/1812847.stm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hrw.org/press/1999/jan/yugo0129.htm&lt;/ref&gt; The Racak Massacre was instrumental in increasing the pressure on Serbia in the following conference at [[Rambouillet]]. After more than a month of negotations Yugoslavia refused to sign the prepared agreement, primarily, it has been argued, because of a clause giving NATO forces access rights to not only Kosovo but to all of Yugoslavia (which the Yugoslav side saw as tantamount to military occupation).

This triggered a 78-day [[NATO]] campaign in [[1999]]. At first limited to military targets in Kosovo proper, the bombing campaign was soon extended to cover targets all over Yugoslavia, including bridges, power stations, factories, broadcasting stations, hospitals, post offices, and various government buildings. 

During the conflict roughly a million ethnic Albanians fled Kosovo, several thousand were killed, the numbers and the ethnic distribution of the casualties are uncertain and highly disputed. An estimated 10,000-12,000 ethnic Albanians and 3,000 Serbs are believed to have been killed during the conflict, including military personnel and civilians, primarily as a result of the ground war in Kosovo between the KLA and the Yugoslav military, Serbian police and Serbian paramilitary forces. Some 3000 people are still missing, of which 2,500 are Albanian, 400 Serbs and 100 Roma.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/781310.stm&lt;/ref&gt; According to OSCE numbers and Kosovar Albanian sources on population size and distribution, an estimated ''45.7%'' of the Albanian population and ''59.5%'' of the Serb population had fled Kosovo during the bombings and ethnic cleansing (i.e. from 23 March to 9 June 1999). Albanian refugees accused the Serbian forces of ethnic cleansing and only returned after NATO secured the area.

With the arrival of NATO, a large number of refugees, mostly Serbs fled the region. The number of registered refugees is around 250,000.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20040203102745/http://www.serbia.sr.gov.yu/coordination_centre/index.html Coordination Centre of Federal Republic of Yugoslavia and Republic of Serbia for Kosovo and Metohija]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[UNHCR]]: 2002 Annual Statistical Report: Serbia and Montenegro, pg. 9&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[USCR]]: [http://www.refugees.org/world/countryrpt/europe/yugoslavia.htm Country report: Yugoslavia]&lt;/ref&gt; Around 120,000 remain in Kosovo. Many Serbs fear to return to their homes since they perceive not to be safe for them, even with [[UNMIK]] protection, notably the [[2004 unrest in Kosovo|unrest in 2004]], when 900 Serbian houses were burned and other property destroyed&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=International Religious Freedom Report 2005|publisher=US Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labour|url=http://belgrade.usembassy.gov/policy/reports/051108.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; while the Serbian populace was closed into enclaves and had to concentrate to the north of Kosovo until today, causing a wave of 3,500 Serbian refugees.

Among the numerous [[UNESCO]] World Heritage sites destroyed by the Albanian para-military forces {{citation needed}} is King [[Stefan Milutin]]'s grave, [[Our Lady of Ljeviš Orthodox Cathedral]] from the 12th century in [[Prizren]]. In total, more than 30 Orthodox Serb Churches and Monasteries were destroyed during the March unrest in Kosovo. Many of the Churches and Monasteries were dating back to the 12th, 13th and 14th century. At the end of the two-day riots, 19 people were dead, 11 Albanians and 8 Serbs.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.kosovo.net/default2.html&lt;/ref&gt;

During the period in between the deployment of KFOR international forces in June 1999 and February 2000, 78 Serbian Orthodox Churches and Monasteries were destroyed and desecrated.&lt;ref&gt;AUSTRALIAN POLISH REVIEW (ed) (2001): ''Crucified Kosovo. Destroyed and Desecrated Churches in Kosovo and Metohia''. Meri Publishing. Sydney, Australia. Page 53.&lt;/ref&gt; Examples include The Church of the Holy Building in Musutiste (built in 1315), Devic Monastery near Srbica (built in 1434), St Uros Cathefral in Urosevac and St Nicholas Church in Ljubizda, near Prizren (16th Century).

According to a report compiled by the Kosovo Cultural Heritage Project, Serbian forces also engaged in a &quot;deliberate campaign of cultural destruction and rampage during the Kosovo War&quot;. Of the 500 mosques that were in use prior to the war, 200 of them were completely destroyed or desecrated. The report concludes that most mosques were deliberately set on fire with no sign of fighting around the area. Examples include: Sinan Pasha Mosque in Prizren, the Prizren League Museum, the Hadum Mosque complex in Gjakova (Serbian: Djakovica); the historic bazaars in Gjakova and Pec (Albanian: Peja); the Roman Catholic church of St. Anthony in Gjakova/Đakovica; and two old Ottoman bridges, Ura e Terzive (Terzijski most) and Ura e Tabakeve (Tabački most), near Gjakova/Đakovica.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.haverford.edu/relg/sells/kosovo/herscherriedlmayer.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

== Kosovo Politics and Governance ==
&lt;!--Please add new information into relevant articles of the series--&gt;
{{morepolitics|country=Kosovo}}
:''see also [[United Nations Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo]] (UNMIK) and [[Provisional Institutions of Self-Government]] (PISG)''

{{Politics of Kosovo}}
UN Security Council Resolution 1244 placed Kosovo under transitional UN administration pending a determination of Kosovo's future status.  This Resolution entrusted UNMIK with sweeping powers to govern Kosovo, but also directed UNMIK to establish interim institutions of self-governance.  Resolution 1244 permits Serbia no role in governing Kosovo and since 1999 Serbian laws and institutions have not been valid in Kosovo.  NATO has a separate mandate to provide for a safe and secure environment.

In May 2001, UNMIK promulgated the Constitutional Framework, which established Kosovo's Provisional Institutions of Self-Government (PISG).  Since 2001, UNMIK has been gradually transferring increased governing competencies to the PISG, while reserving some powers that are normally carried out by sovereign states (e.g., foreign affairs).  Kosovo has also established municipal government and an internationally-supervised Kosovo Police Service.

According to the Constitutional Framework, Kosovo shall have a 120-member Kosovo Assembly.  The Assembly includes twenty reserved seats: ten for Kosovo Serbs and ten for non-Serb minorities (e.g., Bosniak, Roma, etc.).  The Kosovo Assembly is responsible for electing a President and Prime Minister of Kosovo.  

The largest political party in Kosovo, the Democratic League of Kosovo (LDK), has its origins in the 1990s non-violent resistance movement to Milosevic's rule.  The party was led by Ibrahim Rugova until his death in 2006.  The two next largest parties have their roots in the Kosovo Liberation Army (KLA): the Democratic Party of Kosovo (PDK) led by former KLA leader Hashim Thaci and the Alliance for the Future of Kosovo (AAK) led by former KLA commander Ramush Haradinaj.  Kosovo publisher Veton Surroi formed his own political party in 2004 named &quot;Ora.&quot;  Kosovo Serbs formed the Serb List for Kosovo and Metohija (SLKM) in 2004, but have boycotted Kosovo's institutions and never taken their seats in the Kosovo Assembly.  

In November 2001, the [[OSCE]] supervised the first elections for the Kosovo Assembly.  After that election, Kosovo's political parties formed an all-party unity coalition and elected [[Ibrahim Rugova]] as President and Bajram Rexhepi (PDK) as Prime Minister.  

After Kosovo-wide elections in October 2004, the LDK and AAK formed a new governing coalition that did not include PDK and Ora.  This coalition agreement resulted in Ramush Haradinaj (AAK) becoming Prime Minister, while Ibrahim Rugova retained the position of President.  PDK and Ora were critical of the coalition agreement and have since frequently accused the current government of corruption.  

Ramush Haradinaj resigned the post of Prime Minister after he was indicted for war crimes by the International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia (ICTY) in March 2005.  He was replaced by Bajram Kosumi (AAK).  But in a political shake-up after the death of President Rugova in January 2006, Kosumi himself was replaced by former Kosovo Protection Corps commander [Agim Ceku].  Ceku has won recognition for his outreach to minorities, but Serbia has been critical of his wartime past as military leader of the KLA and claims he is still not doing enough for Kosovo Serbs.  The Kosovo Assembly elected Fatmir Sejdiu, a former LDK parliamentarian, president after Rugova's death. Slaviša Petkovic, Minister for Communities and Returns, is governments only Serbian minister and unlike other Serbians have chosen to not boycott the Kosovo institutions.

=== Kosovo Future Status Process ===
{{Current event}}
:''See also: [[Constitutional status of Kosovo]]''

A UN-led process was begun in late 2005 to determine Kosovo's future status.  This process will determine whether Kosovo should be independent or remain a part of the state of Serbia.  [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 1244]] did not address Kosovo's status, but did envision an eventual political process to resolve this question.  In October 2005, a UN-commissioned report written by Norwegian diplomat Kai Eide assessed that Kosovo's undefined status was a factor for regional instability and should be settled soon.  As a result of this report, the UN [[Security Council]] issued a Presidential Statement in November 2005 to endorse Eide's conclusions and authorize the launch of a status process.  

Belgrade's position on Kosovo status is that Kosovo should be highly autonomous, but not independent.  The Belgrade negotiating platform, often characterized by Belgrade leaders as &quot;more than autonomy, less than independence,&quot; envisions granting sweeping rights of self-governance for Kosovo, but would deny Kosovo a role in international affairs, defense or representation in Serbia's central governing institutions.  Pristina's position is that Kosovo should be independent, subject to robust institutional protections for Kosovo's minorities.  Belgrade frequently cites international law provisions about the integrity of sovereign states to justify its claim to Kosovo.  Pristina asserts that Kosovo's independence would be the result of the disintegration of the former Yugoslavia and the actions of Milosevic in the 1990s.

In November 2005, the [[Contact Group]] countries released a set of &quot;Guiding Principles&quot; for the resolution of Kosovo's status.  These principles notably included the requirement that there be no return to the situation prior to 1999 and that there be no change in Kosovo's borders (i.e., no partition of Kosovo) and no union of Kosovo with any neighboring state.  At a January 2006 meeting of foreign ministers, the Contact Group further declared that a settlement &quot;needs, inter alia, to be acceptable to the people of Kosovo&quot; and that &quot;all possible efforts should be made to achieve a negotiated settlement in the course of 2006.&quot;  Contact Group public statements have also emphasized the need to preserve Kosovo's multi-ethnic character.

The Kosovo future status process is led by UN Special Envoy [[Martti Ahtisaari]], former president of Finland; Austrian diplomat Albert Rohan is his deputy.  Ahtisaari's office -- the UN Office of the Special Envoy for Kosovo (UNOSEK) is located in [[Vienna]], Austria, and includes liaison staff from [[NATO]], the [[European Union|EU]] and the United States.  Ahtisaari is supported in his efforts by Ambassador Frank G. Wisner, the U.S. Representative to the Kosovo Status Talks.  Ahtisaari holds regular meetings with representatives of the [[Contact Group]].

The initial status negotiations focused on technicalities important for Kosovo's long-term stability, particularly the rights and protection of Kosovo's minorities, particularly the Kosovo Serbs.  Ahtisaari brought the parties together for the first direct dialogue in February 2006 to discuss decentralization of local government, which is an important measure to protect Kosovo Serb communities.  Subsequent meetings addressed economic issues, property rights, protection of Serbian Orthodox Church heritage and institutional guarantees for the rights of Kosovo's minorities.  

On July 24, 2006, Ahtisaari brought the parties together in Vienna for the first high-level talks on the status outcome itself.  Serbian President [[Boris Tadić]] and Prime Minister [[Vojislav Koštunica]] and Kosovo President [[Fatmir Sejdiu]] and Prime Minister [[Agim Çeku]] attended and presented their respective platforms for Kosovo's future status.  Ahtisaari later told the press that the meeting resulted in no breakthroughs, but that the parties generally listened respectfully to each other's position.  

Ahtisaari briefed Contact Group foreign ministers on September 20, 2006, in New York City at a meeting chaired by U.S. Secretary of state [[Condoleezza Rice]].  At that meeting, the Contact Group released a press statement that reaffirmed its commitment to achieve a negotiated settlement in the course of 2006.  The statement also endorsed Ahtisaari's plans to develop a comprehensive proposal for a status settlement, which he will take to the parties.

Most international observers believe these negotiations will lead to some form of independence &lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.economist.com/displaystory.cfm?story_id=4489028 Kosovo's status - the wheels grind on]&quot;, ''The Economist'', October 6, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; which Serbian leaders still reject.  The [[Contact Group]] has said in numerous public statements that regardless of status outcome a new international mission will be established in Kosovo to supervise the implementation status settlement and guarantee minority rights.  NATO has also announced its intention to maintain KFOR in Kosovo after the status settlement.

Russian President [[Vladimir Putin]] stated in [[September]] [[2006]] that Russia may veto a [[UN Security Council]] proposal on Kosovo's final status that applies different standards than those applied to the separatist [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]]n regions of [[South Ossetia]] and [[Abkhazia]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2006/09/13/europe/EU_GEN_Russia_Kosovo.php Putin says world should regard Kosovo, separatist Georgian regions on equal footing]&quot;, ''International Herald Tribune'', September 13th 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

On the 30th Sept, 2006, the [[Parliament of Serbia|Serbian Parliament]] unanimously adopted a new constitution which describes Kosovo as an integral part of Serbia&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.focus-fen.net/index.php?id=n96849]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;; this Constitution was later adopted after a successful [[Serbian constitutional referendum, 2006|referendum on October 28-29, 2006]]. The UN Civilian Administrator in Kosovo, [[Joachim Rücker]], has argued that this move will have no effect on the final political status of Kosovo.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://kosovareport.blogspot.com/2006/10/un-administrator-says-serbian.html]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, before the referendum, a poll conducted on Aug 26 though Sept 5, 2006 in Serbia suggested that 36 percent expected independence, 29 percent were unsure, 17 percent thought the territory would be split, and 12 percent though it would remain an autonomous region of Serbia.  &lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.signonsandiego.com/news/world/20060929-0906-serbia-kosovo.html]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!-- This DOES NOT accumulate to 100% - but 94%...??? --&gt;

== Economy ==

{{main|Economy of Kosovo}}

Kosovo has one of the poorest economies in Europe, with a per capita income estimated at 1,565 [[Euro]] (2004).&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/COUNTRIES/ECAEXT/KOSOVOEXTN/0,,contentMDK:20629286~menuPK:297777~pagePK:1497618~piPK:217854~theSitePK:297770,00.html]&lt;/ref&gt; Despite substantial development subsidies from all Yugoslav republics, Kosovo was the poorest province of Yugoslavia.&lt;ref&gt;Christian Science Monitor 1982-01-15, &quot;Why Turbulent Kosovo has Marble Sidewalks but Troubled Industries&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, over the course of the 1990s, poor economic policies, international sanctions, weak access to external trade and finance, and ethnic conflict severely damaged the economy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/COUNTRIES/ECAEXT/KOSOVOEXTN/0,,menuPK:297775~pagePK:141159~piPK:141110~theSitePK:297770,00.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

Kosovo's economy remains weak. After a jump in 2000 and 2001 [[GDP]] growth was negative in 2002 and 2003 and is expected to be around 3 percent 2004-2005, with domestic sources of growth unable to compensate for the declining foreign assistance. [[Inflation]] is low, while the budget posted a deficit for the first time in 2004. Kosovo has high external deficits. In 2004, the deficit of the balance of goods and services was close to 70 percent of [[GDP]]. Remittances from Kosovars living abroad accounts for an estimated 13 percent of [[GDP]], and foreign assistance for around 34 percent of [[GDP]].&lt;ref&gt;http://ec.europa.eu/economy_finance/publications/enlargement_papers/2005/elp26en.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

Most economic development since 1999 has taken place in the trade, retail and the construction sectors. The private sector that has emerged since 1999 is mainly small-scale. The industrial sector remains weak and the electric power supply remains unreliable, acting as a key constraint. Unemployment remains pervasive, at around 40-50% of the labor force.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.eciks.org/english/lajme.php?action=total_news&amp;main_id=386&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://ec.europa.eu/economy_finance/publications/enlargement_papers/2005/elp26en.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; 

UNMIK introduced ''de-facto'' an external trade regime and customs administration on September 3, 1999 when it set customs border controls in Kosovo. All goods imported in Kosovo face a flat 10% customs duty fee.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.buyusa.gov/kosovo/en/doingbusinessinkosovo.html&lt;/ref&gt; These taxes are collected from all Tax Collection Points installed at the borders of Kosovo, including those between Kosovo and  Serbia.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.seerecon.org/kosovo/documents/wb_econ_report/wb-kosovo-econreport-2-2.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; UNMIK and Kosovo institutions have signed Free Trade Agreements with [[Croatia]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.b92.net/eng/news/globe-article.php?yyyy=2006&amp;mm=10&amp;dd=02&amp;nav_category=123&amp;nav_id=37090 Croatia, Kosovo sign Interim Free Trade Agreement], [[B92]], 2 October 2006&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bosnia and Hercegovina]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.euinkosovo.org/upload_press/4.06%20-%20UNMIK%20and%20Bosnia%20and%20Herzegovina%20Initial%20Free%20Trade%20Agreement%2017.2.06.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Albania]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.kosovo-eicc.org/oek/index.php?page_id=64&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.buyusa.gov/kosovo/en/doingbusinessinkosovo.html&lt;/ref&gt;

Macedonia is Kosovo's largest import and export market (averaging €220 million and €9 million respectively), followed by Serbia-Montenegro (€111 million and €5 million), Germany and Turkey.[http://siteresources.worldbank.org/INTKOSOVO/147270-1121700806276/20953280/Kosovo_Economic_Briefing_april.pdf]

The [[Euro]] is the official currency of Kosovo and used by UNMIK and the government bodies.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.euinkosovo.org/uk/invest/invest.php&lt;/ref&gt; The Serbian [[Dinar]] is used in the Serbian populated parts.

The economy has been seriously weakened by Kosovo's still-unresolved international status, which has made it difficult to attract investment and loans.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/business/4509781.stm Brussels offers first Kosovo loan]&quot;, BBC News Online, 3 May 2005&lt;/ref&gt; The province's economic weakness has produced a thriving black economy in which smuggled petrol, cigarettes and cement are major commodities. The prevalence of official corruption and the pervasive influence of organised crime gangs has caused serious concern internationally. The United Nations has made the fight against corruption and organised crime a high priority, pledging a &quot;zero tolerance&quot; approach.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.kosovo.undp.org/Projects/TIK/tik.asp Transparency Initiative for Kosovo (TIK)&quot;, UN Development Programme in Kosovo&lt;/ref&gt;

== Demographics ==
{{main|Demographic history of Kosovo}}
[[Image:Kosovo ethnic 2005.png|right|thumb|270px|Ethnic composition of Kosovo in [[2005]] according to the [[OSCE]]]]
According to the Kosovo in Figures 2005 Survey of the Statistical Office of Kosovo,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ks-gov.net/esk/esk/pdf/english/general/kosovo_figures_05.pdf  &lt;/ref&gt; Kosovo's total population is estimated between 1.9 and 2.2 million in the following ethnic proportions:
* ''88%'' [[Albanians]] (between 1,972,000 and 2,100,000) 
* ''7%'' [[Serbs]] (between 126,000 and 140,000) 
* ''1.9%'' [[Bosniaks]] (between 34,200 and 38,000) 
* ''1.7%'' [[Roma people|Roma]] (between 30,600 and 34,000) (see also [[Roma in Mitrovica Camps]])
* ''1%'' [[Turkish people|Turks]] (between 18,000 and 20,000)
* ''0,5%'' [[Gorani (Kosovo)|Gorani]] (approx. 10,000)

However, the figures are highly disputable. Some estimates are that there is an Albanian majority well above 90 percent. The population census is set to take place in the near future. Others give much higher figures for Roma and Turks.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.salon.com/news/1999/03/31newsa.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.serbianunity.net/news/world_articles/Dragnich1098.html&lt;/ref&gt; There was also a small minority of [[Circassians]] in [[Kosovo Polje]] but they were repatriated to the [[Republic of Adygea]], in Southern [[Russia]]. The ethnic Albanian Kosovo Liberation Army is thought to have threatened the Adygs.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/143667.stm BBC News: ''Circassians flee Kosovo conflict''. Sunday, August 2, 1998 Published at 01:01 GMT 02:01 UK&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of the Albanians in Kosovo are [[Muslims]] and most Serbs are [[Eastern Orthodox]], even though Kosovo Albanians do not define their national identity through religion. Most of them are non-practising Muslims. About 5% of the Albanians in Kosovo are [[Catholics]]. Atheism is also common among both Albanians and Serbs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crisisgroup.org/home/index.cfm?id=1591&amp;l=1 Religion in Kosovo] - International Crisis Group&lt;/ref&gt;

== Subdivisions ==

''Main article: [[Subdivisions of Kosovo]], also see: [[Municipalities of Kosovo]].''

Kosovo is divided into 7 districts:
*[[Prishtina District|Prishtina/Pristina District]]
*[[Prizreni District|Prizreni/Prizren District]]
*[[Peja District|Peja/Peć District]]
*[[Ferizaji District|Ferizaji/Uroševac District]]
*[[Gjakova District|Gjakova/Đakovica District]]
*[[Mitrovica District|Mitrovica/Kosovska Mitrovica District]]
*[[Gjilani District|Gjilani/Gnjilane District]]

[[North Kosovo]] maintains its own government, infrastructure and institutions by its dominant ethnic [[Serb]] population in the [[Mitrovica District]], on the [[Leposavic]], [[Zvecan]] and [[Zubin Potok]] municipalities and the northern part of [[Kosovska Mitrovica]].

== Cities ==
[[Image:Prishtina maj 2005.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Prishtina]]/[[Priština]].]]
List of largest cities in Kosovo (with population figures in 2006):&lt;ref&gt;http://www.world-gazetteer.com/wg.php?x=&amp;men=gcis&amp;lng=en&amp;dat=32&amp;srt=npan&amp;col=aohdq&amp;geo=-244&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Prishtina]]/[[Priština]] (562,686)
*[[Prizreni]]/[[Prizren]] (165,227)
*[[Ferizaji]]/[[Uroševac]] (97,741)
*[[Gjakova]]/[[Đakovica]] (97,156)
*[[Peja]]/[[Peć]] (95,190)
*[[Gjilani]]/[[Gnjilane]] (91,595)
*[[Mitrovica (Kosovo)|Mitrovica]]/[[Kosovska Mitrovica]] (86,359)
*[[Podujeva]]/[[Podujevo]] (48,526)

== Culture ==
===Music===
[[Music]] has always been part of the [[Albanian]] culture. Although in Kosovo music is diverse (as it got mixed with the cultures of different regimes dominating in Kosovo), authentic Albanian music (see ''[[World Music]]'') does still exist. It is characterized by use of ''[[çiftelia]]'' (an authentic Albanian instrument), ''mandolin'', ''mandola'' and ''percussion''.
In Kosovo, along with modern music, [[folk]] music is very popular. There are many folk [[singers]] and ensembles.  [[European classical music|Classical music]] is also well known in Kosovo.
The modern music in Kosovo has its origin from the Western countries. The main modern genres include: [[Pop (music)|Pop]], [[Hip hop music|Hip Hop]], [[Rock (music)|Rock]] and [[Jazz]]. The most notable rock bands are: Gjurmët, Troja, Votra, Diadema, Humus, Asgjë sikur Dielli, Kthjellu, [[Cute Babulja]], [[Babilon]], etc. Ilir Bajri is a notable [[jazz]] and [[Electronic Music|electronic]] musician.

[[Leonora Jakupi]] and [[Adelina Ismajli]] are two of the most popular commercial singers in Kosovo today.

There are some notable music festivals in Kosovo:
* ''Rock për Rock'' - contains [[Rock (music)|rock]] and [[Heavy Metal music|metal]] music
* ''Polifest'' - contains all kinds of genres (usually [[Hip hop music|hip hop]], commercal [[Pop (music)|pop]], unusually [[Rock (music)|rock]] and never [[Heavy Metal music|metal]])
* ''Showfest'' - contains all kinds of genres (usually [[Hip hop music|hip hop]], commercal [[Pop (music)|pop]], unusually [[Rock (music)|rock]] and never [[Heavy Metal music|metal]])
* ''Videofest'' - contains all kinds of genres
* ''Kush Këndon Lutet Dy Herë'' - contains all kinds of genres which have [[christian]] [[lyrics]]

Kosovo Radiotelevisions like ''RTK'', ''21'' and ''KTV'' have their musical charts.

:''See also: [[List of Albanians#Musicians|Kosovo's and Albania's musicians]]''

== List of Presidents ==
List of the presidents of Kosovo:&lt;ref&gt;http://www.worldstatesmen.org/Yugoslavia.html#Kosovo&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Fatmir Sejdiu]], [[10 February]] [[2006]] - present
* [[Ibrahim Rugova]], [[4 March]] [[2002]] - 21 January 2006

== List of Prime Ministers ==
* [[Bujar Bukoshi]]
* [[Bajram Rexhepi]], [[2002]]-[[2004]]
* [[Ramush Haradinaj]], [[2004]]-[[2005]]
* [[Bajram Kosumi]], [[2005]]-[[2006]]
* [[Agim Çeku]], [[2006]]-present

== Gallery ==
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Kosovo_government.jpg|The building of the [[Government of Kosovo]] in [[Prishtina]]/[[Priština]].
Image:Prizen kosovo.jpg|[[Prizreni]]/[[Prizren]].
Image:Gjakova.jpg|[[Gjakova]]/[[Đakovica]].
Image:French Peugeot P4 dsc06852.jpg|[[KFOR]].
Image:Rahoveci.jpg|[[Rahovec]]/[[Orahovac]].
Image:Ne Udhetim 132.jpg|Center of [[Prishtina]]/[[Priština]], monument to [[Skenderbeg]].
Image:Decani.jpg|A 14th-century fresco in [[Visoki Dečani monastery]].
Image:Gjerovica new.JPG|[[Gjerovica]]/[[Đeravica]].
Image:Bjeshket Junikut.JPG|[[Juniku Mountains]]/[[Junik Mountains]].
Image:VeshjeKombetare.JPG|[[Albanians in Kosovo|Kosovo Albanian]] ethnic costume/dance.  
Image:Erzengelkloster2.jpg|[[Serbs in Kosovo|Serb]] monastery near river [[Bistrica]].
Image:Bibloteka Kombëtare e Kosovës.jpg|National Public Library in [[Prishtina]]/[[Priština]].
Image:League of Prizren building.jpg|[[League of Prizren]] building in [[Prizren]].
Image:White Drini 05 01.jpg|Bridge &quot;Ura e Fshejte&quot; on the [[White Drin]] river.
Image:Vllaznimi KuqezinjeteJakoves 01.JPG|Sport fans of sport club [[Vëllaznimi]], [[Gjakovë]]/[[Đakovica]].
Image:Prishtinë SQ.JPG|Stadium in [[Prishtina]]/[[Priština]].
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== See also ==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
* [[History of Kosovo]]
* [[Assembly of Kosovo]]
* [[Government of Kosovo]]
* [[Prime Minister of Kosovo]]
* [[President of Kosovo]]
* [[Albanians in Kosovo]]
* [[Kosovo war]]
* [[Serbs in Kosovo]]
* [[Post and Telecom of Kosovo]]
{{col-2}}
* [[Battle of Kosovo|Battle of Kosovo (1389)]]
* [[Subdivisions of Kosovo]]
* [[National awakening and the birth of Albania]]
* [[Demographic history of Kosovo]]
* [[Unrest in Kosovo]] (during March 2004)
* [[Sexual trafficking in Kosovo]]
* [[Metohija]]
* [[North Kosovo]]
{{col-end}}

== External links ==
{{sisterlinks|Kosovo}}
* [http://www.ks-gov.net/pm/?menuid=&amp;subid=&amp;lingo=2 The office of Prime Minister of Kosovo] English version
* [http://www.assembly-kosova.org/?krye=home&amp;lang=en Kosovo Assembly (Kuvendi i Kosovës)] English version
* [http://www.visitkosova.org/ The Official Webportal of Tourism in Kosovo]
* [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/07/23/AR2006072300564.html Serbia's Intransigence] Washington Post Editorial July 24, 2006
* [http://ec.europa.eu/economy_finance/publications/enlargement_papers/2005/elp26en.pdf EU Commission report on economic development in Accession countries, including Kosovo]
* [http://www.balkanforums.com Kosovo and the Balkans] - Discussion Forum
* [http://ec.europa.eu/comm/enlargement/serbia_montenegro/kosovo_economical_profile.htm European Commission information on Kosovo] 
* [http://www.ks-gov.net/esk/index_english.htm Kosovo Statistical Office (SOK)]
* [http://digital.library.unt.edu/govdocs/crs/search.tkl?q=kosovo&amp;search_crit=fulltext&amp;search=Search&amp;date1=Anytime&amp;date2=Anytime&amp;type=form  Congressional Research Service (CRS) Reports regarding Kosovo]
* {{wikitravel}}
* [http://www.rtklive.com  RTK - Kosovo's public television - news in Albanian, Serbian, Turkish and Roma]
* [https://www.osce.org/documents/mik/1999/11/1620_en.pdf Human Rights in Kosovo: As Seen, As Told. Volume I, October 1998 - June 1999].
* [http://www.lib.utexas.edu/maps/kosovo.html Kosovo maps from the Perry-Castañeda Library Map Collection]
* [http://www.kosovakosovo.com/ KosovaKosovo] A source of information reflecting both sides’ claims in the dispute
* [http://www.nato.int/kosovo/ KFOR] [[NATO]] led peacekeeping force in Kosovo.
* [http://www.unmikonline.org/ UNMIK] [[UN]] led civilian administration in Kosovo.
* [http://www.euinkosovo.org/index.php EU] EU Pillar in Kosovo. 
* [http://www.chmouel.com/geeklog/gallery/gallery_individual.php/mkosovo/ A collection of photos from Kosovo]
* [http://www.otvoreno.org.yu/ Otvoreno ] A place where Serbian politicians speak openly on the Kosovo issue
* [http://www.iom.ipko.org/ IOM ] International Organization for Migration 
* [http://www.crisisgroup.org/home/index.cfm?id=1243&amp;l=1 (ICG)] International Crisis Group, a source of independent analysis on Kosovo issues.
* [http://www.csdbalkans.org/roma Kosovo Roma Oral History Project] An advocacy website for Kosovo's Roma/ Gypsies, with significant details on Kosovo's contested history.
* [http://www.xhakli.com/2004/05/kosovo-search-challenge-helping-people_25.php?show_id=108543905534062634 Kosovo Blog] Search Challenge: Helping people find information from Kosovo
* [http://www.eciks.org/english/index.php ECIKS] Economic Initiative for Kosovo, information on investment opportunities.
* [http://www.state.gov/www/regions/eur/rpt_990604_ksvo_ethnic.html US State Dept. fact sheet &quot;The Ethnic Cleansing of Kosovo&quot;]
* [http://www.state.gov/www/global/human_rights/kosovoii/homepage.html ''Ethnic Cleansing in Kosovo: An Accounting'', U.S. State Department Report, December 1999]
* [http://www.savekosovo.org/ American Council for Kosovo]
* [http://www.kosovocompromise.com/ Kosovo 2006 Making of a Compromise]

=== Pro-Albanian ===
* [http://www.newkosovo.org/ Alliance for a New Kosovo] A Policy Resource on Kosovo Independence.
* [http://www.newkosovo.org/Ceku-Kosovos%20Turn-WSJ-08%20June%202006.pdf Kosovo`s Turn] Kosovo`s Prime Minister Agim Ceku, published by Wall Street Journal, June 8, 2006
* [http://www.kosovaevidence.com KosovoEvidence.com] - movie about what happened in Kosovo during the war
* [http://www.eciks.org Economic Initiative for Kosovo] - &quot;...latest news, analysis and publications from the Kosovar economy&quot;
* [http://www.albanian.com/main/countries/kosova Albanian.com] - general information
* [http://www.alb-shkenca.org/images/stories/Why%20Independence.pdf Why Independence for Kosovo?] A summary of the case for an independent Kosovo by two Prishtina intellectuals
* [http://www.newkosovo.org/news.htm Alliance for New Kosovo] A policy resource on Kosovo independence
* [http://www.alb-net.com/index.htm Kosova Crisis Center] A collection of articles on Kosovo, in [[English language|English]].
* [http://www.aacl.com/indexmain.html AACL] Albanian American Civic League.
* [http://www.kosovalive.com/?cid=2 KosovaLive] Kosovo Albanian independent news agency (this section in [[English language|English]]).
* [http://www.savekosova.org/ American Council for Kosova] - Albanian American organization dedicated to a better understanding of the issue of Kosova by the American public
* [http://www.newkosovo.org/ The Alliance For A New Kosovo] - An American Group of Diplomats Working For Kosovo's Independence

=== Pro-Serbian ===
* [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/07/11/AR2006071101202.html Justice for Serbia], article by Vojislav Kostunica, Prime Minister of Serbia, in the Washington Post, 12 July 2006
* [http://www.srbija.sr.gov.yu/kosovo-metohija/ Serbian Government for Kosovo-Metohija] Website that focusses on the human rights situation of Serbian and other non-Albanian populations in Kosovo. 
* [http://www.rastko.org.yu/kosovo/crucified/default.htm Crucified Kosovo] Overview of destroyed Serbian Orthodox churches in Kosovo
* [http://www.kc.gov.yu/ Coordination Center of SCG and the Republic of Serbia for Kosovo]
* [http://www.tserkovnost.org/srbija/ Eastern Orthodox Resource Centre]
* [http://www.axisglobe.com/article.asp?article=689 Southern Serbia: The second Kosovo?]
* [http://www.b92.net/english/news/index.php?style=headlines&amp;nav_category=19 B92] Serbian Independent news agency
* [http://www.kosovo.net/sk/history/kosovo_origins/default.htm Hugo Roth, ''Kosovo Origins'']: a historian's comprehensive overview 
* [http://www.savekosovo.org Save Kosovo] U.S. nonprofit organization dedicated to promoting a better American understanding of the Serbian province of Kosovo and Metohija and of the critical American stake in the province’s future.

==References==
&lt;div class=&quot;references-small&quot; style=&quot;-moz-column-count:2; column-count:2;&quot;&gt;&lt;references/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


{{Kosovo}}
{{Autonomous Provinces of Serbia}}
{{Republics and autonomous provinces of the former Yugoslavia}}

[[Category:Kosovo|*]]
[[Category:Proposed countries]]

[[als:Kosova]]
[[ar:قوصوه]]
[[ast:Kosovo]]
[[zh-min-nan:Kosovo]]
[[bs:Kosovo]]
[[br:Kosovo]]
[[bg:Косово (област)]]
[[ca:Kosovo]]
[[cs:Kosovo]]
[[da:Kosovo]]
[[de:Kosovo]]
[[et:Kosovo]]
[[es:Kosovo]]
[[eo:Kosovo]]
[[fr:Kosovo]]
[[ko:코소보]]
[[hr:Kosovo]]
[[io:Kosovo]]
[[id:Kosovo]]
[[it:Kosovo]]
[[he:קוסובו ומטוחיה]]
[[la:Cosovum]]
[[lv:Kosova un Metohija]]
[[lt:Kosovas]]
[[hu:Koszovó]]
[[mk:Косово]]
[[nl:Kosovo]]
[[ja:コソボ]]
[[no:Kosovo]]
[[nn:Kosovo]]
[[oc:Kosovo]]
[[nds:Kosovo]]
[[pl:Kosowo i Metohija]]
[[pt:Kosovo]]
[[ro:Kosovo]]
[[ru:Косово и Метохия]]
[[sq:Kosova]]
[[simple:Kosovo]]
[[sl:Kosovo]]
[[sr:Косово и Метохија]]
[[sh:Kosovo i Metohija]]
[[fi:Kosovo]]
[[sv:Kosovo]]
[[tr:Kosova]]
[[uk:Косово]]
[[zh:科索沃]]</text>
