      <text xml:space="preserve">{{otheruses}}
{{POV}}
{{POV-check}}
{| {{prettyinfobox}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
&lt;big&gt;''' Kosovo '''&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/big&gt;&lt;br&gt;
|-
| style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Image:LocationKosova.PNG|300px]] 
|-
| [[Official language]]s
| [[Albanian language|Albanian]], [[Serbian language|Serbian]]
|-
| [[Capital]]
| [[Prishtinë]]/[[Priština]]
|-
| [[President of Kosovo|President]]
| [[Fatmir Sejdiu]]
|-
| [[Prime Minister of Kosovo|Prime Minister]]
| [[Agim Çeku]]
|-
| [[Area]]&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; Total&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; % water
| &lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;[[1 E10 m²|10,912]] km²&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;4,213&amp;nbsp;[[square mile|sq.&amp;nbsp;mi]]&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;n/a
|-
| valign=top | [[Population]]&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; Total ([[2003]])&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; [[Population density|Density]]&lt;br/&gt;
| &lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;2.1 million (est.)&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;220/km² (approx)&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;570/sq.&amp;nbsp;mi
|-
| valign=top | [[List of ethnic groups|Ethnic groups]]&lt;br/&gt;([[2003]])
| [[Albanians]]: 88%&lt;br/&gt;[[Serbs]]: 7%&lt;br/&gt;Others: 5%
|-
| [[Time zone]]
| [[Coordinated Universal Time|UTC]] +1
|-

|
|}


'''Kosovo''' ([[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Kosovë''/''Kosova'', [[Serbian language|Serbian]]: Косово и Метохија/''Kosovo i Metohija'') is a [[UN]]-administered province. By the [[UN Security Council]] [[Resolution 1244]] (adopted in [[1999]]), Kosovo is defined as autonomous province within former [[Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Ex-Yugoslavia]] under [[UN]] administration. Whether this will remain the case is still unclear, as the final status of Kosovo is the subject of an ongoing dispute between government of Serbia and Kosovo's government. Talks on this issue started in [[Vienna]], on [[February 20]], [[2006]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unmikonline.org/news.htm#1703 Kosovo, Serbian delegations hold new status talks under UN chairmanship]&lt;/ref&gt;.

== Geography ==

With an area of [[1 E10 m²|10,912]] [[square kilometre]]s (4,213 [[square mile|sq.&amp;nbsp;mi]]) and a population of over two million of the eve of the [[1999]] crisis, Kosovo borders [[Montenegro]] to the northwest, [[Serbia]] to the North and East; [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]] to the south, and [[Albania]] to the southwest. The largest cities are [[Prishtinë]]/[[Pristina]] the capital, with an estimated 500,000 citizens, and [[Prizren]] in the southwest with 120,000 citizens; five other towns have populations in excess of 50,000. 

== History ==
{{main|History of Kosovo}}
The Province of Kosovo and Metohija was formed autonomous to protect its regional [[Albanians|Albanian]] majority withing the [[History of Serbia|People's Republic of Serbia]] as a member of the [[SFRJ|Federal People's Republic of Yugoslavia]] in [[1945]] under the strong dictatorship of the former Partisan leader, [[Josip Broz Tito]], but with a strictly limited status. Prior to Yugoslavia's name change to the [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia]] and Serbia's to the [[History of Serbia|Socialist Republic of Serbia]] in [[1963]], the Autonomous Region of Kosovo and Metohija gained more inner autonomy. In the [[1974]] constitution, the Socialist Autonomous Province of Kosovo and Metohija's government received higher powers, including the highest governmental titles - President and Premier and a seat in the Federal Presidency which made it a ''de facto'' Socialist Republic within the SFRJ, but remaining as a Socialist Autonomous Region within the Socialist Republic of Serbia. [[Serbo-Croatian]] and [[Albanian language|Albanian]] were defined official on the Provincial level marking the two largest linguistic Kosovan groups: [[Serbs]] and [[Albanians]]. In the 1970s, an Albanian nationalist movement for more freedom desired full recognition of the Province of Kosovo and Metohija as another Republic within the Federation, while the most extreme aimed for full-scale independence. Tito's arbitrary regime dealt with the situation swiftly, but only giving it a temporary solution. The enthic composure of Kosovo and Metohija witnessed unproportional increase as the number of [[Albanians]] trippled gradually rising from almost ''65%'' to over ''80%'' and the number [[Serbs]] barelly increasing and dropping in the full share of the total population from some ''25%'' down to ''10%''.

In [[1981]] the Kosovar Albanian students organized protests seeking that Kosovo become a republic within Yugoslavia. Those protests were harshly attacked by the Serbian government. In [[1986]], the Serbian Academy of Sciences and Arts published a document [[Memorandum]] which contained heavily Serbian nationalist propaganda, based on both true and unendingly exaggerated individual events and historical suffers of the Serbian people. They were criticising the ethnic strifes in the province and the disintegration of the Yugoslav economy into separate economic sectors and territories, which was transforming the federal state into a loose confederation. During this time, [[Slobodan Milošević]]s rise to power started in [[Serbia]].

== Economy ==
[[UNMIK]] declared the [[euro]] to be the official currency of the province in [[2001]] in the course of implementing a currency reform. This was undertaken to replace the previous widespread use of the [[Deutschmark]], which had become the ''de facto'' currency even before the 1999 war. However, the [[Serbian dinar]] remains an official currency, used principally in the [[Kosovo Serb enclaves]]; it is only used sporadically outside of them. Most trade is conducted using the euro; Kosovo's administration uses the euro exclusively, and all commercial banks use the euro as the primary currency. Of other international currencies, the [[United States dollar]] and [[Swiss franc]] are the most widespread.

== Demographics ==
Ethnic Albanians comprise almost 90% of the population of the province. In the aftermath of the conflict some one thousand non-Albanians, particularly [[Serbs]] and [[Roma]] either followed Serb soldiers as they withdrew, were forcibly expelled by the Albanian majority or fled the province to escape perceived threats of revenge by Albanians. The non-Albanian population of Kosovo has continued to fall since the arrival of NATO and the UN as a result of violence, perceived intimidation, and economic hardship. Many still live in communal camps in [[Serbia]] or [[Macedonia]] cared for by international relief agencies. However, there have been many attempts by Kosovo's government to resettle non-Albanians in the region which have largely been successful, including the resettlement of well over one thousand Serbians and Roma from 2004 - 2005. The Kosovo government has been widely praised for paying for the rebuilding of Serb houses in the aftermath of the 2004 riots. This has been marked as the first case of reparations in the history of the Balkans. 

According to the 2000 Living Standard Measurement Survey of the Statistical Office of Kosovo[http://www.sok-kosovo.org/pdf/population/Kosovo_population.pdf], Kosovo's total population is estimated between 1,8 and 2,0 million in the following ethnic proportions:
* ''88%'' [[Albanians]] (between 1,584,000 and 1,733,600) 
* ''7%'' [[Serbs]] (between 126,000 and 140,000)	
* ''3%'' [[Muslims by nationality|Muslims]] and [[Bosniaks]] (54 to 60 thousand) 
* ''2%'' [[Roma people|Roma]] (36 to 40 thousand) (see also [[Roma in Mitrovica Camps]])
* ''1%'' [[Turkish people|Turks]] (18 to 20 thousand)
However, the figures are highly disputable. Some estimates are that there is an Albanian majority well above 90 percent. Others give much higher figures for Roma and Turks [http://www.siri-us.com/backgrounders/Archives_Kosovo/Kosovo-Milosevic.html][http://www.salon.com/news/1999/03/31newsa.html][http://www.serbianunity.net/news/world_articles/Dragnich1098.html]

== List of Presidents ==
* [[Ibrahim Rugova]], [[1992]]-[[2006]] (deceased)
* [[Fatmir Sejdiu]], [[2006]]-present

== List of Prime Ministers ==
* [[Bajram Rexhepi]], [[2002]]-[[2004]]
* [[Ramush Haradinaj]], [[2004]]-[[2005]]
* [[Bajram Kosumi]], [[2005]]-[[2006]]
* [[Agim Çeku]], [[2006]]-present

== See also ==
* [[Vinnea meeteng]]
* [[Assembly of Kosovo]]
* [[Government of Kosovo]]
* [[Prime Minister of Kosovo]]
* [[President of Kosovo]]
* [[Post and Telecom of Kosovo]]
* [[Battle of Kosovo|Battle of Kosovo (1389)]]
* [[Subdivisions of Kosovo]]
* [[National awakening and the birth of Albania]]
* [[Demographic history of Kosovo]]

== External links ==
{{sisterlinks|Kosovo}}
* [http://www.balkanforums.com Kosovo and the Balkans] - Discussion Forum
* [http://digital.library.unt.edu/govdocs/crs/search.tkl?q=kosovo&amp;search_crit=fulltext&amp;search=Search&amp;date1=Anytime&amp;date2=Anytime&amp;type=form  Congressional Research Service (CRS) Reports regarding Kosovo]
* {{wikitravel}}
* [http://www.rtklive.com  RTK - Kosova's public television - news in Albanian, Serbian, Turkish and Roma]
* [https://www.osce.org/documents/mik/1999/11/1620_en.pdf Human Rights in Kosovo: As Seen, As Told. Volume I, October 1998 - June 1999].
* [http://www.lib.utexas.edu/maps/kosovo.html Kosovo maps from the Perry-Castañeda Library Map Collection]
* [http://www.kosovakosovo.com/ A source of information reflecting both sides’ claims in the dispute] 

=== Pro-Albanian ===
* [http://BalkanUpdate.blogspot.com Balkan Update]- A blog with news, analysis and the lates updates from Balkans
* [http://www.eciks.org Economic Initiative for Kosovo] - &quot;...latest news, analysis and publications from the Kosovar economy&quot;
* [http://www.albanian.com/main/countries/kosova Albanian.com] - general information
* [http://www.kosovaelire.com/ Kosova e lirë] (Free Kosova) -- Material about Kosovars and Albanians in Albanian language. 
* [http://www.alb-shkenca.org/images/stories/Why%20Independence.pdf Why Independence for Kosovo?] A summary of the case for an independent Kosovo by two Prishtina intellectuals
* [http://www.newkosovo.org/news.htm Alliance for New Kosovo] A policy resource on Kosovo Independence
* [http://www.kosovareport.org/news.htm Kosovareport] A collection of news on Kosovo, in English, gathered from many agencies.

=== Pro-Serbian ===
* [http://www.rastko.org.yu/kosovo/crucified/default.htm Account of destroyed Serbian Orthodox churches in Kosovo and Metohija]
* [http://groups.yahoo.com/group/decani/ Kosovo Newsgroup archive]
* [http://www.kc.gov.yu/ Coordination Center of SCG and the Republic of Serbia for Kosovo]
* [http://www.tserkovnost.org/srbija/ Eastern Orthodox Resource Centre]
* [http://www.axisglobe.com/article.asp?article=689 Southern Serbia: The second Kosovo?]
* [http://serbo.blogspot.com Kosovo News blog]

[[Category:Disputed territories]]
[[Category:Kosovo]]
[[Category:United Nations]]


[[ar:قوصوة]]
[[ast:Kosovo]]
[[bg:تîٌîâî]]
[[zh-min-nan:Kosovo]]
[[bs:Kosovo]]
[[ca:Kosovo]]
[[cs:Kosovo]]
[[da:Kosovo]]
[[de:Kosovo]]
[[et:Kosovo]]
[[es:Kosovo]]
[[eo:Kosovo]]
[[fr:Kosovo]]
[[ko:ؤع¼ز؛¸]]
[[hr:Kosovo]]
[[id:Kosovo]]
[[it:Kosovo]]
[[he:קוסובו ומטוחיה]]
[[lt:Kosovas]]
[[hu:Koszovó]]
[[mk:Косово]]
[[nl:Kosovo]]
[[nds:Kosovo]]
[[ja:コソボ]]
[[no:Kosovo]]
[[nn:Kosovo]]
[[pl:Kosowo]]
[[pt:Kosovo]]
[[ro:Kosovo]]
[[ru:Косово]]
[[sq:Kosova]]
[[sr:Косово]]
[[fi:Kosovo]]
[[sv:Kosovo]]
[[tr:Kosova]]
[[uk:Косово]]
[[zh:科索沃]]</text>
