      <text xml:space="preserve">[[de:Kosovo]]
[[nl:Kosovo]]
'''Kosovo and Metohia''' ([[Serbian language|Serbian]]: &amp;#1050;&amp;#1086;&amp;#1089;&amp;#1086;&amp;#1074;&amp;#1086; &amp;#1080; &amp;#1052;&amp;#1077;&amp;#1090;&amp;#1086;&amp;#1093;&amp;#1080;&amp;#1112;&amp;#1072;; [[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Kosova'') or '''Kosovo''' is a region in the western [[Balkan Peninsula]] with an [[Albanians|Albanian]] population (estimated at 80% prior to the international conflict of 1999, but now somewhat larger owing to the [[ethnic cleansing]] of [[Serbs]] and other non-Albanians; see [[Kosovo population data-points]]). &quot;Kosovo&quot; is from &quot;Kosovo Polje&quot; that means &quot;Blackbird's field&quot; in [[Serbian language]], &quot;Metohia&quot; is a Greek word which denotes church-owned land.

Its international status is anomalous in that although it is formally a province of the Republic of [[Serbia]], actual administration is presently conducted by the [[United Nations]] with no involvement on the part of the Serbian governments. A [[parliament]] was elected in November [[2001]] and [[Ibrahim Rugova]] was selected as president in March [[2002]], however the UN retained control of security, justice and external affairs.

With an area of [[1 E10 m2|10,887]] [[square kilometre|km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;]] and a population of almost 2 million on the eve of the 1999 crisis, Kosovo borders with [[Montenegro]] to the northwest, rest of [[Serbia]] to the north and east, the [[Former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia]] to the south and [[Albania]] to the southwest. The largest cities are [[Prishtina|Pri&amp;#353;tina]], the capital, with 190,000 inhabitants, and [[Prizren]] in the southwest with 120,000: five other towns have populations in excess of 50,000.

Kosovo's anomalous status is the result of the [[Kosovo War]] of March-June [[1999]], in the course of which air strikes against the [[Yugoslavia|Federal republic of Yugoslavia]]'s armed forces and civilian infrastructure, by members of the [[North Atlantic Treaty Organization]] forced the signing of the [[Kumanovo agreement]] which provided for the withdrawal of military and the province's occupation by a NATO-led international force (KFOR) including also [[Russia]]n troops (no longer serving as of July [[2003]]).

Entered by Serbs migrating from the north-east around the early 7th century AD, Kosovo was a centre of the medieval Serbian kingdom until its conquest by the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman Turks]] in the late 14th century. The existing Albanian population is greatly formed by migrants from the south-west (modern [[Albania]]) during the centuries of Ottoman rule (particularly during and after the 17th century), when Islam also became the faith of most of the Albanian people.

Kosovo became a part of the Kingdom of Serbia during the [[Balkan Wars|First Balkan War]] of 1912-1913, at which time about 60% of the population was Serb (see [[Kosovo population data-points]]). [[Yugoslavia]]n [[communist]] government created Kosovo as an autonomous region of Serbia in 1946 and an autonomous province in 1963. Kosovo enjoyed almost complete self-government under predominantly Albanian local communist party leaders from 1974 until 1989, when its autonomy was revoked by referendum which implemented a new, more democratic, Serbian constitution, following widespread discrimination against Serbs.

Albanian opposition to sovereignty of Yugoslavia and especially Serbia, which had surfaced in rioting (1968 and March 1981) in the capital [[Prishtina|Pri&amp;#353;tina]], subsequently took the form of separatist agitation by opposition political groups and armed action from 1996 by the &quot;[[Kosovo Liberation Army]]&quot; (''Ushtria Çlirimtare e Kosovës'', or UÇK). The Serbian police and UÇK actions by 1998 created a state of low intensity warfare with some 2000 dying prior to [[Kosovo War]] of [[1999]].

Both [[NATO]] and the [[United Nations|UN]] continue to recognise Kosovo as a part of Serbia, but with the departure since 1999 of much of the Serb population and the reluctance of local Albanians to see Serbian sovereignty restored in practice, it is difficult to imagine how the removal of de facto Serbian authority in the province can be reconciled with assurances of Serbia's continued territorial integrity given by the NATO powers and reaffirmed (June 1999) in UN Security Council resolution 1244. 

At the same time, it is also difficult to see how [[Serbia]] would consent to recognizing independence of Kosovo, and without Serbia's approval, recognition of Kosovo independence would be extremely problematic under [[international law]] as it would be a violation of the principles of [[territorial integrity]] and [[non-interference in internal affairs]]. The most likely outcome is the indefinite continuation of the current situation.

==External links==
* [http://www.b92.net/english/news/index.php?order=priority&amp;nav_category=19 News from B92 Belgrade]
* [http://www.serbia.sr.gov.yu/news/kosovo News from the Serbian Government]
* [http://www.kosovo.com/default4.html News from the Serbian Orthodox Church] 
* [http://www.kosovapress.com Kosova Press - the KLA news agency]
* [http://www.lib.utexas.edu/maps/kosovo.html Kosovo maps from the Perry-Castañeda Library Map Collection]
* [http://www.serbia.sr.gov.yu/coordination_centre/index.html Serb Kosovo Coordination Center]</text>
