      <text xml:space="preserve">{{otheruses}} {{seealso|Names of Kosovo}}
{{Infobox Kosovo}}&lt;!--

Please be very careful in editing the introduction of this article. The Arbitration Committee has placed this article on probation. If any editor makes disruptive edits, they may be banned by an administrator from this and related articles, or other reasonably related pages. See the talk page for more information.

--&gt;
'''Kosovo''' &lt;!--Please leave the following language order as Albanian followed by Serbian: this is alphabetical and as neutral as we can get. Serbian is listed first in the infobox as balance--&gt;([[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Kosova'' or ''Kosovë'', [[Serbian language|Serbian]]: {{lang|sr-Cyrl|Косово и Метохија}}, [[Transliteration|transliterated]] {{lang|sr-Latn|''Kosovo i Metohija''}}; also {{lang|sr-Cyrl|Космет}}, transliterated {{lang|sr-Latn|''Kosmet''}}) is a region in southern [[Serbia]] which has been under [[United Nations]] [[United Nations Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo|administration]] since [[1999]]. While Serbia's [[sovereignty]] is recognised by the international community, in practice Serbian governance in the province is virtually non-existent (see also [[Constitutional status of Kosovo]]). The province is governed by the [[United Nations Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo]] (UNMIK) with the help of the local [[Provisional Institutions of Self-Government]] (PISG), as well as security provided by the [[NATO]]-led [[Kosovo Force]] (KFOR). 

The Province of Kosovo borders [[Montenegro]], [[Albania]], and the [[Republic of Macedonia]]. It has a population of just over two million people, predominantly ethnic [[Albanians]], with smaller populations of [[Serbs]], [[Turkish people|Turks]], [[Bosniaks]], [[Romani people]], and other ethnic groups. [[Priština]] is the capital and largest city. 

The province is the subject of a long-running political and territorial dispute between the Serbian (and previously, the [[Yugoslavia|Yugoslav]]) government and Kosovo's largely ethnic-Albanian population. International negotiations began in [[2006]] to determine the final status of Kosovo (''See [[Kosovo status process]]'').

== Geography

== History ==
{{main|History of Kosovo}}
{{see also|Demographic history of Kosovo}}

The last disputed region of the now defunct communist Yugoslavia, the province of Kosovo has an extensive and rich history. Inhabited by several different groups, it was initially (circa 1300 B.C.E.) inhabited by [[Illyrians]], which eventually became incorporated into the Roman empire and subsequently the Byzantine empire. From c. 6th century AD it was settled by [[Slavs]] (Serbians) migrating from the north. It was conquered by the Ottoman empire during their take-over of south-eastern Europe. However, it was re-occupied by the Serbs after the defeat of the Ottoman Empire in the 1912-13 [[Balkan Wars]].  Kosovo has since been a region or province of modern Yugoslavia and its successor state of Serbia.

=== Kosovo in the Middle-Ages ===
{{see also|History of Medieval Kosovo}}
[[Image:Serbia boundaries CIA.jpg|thumb|righ|230px|Map: ''&quot;Kosovo: History of a Balkan Hot Spot&quot;'', 1998]]
The Kosovo region has been taken, retaken, and ruled by several empires. It lies both on the outer fringes of the [[Byzantine Empire]] and directly in the path of [[Slavs|Slavic]] invasions in the [[5th century|5th]] and [[6th century|6th]] centuries, culminating with the arrival of [[White Serbs]] in the first half of the [[7th century|7th]] who formed the realm of [[Rascia]], the center of which was in northwest Kosovo. From [[863]] to [[971]], most of the remainder of Kosovo was ruled by [[Bulgaria]], cementing the ''slavic'' character of Kosovo. Various Slavic rebellions wanted to restore the Bulgarian Empire, like the one from Macedonia in [[976]] to [[1014]] or the one raised in the 1040s. The Serbs from [[Doclea]] also tried in [[1070]] to [[1072]] to restore the Bulgarian Empire, but they were defeated in the Battle of Sitnica. From the 1090s, most of Kosovo is incorporated into the Grand Principality of Rascia under the [[Vojislavljević|Vukanović]] family. Although it would not be until [[1208]] that Grand Prince Stefan Nemanjić would finally conquer [[Prizren]] that Kosovo got fully incorporated into Serbia. 

During the rule of the [[Nemanjić]] dynasty, many [[Serbian Orthodox]] churches and monasteries were built throughout Kosovo. Kosovo became the core of the Serbian realm in the second half of the 13th and in the 14th century; the [[Nemanjić]] rulers alternatively used both [[Prizren]] and [[Priština]] as their capitals. Large estates were given to the monasteries in Metohija (Western Kosovo) (which included parts of modern-day Albania and Montenegro). The most prominent churches in Kosovo - the [[Patriarchate]] at [[Pec]], the church at [[Gračanica]] and the monastery at [[Visoki Dečani]] near [[Dečani]] - were all adopted during this period. At the end of the 13th century, Pec became the center of the [[Serbian Orthodox Church]], which became a Patriarchate in [[1346]]. Kosovo was economically important, as the modern Kosovo capital [[Priština]] was a major trading centre on routes leading to ports on the [[Adriatic Sea]]. As well, mining was an important industry in [[Novo Brdo]] and [[Janjevo]] which had its communities of émigré [[Saxons|Saxon]] miners and [[Republic of Ragusa|Ragusan]] merchants.

Ethnic identity from the [[Middle Ages]] was somewhat fluid throughout Europe, and people at that time do not appear to have defined themselves rigidly by a single ethnic identity. Those of Slavic origin, particularly of the Serbian background, appear to have been the dominant population culturally and were probably a demographic majority as well. 

In the second half of the 14th century the Serbian Empire fell into feudal anarchy on the death of [[Tsar]] [[Stefan Dušan]] and local fiefdoms rose to power and prominence in their respective lands, with Kosovo becoming a Lordship under the [[Branković]] dynasty. The Ottoman Emirate took the opportunity to exploit Serbian weakness and invaded, with the epic [[Battle of Kossovo]] occurring in [[1389]]. In [[1455]], the Ottoman Empire conquered Kosovo from Serbia.

===Ottoman Empire===
{{seealso|Vilayet of Kosovo}}
{{seealso|History of Ottoman Serbia}}

The [[Ottoman Empire|Ottomans]] brought [[Islamisation]] with them, particularly in towns, and later also created the [[Vilayet of Kosovo]] as one of the Ottoman territorial entities. Ottoman rule lasted for about 500 years, in which time the Ottomans were the absolute paramount power in the region. Many Christians adopted Islam, particularly many Bosnians and Albanians, whose populations became predominantly Islamic. The Ottomans administered through a ''millet'' system whereby Muslim subjects received more tax concessions and personal liberties compared to Christians and Jews &lt;ref&gt; The Balkans: from Constantinople to Communsim. Dennis P Hupchick &lt;/ref&gt;. 

Kosovo was taken temporarily by the Austrian forces during the War of [[1683]]&amp;ndash;[[1699]] with help of Serbs. After the Austrians retreated, many Serbs had to flee from Kosovo to evade Ottoman reprisals. In [[1690]], the [[Serbian Patriarch of Peć]] [[Arsenije III]], who previously escaped a certain death, led 37,000 families from Kosovo, to evade [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] wrath. The people that followed him were mostly [[Serbs]] —but they were likely followed by Christians of other ethnic backgrounds. 

The Albanian people of the area also continued to intermittently struggle against occupation, yet suffered less reprisals at the hands of the Ottomans. Quite a few rose to prominence in the Turkish system, as administrators and as soldiers. During this time, many Albanians moved into Kosovo, filling in lands and houses vacated by fleeing Christians &lt;ref&gt; the Balkans: from Constantinople to Communism &lt;/ref&gt;. Whilst relations between Serbs and Albanians were peaceful initially, this eventually deteriorated. At the outset, Christians and Muslim-converts celebrated each other's religious holidays together. However, later, many young Albanian Islamics participated in Turkish massacres of Christians &lt;ref&gt; Alex Dragnich and Slavko Todorovich. Serbs and Albanians Under Turkish Rule &lt;/ref&gt;, which in turn would be retaliated upon by the Serbs when they got the upper hand. This period has by many been identified as the catalyst of the subsequent deterioration of the relationship between Serbian and Albanian peoples. Apart from religious tensions, the subsequent political outlook changed for the two people. As the Ottoman empire began to collapse, Serbia aimed to re-incorporate Kosovo into the heart of its realm, whereas many Albanians were content with their new-found authority within the Ottoman system.

With ongoing oppression from the Ottomans, migrations of Christian people out of Kosovo continued until the Ottoman empire finally collapsed. Many Serbs (and Vlachs) moved to Vojvodina and the Krajina region. Also, many of the minority of Albanians that remained Christian also migrated to towns in Dalmatia.

===Modern era===

{{seealso|History of Modern Kosovo}}

[[Image:SAP Kosovo.png|thumb|left|275px|[[Socialist Autonomous Province of Kosovo]] of [[Socialist Republic of Serbia|Socialist Serbia]] inside [[Socialist Yugoslavia]], 1974-1990]]
During the 19th Century part of modern Kosovo was reintegrated into 'Old Serbia' following a Peace Accord of 1878 which brought the cities of Priština and Kosovska Mitrovica under Serbian control whilst leaving the remainder of Kosovo under Ottoman authority. An ethnic-Albanian Prizren League was formed which sought to unite all of the Albanian provinces of the Ottoman Empire, but which was ultimately defeated by Ottoman forces. During the [[First Balkan War]] of [[1912]] most of Kosovo was retaken by the [[Kingdom of Serbia]] while the region of Metohija (know as the Dukagjini Valley to ethnic-Albanians) was taken by the Kingdom of Montenegro. Populations of ethnic Serbs and Albanians tended to shift following territorial conquests.

During World War I, Kosovo was occupied by the Bulgarian and Austro-Hungarian forces following a serious defeat of Serbian and allied armies in 1915. Returning in 1918, the Serbian army pushed the central powers out of Kosovo as the war came to a close. Following WWI, the [[Kingdom of the Serbs, Croats and Slovenes]] was formed, bringing together Serbian Kosovo and Montenegrin Metohija within the new kingdom. The partition of Yugoslavia by the invading [[Axis Powers]] from 1941 and 1945 awarded most of the territory to the Italian-occupied [[Greater Albania]], and a smaller part of it to [[Nazi Germany|German]]-occupied Serbia and [[Greater Bulgaria]]. Both wars were occasions for inter-ethnic violence and both voluntary and forced population shifts.</text>
