      <text xml:space="preserve">{{semi-protected}}
{{pp-move|small=yes}}
{{inuse}}
&lt;!--

Please be very careful in editing the introduction of this article. The Arbitration Committee has placed this article on probation. While this occurred in 2006, it was never lifted; thus, this page is still under probation. If any editor makes disruptive edits, they may be banned by an administrator from this and related articles, or other reasonably related pages. See the talk page for more information.

Please also note that the current delicate (and controversial) political situation of Kosovo makes the terms of article probation all the more important. DO NOT ENGAGE IN EDIT-WARRING ON THIS ARTICLE or any related articles. Edit-warring on this article will result in immediate blocking and application of additional sanctions under the terms of probation as administrators and/or the community deem appropriate. Thank you.

--&gt;

{{other uses|Kosovo (disambiguation)}}
{{redirect|Kosova||Kosova (disambiguation)}}
{{Kosovo (geopolitical region)}}


'''Kosovo'''  ({{lang-sr|Косово}}; {{lang-sq|Kosova}}).  is a [[geopolitical]] [[Historical regions of the Balkan Peninsula|region of the Balkan Peninsula]] in the [[Balkans]], covering 10,908 km², with a population of 2,100,000. The region has been settled since the Neolithic era, and has been part of the [[Roman empire]], [[history of Serbia|historical Serbia]], the [[Ottoman empire]], and [[Yugoslavia]].   The region is today [[disputed territory]].  It has been under [[Kosovo (UNMIK)|ad interim control]] of the [[United Nations]] since the end of the [[Kosovo War]] in 1999.  The [[Republic of Serbia]] continues to claim it as its [[Autonomous Province of Kosovo and Metohija]].  In February 2008, the [[Provisional Institutions of Self-Government]], an assembly under UNMIK, declared that the region was a sovereign and independent state, the '''Republic of Kosovo'''  ({{lang-sq|Republika e Kosovës}}, {{lang-sr|Република Косово}}).  This declaration is [[International reaction to the 2008 Kosovo declaration of independence|partially recognized]] internationally (by 36 out of 192 UN members as of 28 March 2008) but is strongly opposed by Serbia. 


It borders [[Central Serbia]] to the north and east, [[Montenegro]] to the northwest, [[Albania]] to the west and the [[Republic of Macedonia]] to the south. The capital is [[Pristina]], and other cities in the region include [[Peć]], [[Prizren]] and [[Mitrovica, Kosovo|Mitrovica]].  
Kosovo has [[borders]] with the following entities:
* with [[Albania]] - 111.7 km
* with [[Macedonia]] - 158.7 km  
* with [[Montenegro]] - 78.6 km 
* with [[Serbia]] - 351.6 km
The total border length is 700.7 km.&lt;ref name=&quot;SYSFRY1983&quot;&gt;Statistical Yearbook of the Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia, 1983.&lt;/ref&gt;


==Name==
{{main|Names of Kosovo}}
The entire region is commonly referred to in [[English language|English]] simply as '''Kosovo''' and in [[Albanian language|Albanian]], the language of its majority inhabitants, as '''Kosova'''. In [[Serbian language|Serbian]], the language of its largest minority population, a distinction is made between the eastern and western areas; the term Kosovo (Косово) is used for the eastern part, while the western part is called &quot;[[Metohija]]&quot; (Метохија) ([[Dukagjini]] in Albanian), and the region as a whole is called &quot;'''Kosovo'''&quot; ([[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Kosova''; [[Serbian language|Serbian]]: Косово, ''Kosovo''). 

Kosovo has an area of 10,887 [[square kilometers]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.kosovo-mining.org/kosovoweb/en/home.html |title=Welcome to the Independent Commission for Mines and Minerals (ICMM), Kosovo |author=Independent Commission for Mines and Minerals}}&lt;/ref&gt; (4,203 [[square mile|sq&amp;nbsp;mi]]) and a population of nearly two million. The largest cities are [[Priština]] (''Prishtinë''), the capital, with an estimated 550,000 inhabitants, [[Prizren]] (''Prizreni'') in the south west with a population of 110,000, [[Peć]] (''Peja'') in the west with 70,000, and [[Mitrovica]] in the north with 70,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.citypopulation.de/Kosovo.html |title=Kosovo |author=City Population}}&lt;/ref&gt;


==History==
{{main|History of Kosovo|20th century history of Kosovo}}

The formation of the Republic of Kosovo is a result of the turmoils of the [[disintegration of Yugoslavia]], particularly the [[Kosovo War]] of 1996 to 1999, but it is suffused with issues dating back to the [[rise of nationalism in the Balkans]] under [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman rule]] in the 19th century, [[Albanian nationalism|Albanian]] vs. [[Serbian nationalism|Serbian]] nationalisms in particular, the latter notably surrounding the [[Battle of Kosovo]] eponymous of the Kosovo region.
{{main|History of Kosovo}}
{{History of Kosovo and Metohija}}
=== Early history ===
{{main|Prehistoric Balkans|Moesia Superior|History of Medieval Kosovo|First Bulgarian Empire|History of Medieval Serbia}}
 
During the [[Neolithic]] period, the region of Kosovo lay within the extent of the [[Vinča-Turdaş culture]]. In the 4th to 3rd centuries  BC, it was the territory of the [[Thraco-Illyrian]] tribe of the [[Dardani]], forming part of the kingdom of [[Illyria]]. The [[Illyrians]], possible ancestors of Albanians (see [[Albanians#History_of_the_term|Albanians]], [[Origin of the Albanians]]), were conquered by Rome in the 160s BC, and made the Roman province of [[Illyricum (Roman province)|Illyricum]] in 59 BC. The Kosovo region became part of [[Moesia Superior]] in AD 87. The [[Slavic migrations]] reached the Balkans in the 6th to 7th century. The area was absorbed into the [[Byzantine empire]] in the 850s. As the center of Slavic resistance to Constantinople in the region, it often switched between Serbian and Bulgarian rule on one hand and Byzantine on the other until the Serb principality of [[Rascia]] conquered it by the end of the [[11th century]].

Fully absorbed into the Serbian Kingdom until the end of the [[12th century|12th]], it became the secular and spiritual center of the [[History of Medieval Serbia|Serbian medieval state]] of the [[House of Nemanjić|Nemanyiden]] dynasty in the [[13th century]], with the Patriarchate of the Serbian Orthodox Church in [[Peć]], while [[Prizren]] was the secular center. The zenith was reached with the formation of a [[Serbian Empire]] in 1346, which after 1371 transformed from a centralized absolutist medieval monarchy to a feudal realm. Kosovo became the hereditary land of the [[House of Branković]] and [[Vučitrn]] and [[Priština]] flourished. 

In the 1389  [[Battle of Kosovo]], Ottoman forces defeated a coalition led by [[Lazar Hrebeljanović]].
In 1402 a [[Serbian Despotate]] was raised and Kosovo became its richest territory, famous for mines. 
The local House of [[Vuk Branković|Branković]] came to prominence as the local lords of Kosovo, under [[Vuk Branković]], with the temporary fall of the [[History of Serbia|Serbian Despotate]] in [[1439]]. 
During the first fall of Serbia [[Novo Brdo]] and Kosovo offered last resistance to the invading Ottomans in 1441, in 1455 it was finally and fully conquered by the Ottoman Empire.

=== Ottoman Kosovo (1455 to 1912)===
{{main|History of Ottoman Kosovo}}
{{see|Vilayet of Kosovo|History of Ottoman Serbia}}
[[Image:Kosovo02.png|thumb|170px|Kosovo Vilayet, 1875-1878]]

Kosovo was part of the [[Ottoman Empire]] from [[1455]] to [[1912]], at first as part of the [[eyalet]] of [[Rumelia]], and from 1864 as a [[Kosovo Province, Ottoman Empire|separate province]].

Kosovo was briefly taken by the Austrian forces during the Great War of [[1683]]&amp;ndash;[[1699]] with help of 6,000 led by [[Pjetër Bogdani]]. In [[1690]], the [[Serbian Patriarch of Peć]] [[Arsenije III]]  led 37,000 families out of Kosovo. Other migrations of Orthodox Christians from the Kosovo area continued throughout the [[18th century]]. 
In 1766, the Ottomans abolished the [[Patriarchate of Peć]] and the position of Christians in Kosovo deteriorated, including full imposition of [[jizya]] (taxation of non-Muslims).

[[Image:Balkans-ethnique.JPG|thumb|260px|left|Ethnographic map of the Balkans and west Asia Minor, ''Atlas Général Vidal-Lablache'', Paris, 1898]]

In the 19th century, Kosovo along with the rest of the Balkans saw an &quot;[[Rise of nationalism under the Ottoman Empire|awakening]]&quot; of [[ethnic nationalism]], in the case of Kosovo ethnic [[Albanian nationalism]], including [[Romantic nationalism|Romantic]] notions of ancient [[Illyria]].
 
In 1871, a Serbian meeting was held in [[Prizren]] at which the possible retaking and reintegration of Kosovo and the rest of &quot;Old Serbia&quot; was discussed, as the [[History of Serbia|Principality of Serbia]] itself had already made plans for expansions towards Ottoman territory.  In 1878, a Peace Accord was drawn that left the cities of Priština and [[Kosovska Mitrovica]] under civil Serbian control,  and outside Ottoman jurisdiction, while the rest of Kosovo remained under Ottoman control. As a response, ethnic Albanians formed the  [[League of Prizren]], pursuing  political aspirations of unifying the Albanian people under the Ottoman umbrella.  By the end of the 19th century the [[Albanians]] replaced the [[Serbs]] as the majority population people within what presently composes Kosovo and Metohija, though not the entire Ottoman Province.

=== 20th century ===
{{main|20th century history of Kosovo}}
 
==== Balkan Wars to World War I====
[[Image:Balkan Wars Boundaries cleanup.jpg|thumb|Boundaries on the Balkans after the [[First Balkan War|First]] and [[Second Balkan War]].]]

The [[Young Turk]] movement supported a centralist rule and opposed any sort of autonomy desired by Kosovars, and particularly the Albanians. In 1910, an [[Albanian]] uprising spread from Priština and lasted until the Ottoman Sultan's visit to Kosovo in June of 1911. 
In [[1912]], during the [[Balkan Wars]], most of Kosovo was taken by the [[History of Serbia|Kingdom of Serbia]], while the region of [[Metohija]] ([[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Dukagjini Valley'') was taken by the [[History of Montenegro|Kingdom of Montenegro]]. An exodus of the local Albanian population occurred. This was described by [[Leon Trotsky]], who was a reporter for the ''[[Pravda]]'' newspaper at the time. The Serbian authorities planned a recolonization of Kosovo.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.elsie.de/pdf/B2002GatheringClouds.pdf Elsie, R. (ed.) (2002): &quot;''Gathering Clouds. The roots of ethnic cleansing in Kosovo. Early twentieth-century documents''&quot;]. Dukagjini Balkan Books, Peja (Kosovo, Serbia). ISBN 9951-05-016-6&lt;/ref&gt; Numerous colonist Serb families moved into Kosovo, equalizing the demographic balance between Albanians and Serbs. 
Kosovo's status within Serbia was finalised the following year at the [[Treaty of London]]. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mtholyoke.edu/acad/intrel/boshtml/bos145.htm Treaty of London, 1913]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the winter of [[1915]]-[[1916]], during [[World War I]], Kosovo saw a large exodus of the Serbian army which became known as the ''Great Serbian Retreat'', as Kosovo was occupied by [[Third Bulgarian Empire|Bulgarians]] and [[Austro-Hungarians]].
In 1918, the Serbian Army pushed the [[Central Powers]] out of Kosovo.  After World War I ended, the Monarchy was then transformed into the [[Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenians]]   on [[1 December]] [[1918]].

==== Kingdom of Yugoslavia and World War II ====
The 1918&amp;ndash;1929 period of the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenians witnessed a rise of the Serbian population in the region. Kosovo was split into four counties, three being a part of  Serbia (Zvečan, Kosovo and southern Metohija) and one of Montenegro (northern Metohija). However, the new administration system since [[26 April]] [[1922]] split Kosovo among three Areas of the Kingdom: Kosovo, [[Rascia]] and [[Zeta]].  In 1929, the Kingdom was transformed into the [[Kingdom of Yugoslavia]] and the territories of Kosovo were reorganised among the [[Zeta Banovina|Banate of Zeta]], the [[Morava Banovina|Banate of Morava]] and the [[Vardar Banovina|Banate of Vardar]]. The Kingdom of Yugoslavia lasted until the [[World War II]] [[Axis powers|Axis]] invasion of 1941, when the greatest part of Kosovo became a part of [[Kingdom of Italy (1861–1946)|Italian]]-controlled  Albania, and smaller bits by the [[Tsardom of Bulgaria]] and [[Nazi Germany|German]]-occupied [[Serbia (1941-1944)|Military Administration of Serbia]].  After numerous uprisings of [[Partisans]] led by [[Fadil Hoxha]], Kosovo was liberated after [[1944]] with the help of the Albanian partisans of the [[Comintern]], and became a province of [[Serbia]] within the [[Yugoslavia|Democratic Federal Yugoslavia]].
 
 
====Kosovo in Yugoslavia====
{{main|Autonomous Province of Kosovo and Metohija (1946-1974)|Socialist Autonomous Province of Kosovo}}
[[Image:SAP Kosovo.png|thumb|[[Socialist Autonomous Province of Kosovo]] of [[Socialist Republic of Serbia|Socialist Serbia]] inside [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Socialist Yugoslavia]], 1974-1990.]]

The province was first formed in 1945 as the Autonomous Kosovo-Metohian Area to protect its regional [[Albanians|Albanian]] majority within the [[People's Republic of Serbia]] as a member of the [[SFRJ|Federal People's Republic of Yugoslavia]] under the leadership of the former Partisan leader, [[Josip Broz Tito]], but with no actual autonomy {{Fact|date=March 2008}}. After Yugoslavia's name change to the [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia]] and Serbia's to the [[Socialist Republic of Serbia]] in 1953, Kosovo gained internal autonomy in the 1960s. In the 1974 constitution, the [[Socialist Autonomous Province of Kosovo]]'s government received higher powers, including the highest governmental titles — President and Prime Minister and a seat in the Federal Presidency which made it a ''de facto'' Socialist Republic within the Federation, but remaining a Socialist Autonomous Province within the Socialist Republic of Serbia. (Similar rights were extended to [[Vojvodina]]). In Kosovo [[Serbo-Croatian]], [[Albanian language|Albanian]] and [[Turkish language|Turkish]] were defined as official languages on the provincial level.
The ethnic balance of Kosovo tilted as the number of Albanians tripled, rising from almost 75% to over 90%, but the number of Serbs barely increased, dropping from 15% to 8% of the total population. Even though Kosovo was the least developed area of the former Yugoslavia, the living and economic prospects and freedoms were far greater than under the totalitarian [[Enver Hoxha|Hoxha]] regime in Albania. Beginning in March 1981, Kosovar Albanian students organized protests seeking that Kosovo become a republic within Yugoslavia.&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt19810419&quot;&gt;New York Times 1981-04-19, &quot;One Storm has Passed but Others are Gathering in Yugoslavia&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; During the 1980s, ethnic tensions continued with frequent violent outbreaks against Serbs and Yugoslav state authorities resulting in increased emigration of Kosovo Serbs and other ethnic groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;reuters19860527&quot;&gt;Reuters 1986-05-27, &quot;Kosovo Province Revives Yugoslavia's Ethnic Nightmare&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;csm19860728&quot;&gt;Christian Science Monitor 1986-07-28, &quot;Tensions among ethnic groups in Yugoslavia begin to boil over&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The Yugoslav leadership tried to suppress protests of Kosovo Serbs seeking protection from ethnic discrimination and violence.&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt19870627&quot;&gt;New York Times 1987-06-27, &quot;Belgrade Battles Kosovo Serbs&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

===1st Declaration of independence===
{{main|Autonomous Province of Kosovo and Metohija (1990-1999)|Republic of Kosova (1990–2000)}}
Inter-ethnic tensions continued to worsen in Kosovo throughout the 1980s.
The 1986  [[SANU Memorandum]] warned that Yugoslavia was suffering from ethnic strife and the disintegration of the Yugoslav economy into separate economic sectors and territories, which was transforming the federal state into a loose confederation.&lt;ref&gt;SANU (1986): [http://www.balkan-archive.org.yu/kosta/memorandum/contents.html Serbian Academy of Sciences and Arts Memorandum]. GIP Kultura. Belgrade.&lt;/ref&gt;
On [[June 28]] [[1989]], Milošević delivered a speech in front of a large number of Serb citizens at the main celebration marking the 600th anniversary of the [[Battle of Kosovo]], held at [[Gazimestan]]. Many think that this speech helped Milošević consolidate his authority in Serbia.&lt;ref&gt;''The Economist'', June 05, 1999, U.S. Edition, 1041 words, &quot;What's next for Slobodan Milošević?&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
In 1989, Milošević, employing a mix of intimidation and political maneuvering, drastically reduced Kosovo's special autonomous status within Serbia. Soon thereafter Kosovo Albanians organized a non-violent separatist movement, employing widespread civil disobedience, with the ultimate goal of achieving the independence of Kosovo.  On [[July 2]] [[1990]], an unconstitutional Kosovo parliament declared Kosovo an independent country, the ''Republic of Kosova''.   The Republic of Kosova was formally disbanded in 2000 when its institutions were replaced by the [[Joint Interim Administrative Structure]] established by the [[United Nations Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo]] (UNMIK). During its lifetime, the Republic of Kosova was only recognized by [[Albania]].

====The Kosovo War====
{{main|Kosovo War}}
The [[Kosovo War]] was initially a conflict between [[Serbs|Serbian]] and [[Yugoslavia|Yugoslav]] security forces and the [[Kosovo Liberation Army]] (KLA), an ethnic [[Albanians|Albanian]] guerrilla group  identified by some as terrorist.[http://judiciary.house.gov/Legacy/muts1213.htm], seeking secession from the former Yugoslavia.  In 1998 Western interest had increased and the Serbian authorities were compelled to sign a unilateral cease-fire and partial retreat. Under an agreement devised by [[Richard Holbrooke]], [[OSCE]] observers moved into Kosovo to monitor the ceasefire, while Yugoslav military forces partly pulled out of Kosovo. However, the ceasefire was systematically broken shortly thereafter by KLA forces, which again provoked harsh counterattacks by the Serbs.{{Fact|date=March 2008}}

The Serbs then began to escalate the conflict, using military and paramilitary forces in another [[ethnic cleansing]] campaign this time against against the Kosovar Albanians.  An estimated 300,000 refugees were displaced during the winter of 1998, many left without adequate food or shelter, precipitating a humanitarian crisis and calls for intervention by the international community.

[[1999 NATO bombing of the Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|NATO intervention]] between [[March 24]] and [[June 10]] [[1999]],&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb|url=http://www.nato.int/kosovo/all-frce.htm|title=Operation Allied Force|publisher=[[NATO]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; combined with continued skirmishes between Albanian guerrillas and Yugoslav forces resulted in a massive displacement of population in Kosovo.&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb|url=http://www.unhcr.org/partners/PARTNERS/3bb051c54.pdf|title=NATO and Humanitarian Action in the Kosovo Crisis|author=Larry Minear, Ted van Baarda, Marc Sommers|year=2000|publisher=[[Brown University]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
During the conflict roughly a million ethnic Albanians fled or were forcefully driven from Kosovo. Altogether, more than 11,000 deaths have been reported to Carla Del Ponte by her prosecutors.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC&quot;&gt;{{citeweb| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/514828.stm |title=World: Europe UN gives figure for Kosovo dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; Some 3,000 people are still missing, of which 2,500 are Albanian, 400 Serbs and 100 Roma.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/781310.stm |title=3,000 missing in Kosovo |author=KiM Info-Service |date=07/06/00}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===The UN administration period===
{{main|Kosovo (UNMIK)|Kosovo status process}}

After the war ended, the UN Security Council passed Resolution 1244 that placed Kosovo under transitional UN administration ([[UNMIK]]) and authorized [[Kosovo Force|KFOR]], a NATO-led peacekeeping force. Resolution 1244 also delivered that Kosovo will have autonomy within Federal Republic of Yugoslavia&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first= | last= | coauthors= | title=RESOLUTION 1244 (1999) | date=[[1999-06-17]] | publisher=BBC News | url =http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/371562.stm | work = | pages = | accessdate = 2008-02-19 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt; (today legal successor of  Federal Republic of Yugoslavia is Republic of Serbia).

Some 200,000-280,000, representing the majority of the Serb population, left when the Serbian forces left.  There was also some looting of Serb properties and even violence against some of those Serbs and Roma who remained.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.reliefweb.int/library/documents/2002/coe-kos-16oct.pdf Kosovo: The Human Rights Situation and the Fate of Persons Displaced from Their Homes (.pdf)] &quot;, report by [[Alvaro Gil-Robles]], [[Council of Europe]] Commissioner for Human Rights, Strasbourg, [[October 16]] [[2002]], p. 30.&lt;/ref&gt; The current number of [[internally displaced person]]s is disputed,&lt;ref&gt;[[United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees|UNHCR]], Critical Appraisal of Responsee Mechanisms Operating in Kosovo for Minority Returns, Pristina, February 2004, p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;U.S. Committee for Refugees (USCR), April 2000, Reversal of Fortune: Yugoslavia's Refugees Crisis Since the Ethnic Albanian Return to Kosovo, p. 2-3.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.reliefweb.int/library/documents/2002/coe-kos-16oct.pdf Kosovo: The human rights situation and the fate of persons displaced from their homes (.pdf)] &quot;, report by [[Alvaro Gil-Robles]], [[Council of Europe]] Commissioner for Human Rights, Strasbourg, [[October 16]] [[2002]].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;International Relations and Security Network (ISN): [http://www.esiweb.org/pdf/esi_lausanne_reactions_id_1.pdf Serbians return to Kosovo not impossible, says report (.pdf)] , by Tim Judah, [[June 7]] [[2004]].&lt;/ref&gt; with estimates ranging from 65,000&lt;ref&gt;European Stability Initiative (ESI): [http://www.esiweb.org/pdf/esi_document_id_53.pdf The Lausanne Principle: Multiethnicity, Territory and the Future of Kosovo's Serbs (.pdf)] , [[June 7]] [[2004]].&lt;/ref&gt; to 250,000&lt;ref&gt;Coordinating Centre of Serbia for Kosovo-Metohija: [http://www.kc.gov.yu/D-ENGLISH/dokumenti-eng/program-povratka-eng.html Principles of the program for return of internally displaced persons from Kosovo and Metohija] .&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees|UNHCR]]: 2002 Annual Statistical Report: Serbia and Montenegro, pg. 9&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[U.S. Committee for Refugees and Immigrants]] (USCRI): [http://www.refugees.org/countryreports.aspx?id=1624 Country report: Serbia and Montenegro 2006].&lt;/ref&gt;. Many displaced Serbs are afraid to return to their homes, even with [[UNMIK]] protection.  Around 120,000-150,000 Serbs remain in Kosovo, but are subject to ongoing harassment and discrimination. According to Amnesty International, the aftermarth of the war resulted in an increase in the [[trafficking of women]] for sexual exploitation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/3686173.stm Kosovo UN troops 'fuel sex trade'], [[BBC]].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.amnesty.org/actforwomen/stories-9-eng Kosovo: Trafficked women and girls have human rights], [[Amnesty International]].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/international/story/0,,1211214,00.html Nato force 'feeds Kosovo sex trade'], [[Guardian Unlimited]].&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2001, UNMIK promulgated a Constitutional Framework for Kosovo that established the [[Provisional Institutions of Self-Government]] (PISG), including an elected Kosovo Assembly, Presidency and office of Prime Minister.  Kosovo held its first free, Kosovo-wide elections in late 2001 (municipal elections had been held the previous year).

In March 2004, Kosovo experienced its worst inter-ethnic violence since the Kosovo War.  The [[2004 unrest in Kosovo|unrest in 2004]] was sparked by a series of minor events that soon cascaded into large-scale riots.&lt;ref&gt;U.S State Department Report, published in 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

International negotiations began in 2006 to determine the final status of Kosovo, as envisaged under [[UN Security Council Resolution 1244]].  The [[UN]]-backed talks, lead by UN Special Envoy [[Martti Ahtisaari]], began in February 2006. Whilst progress was made on technical matters, both parties remained diametrically opposed on the question of status itself.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/6034567.stm UN frustrated by Kosovo deadlock] &quot;, ''BBC News'', [[October 9]] [[2006]].&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2007, Ahtisaari delivered a draft status settlement proposal to leaders in Belgrade and Pristina, the basis for a draft UN Security Council Resolution which proposes 'supervised independence' for the province. A draft resolution, backed by the [[United States]], the [[United Kingdom]] and other European members of the [[Security Council]], was presented and rewritten four times to try to accommodate Russian concerns that such a resolution would undermine the principle of state sovereignty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.setimes.com/cocoon/setimes/xhtml/en_GB/newsbriefs/setimes/newsbriefs/2007/06/29/nb-07 |title=Russia reportedly rejects fourth draft resolution on Kosovo status |author=Southeast European Times |date=29/06/2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Russia, which holds a veto in the Security Council as one of five permanent members, had stated that it would not support any resolution which was not acceptable to both Belgrade and Kosovo Albanians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.setimes.com/cocoon/setimes/xhtml/en_GB/newsbriefs/setimes/newsbriefs/2007/07/10/nb-02 |title=UN Security Council remains divided on Kosovo |author=Southeast European Times |date=09/07/07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Whilst most observers had, at the beginning of the talks, anticipated independence as the most likely outcome, others have suggested that a rapid resolution might not be preferable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/985caa90-de5a-11db-afa7-000b5df10621.html?nclick_check=1 |title=A long reconciliation process is required |author=James Dancer |date=30/03/07 |publisher=Financial Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After many weeks of discussions at the UN, the [[United States]], [[United Kingdom]] and other European members of the Security Council formally 'discarded' a draft resolution backing Ahtisaari's proposal on [[20 July]] [[2007]], having failed to secure Russian backing. Beginning in August, a &quot;[[Troika (triumvirate)|Troika]]&quot; consisting of negotiators from the [[European Union]] (Wolfgang Ischinger), the [[United States]] (Frank Wisner)  and [[Russia]] (Alexander Botsan-Kharchenko) launched a new effort to reach a status outcome acceptable to both Belgrade and Pristina.  Despite Russian disapproval, the [[United States|U.S.]], the [[United Kingdom]], and [[France]] appeared likely to recognize Kosovar independence&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/international/story/0,,2209907,00.html |title=Bosnian nightmare returns to haunt EU |author=Simon Tisdall |date=13/11/07 |publisher=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt;. A declaration of independence by Kosovar Albanian leaders was postponed until the end of the Serbian presidential elections ([[4 February]] [[2008]]). Most EU members and the US had feared that a premature declaration could boost support in Serbia for the ultra-nationalist candidate, Tomislav Nikolić.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/6386467.stm&lt;/ref&gt;

====2nd Declaration of Independence====
{{main|2008 Kosovo declaration of independence|International reaction to the 2008 Kosovo declaration of independence|2008 Post declaration of independence unrest in Kosovo}}
The [[Assembly of Kosovo|Kosovar Assembly]] approved a declaration of independence on [[17 February]] [[2008]].&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc_proclaim&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/7249034.stm Kosovo MPs proclaim independence]&quot;, BBC News Online, [[17 February]] [[2008]]&lt;/ref&gt; Over the following days, several countries (the [[United States]], [[Turkey]], [[Albania]], [[Austria]], [[Germany]], [[Italy]], [[France]], the [[United Kingdom]], [[Republic of China]] (Taiwan)&lt;ref&gt;http://www.taipeitimes.com/News/taiwan/archives/2008/02/20/2003402059&lt;/ref&gt;, [[Australia]] and others) announced their recognition, despite protests by [[Serbia]] in the [[UN Security Council]].&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc=recog1&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/7251359.stm Recognition for new Kosovo grows]&quot;, BBC News Online, [[18 February]] [[2008]]&lt;/ref&gt;

The UN Security Council remains divided on the question (as of [[25 February]] [[2008]]). Of the five members with [[United Nations Security Council veto power|veto power]], three (USA, UK, France) recognize the declaration of independence, and two ([[Russia]] and [[People's Republic of China]]) consider it illegal. As of 28th March 2008, no member-country of [[Commonwealth of Independent States|CIS]], [[CSTO]] and [[Shanghai Cooperation Organization|SCO]] have recognized Kosovo as independent.

The [[European Union]] has no official position towards Kosovo's status, but has decided to deploy the [[European Union Rule of Law Mission in Kosovo]] to ensure a continuation of international civil presence in Kosovo. As of today, most of member-countries of [[NATO]], [[EU]], [[Western European Union|WEU]] and [[OECD]] have recognized Kosovo as independent.

Of Kosovo's immediate neighbour states (other than Serbia), [[Albania]] recognizes the declaration of independence, [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]] announced they will likely recognize it within &quot;a few weeks&quot; and [[Montenegro]] stated they will wait for a decision of the European Union. [[Croatia]], [[Bulgaria]] and [[Hungary]], all neighbours of Serbia, announced in a joint statement that they would also recognise the declaration. &lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/7304488.stm BBC News, ''Serbia's neighbours accept Kosovo ''], accessed 12:41 [[19 March]] [[2008]].&lt;/ref&gt;

====The Celebration of Independence====
On [[17 February]] [[2008]] Kosovo has declared its independence. In the same day there has been a lot of celebrations. Thousands of [[Albanians]] came from [[Kosovo]], [[Albania]], [[Macedonia]] and [[Montenegro]] in the capital of Kosovo, [[Prishtina]] to celebrate the independence. The streets of Prishtina were full of people, so, [[urban transport]] was not available.
[[17 February]] [[2008]] was a very busy day for politicians. They have agreed to declare the independence on 15:00. On those moments, the [[parliament]] scene was being broadcast by huge TV channels, such as [[BBC]], [[CNN]], [[Sky News]] etc. After declaring the independence there was a philharmonic concert which was held on &quot;[[1 tetori]]&quot;. After the philharmonic concert there was an another concert with famous [[Albanian]] singers. Concerts were also held in other cities with with significant ethnic-Albanian populations (i.e. [[Tetovo]] and [[Skopje]]) and [[Tirana]].

==Geography==
{{main|Geography of Kosovo}}
Kosovo has an area of 10,908 [[square kilometers]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ks-gov.net/ESK/|title=Statistical Office of Kosova}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a population of about 2.2 million. The largest cities are [[Priština]], the capital, with an estimated 170,000 inhabitants, [[Prizren]] in the south west with a population of 110,000, [[Peć]] in the west with 70,000, and [[Kosovska Mitrovica]] in the north with 70,000.  The climate is continental, with warm summers and cold and snowy winters. Most of Kosovo's terrain in mountainous, but there are plain regions.

==Republic of Kosovo==
{{Republic of Kosovo}}
{{see|Constitution of Kosovo}}


==Administrative regions==
Kosovo, for administrative reasons, is considered as consisting of seven districts.
[[North Kosovo]] maintains its own government, infrastructure and institutions by its dominant ethnic [[Serb]] population in the [[District of Kosovska Mitrovica]], viz. in the [[Leposavić]], [[Zvečan]] and [[Zubin Potok]] municipalities and the northern part of [[Kosovska Mitrovica]].

===Districts===
{{main|Subdivisions of Kosovo}}

===Municipalities and cities===
{{main|Municipalities of Kosovo}}
Kosovo is also divided into 30 municipalities:
{{Municipalities of Kosovo}}

==Politics==
{{main|Politics of Kosovo|United Nations Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo|Provisional Institutions of Self-Government}}
{{update|section}}
===Parliament===
In 1999, [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 1244|UN Security Council Resolution 1244]] placed Kosovo under transitional UN administration pending a determination of Kosovo's future status. This Resolution entrusted the [[United Nations Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo]] (UNMIK) with sweeping powers to govern Kosovo, but also directed UNMIK to establish interim institutions of self-governance. Resolution 1244 permits Serbia no role in governing Kosovo and since 1999 Serbian laws and institutions have not been valid in Kosovo. NATO has a separate mandate to provide for a safe and secure environment.

In May 2001, UNMIK promulgated the Constitutional Framework, which established Kosovo's [[Provisional Institutions of Self-Government]] (PISG). The PISG replaced the [[Joint Interim Administrative Structure]] (JIAS) established a year earlier. Since 2001, UNMIK has been gradually transferring increased governing competencies to the PISG, while reserving some powers that are normally carried out by sovereign states, such as foreign affairs. Kosovo has also established municipal government and an internationally-supervised Kosovo Police Service.

According to the Constitutional Framework, Kosovo shall have a 120-member Kosovo Assembly. The Assembly includes twenty reserved seats: ten for Kosovo Serbs and ten for non-Serb minorities (Bosniaks, Roma, etc). The Kosovo Assembly is responsible for electing a President and Prime Minister of Kosovo.
===Government===
The largest political party in Kosovo, the Democratic League of Kosovo (LDK), has its origins in the 1990s non-violent resistance movement to Miloševic's rule. The party was led by Ibrahim Rugova until his death in 2006. The two next largest parties have their roots in the Kosovo Liberation Army (KLA): the Democratic Party of Kosovo (PDK) led by former KLA leader Hashim Thaci and the Alliance for the Future of Kosovo (AAK) led by former KLA commander Ramush Haradinaj. Kosovo publisher Veton Surroi formed his own political party in 2004 named &quot;Ora.&quot; Kosovo Serbs formed the Serb List for Kosovo and Metohija (SLKM) in 2004, but have boycotted Kosovo's institutions and never taken their seats in the Kosovo Assembly.

In November 2001, the [[OSCE]] supervised the first elections for the Kosovo Assembly. After that election, Kosovo's political parties formed an all-party unity coalition and elected [[Ibrahim Rugova]] as President and Bajram Rexhepi (PDK) as Prime Minister. After Kosovo-wide elections in October 2004, the LDK and AAK formed a new governing coalition that did not include PDK and Ora. This coalition agreement resulted in [[Ramush Haradinaj]] (AAK) becoming Prime Minister, while Ibrahim Rugova retained the position of President. PDK and Ora were critical of the coalition agreement and have since frequently accused the current government of corruption.

Ramush Haradinaj resigned the post of Prime Minister after he was indicted for war crimes by the International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia (ICTY) in March 2005. He was replaced by Bajram Kosumi (AAK). But in a political shake-up after the death of President Rugova in January 2006, Kosumi himself was replaced by former Kosovo Protection Corps commander [[Agim Ceku]]. Ceku has won recognition for his outreach to minorities, but Serbia has been critical of his wartime past as military leader of the KLA and claims he is still not doing enough for Kosovo Serbs. The Kosovo Assembly elected [[Fatmir Sejdiu]], a former LDK parliamentarian, president after Rugova's death. Slaviša Petkovic, Minister for Communities and Returns, was previously the only ethnic Serb in the government, but resigned in November 2006 amid allegations that he misused ministry funds.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.adnki.com/index_2Level_English.php?cat=Politics&amp;loid=8.0.363650179&amp;par=0 Kosovo: Serb minister resigns over misuse of funds] &quot;, Adnkronos international (AKI), [[November 27]] [[2006]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.reliefweb.int/rw/RWB.NSF/db900SID/LZEG-6VUQUS?OpenDocument Sole Kosovo Serb cabinet minister resigns: PM] &quot;, Agence France-Presse (AFP), [[November 24]] [[2006]].&lt;/ref&gt; Today two of the total thirteen ministries in Kosovo's Government have ministers from the minorities. Branislav Grbic, ethnic Serb, leads Minister of Returns and Sadik Idriz, ethnic Bosnjak, leads Ministry of Health&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ks-gov.net/pm/?menuid=2&amp;subid=20&amp;subs=56&amp;lingo=1 Fillimi&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Kosovan parliamentary election, 2007|Parliamentary elections]] were held on [[17 November]] [[2007]]. After early results, [[Hashim Thaçi]] who was on course to gain 35 per cent of the vote, claimed victory for PDK, the [[Democratic Party of Kosovo|Albanian Democratic Party]], and stated his intention to declare independence. Thaci is likely to form a coalition with current [[Fatmir Sejdiu|President Fatmir Sejdiu]]'s [[Democratic League of Kosovo|Democratic League]] which was in second place with 22 percent of the vote. The turnout at the election was particularly low with most Serbs refusing to vote.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.euronews.net/index.php?page=info&amp;article=454473&amp;lng=1 EuroNews: Ex-guerrilla chief claims victory in Kosovo election]. Retrieved [[18 November]] [[2007]].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Military==
{{main|Military of Kosovo}}
The [[military of Kosovo]] is still in the process of being organized following self-proclaimed and [[International reaction to the 2008 Kosovo declaration of independence|partially recognized]] declaration of independence of [[February 17]] [[2008]]. Following the [[Kosovo War]] in 1999, [[United Nations]] [[United Nations Security Council|Security Council]] [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 1244|Resolution 1244]] placed Kosovo under the authority of the [[United Nations Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo]] (UNMIK), with security provided by the [[NATO]]-led [[Kosovo Force]] (KFOR).&lt;ref&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Military_of_Kosovo Military of Kosovo&lt;/ref&gt;

==Economy==
{{main|Economy of Kosovo}}
Kosovo has one of the most under-developed economies in Europe, with a per capita income estimated at [[Euro|€]]1,565 (2004).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://web.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/COUNTRIES/ECAEXT/KOSOVOEXTN/0,,contentMDK:20629286~menuPK:297777~pagePK:1497618~piPK:217854~theSitePK:297770,00.html |title=Kosovo Brief 2006 |author=The World Bank |date=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite substantial development subsidies from all Yugoslav republics, Kosovo was the poorest province of Yugoslavia.&lt;ref&gt;Christian Science Monitor 1982-01-15, &quot;Why Turbulent Kosovo has Marble Sidewalks but Troubled Industries&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, over the course of the 1990s a blend of poor economic policies, international sanctions, poor external commerce and ethnic conflict severely damaged the economy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://web.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/COUNTRIES/ECAEXT/KOSOVOEXTN/0,,menuPK:297775~pagePK:141159~piPK:141110~theSitePK:297770,00.html |title=World Bank Mission in Kosovo |author=The World Bank |date=2006/2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kosovo's economy remains weak. After a jump in 2000 and 2001, growth in [[Gross Domestic Product]] (GDP) was negative in 2002 and 2003 and is expected to be around 3 percent 2004-2005, with domestic sources of growth unable to compensate for the declining foreign assistance. [[Inflation]] is low, while the budget posted a deficit for the first time in 2004. Kosovo has high external deficits. In 2004, the deficit of the balance of goods and services was close to 70 percent of GDP. Remittances from Kosovars living abroad accounts for an estimated 13 percent of GDP, and foreign assistance for around 34 percent of GDP.

Most economic development since 1999 has taken place in the trade, retail and the construction sectors. The private sector that has emerged since 1999 is mainly small-scale. The industrial sector remains weak and the electric power supply remains unreliable, acting as a key constraint. Unemployment remains pervasive, at around 40-50% of the labor force.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.eciks.org/english/lajme.php?action=total_news&amp;main_id=386 |title=May finds Kosovo with 50% unemployed |author=eciks |date=04/05/06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

UNMIK introduced an external trade regime and customs administration on [[September 3]], [[1999]] when it set customs border controls in Kosovo. All goods imported in Kosovo face a flat 10% customs duty fee.&lt;ref name=&quot;BuyUSA&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.buyusa.gov/kosovo/en/doingbusinessinkosovo.html |title=Doing Business in Kosovo |author=U.S. Commercial Service}}&lt;/ref&gt; These taxes are collected from all Tax Collection Points installed at the borders of Kosovo, including those between Kosovo and Serbia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.seerecon.org/kosovo/documents/wb_econ_report/wb-kosovo-econreport-2-2.pdf |format=PDF |title=External Trade and Customs |author=Economic Reconstruction and Development in South East Europe}}&lt;/ref&gt; UNMIK and Kosovo institutions have signed Free Trade Agreements with [[Croatia]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.b92.net/eng/news/globe-article.php?yyyy=2006&amp;mm=10&amp;dd=02&amp;nav_category=123&amp;nav_id=37090 |title=Croatia, Kosovo sign Interim Free Trade Agreement |author=B92 |authorlink=B92 |date=02/10/06 |publisher=mrt.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.euinkosovo.org/upload_press/4.06%20-%20UNMIK%20and%20Bosnia%20and%20Herzegovina%20Initial%20Free%20Trade%20Agreement%2017.2.06.pdf |format=PDF |title=UNMIK and Bosnia and Herzegovina Initial Free Trade Agreement |author=EU in Kosovo |date=17/02/06 |publisher=UNMIK}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Albania]] and [[Republic of Macedonia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BuyUSA&quot;/&gt;

The [[euro]] is the official currency of Kosovo and used by UNMIK and the government bodies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.euinkosovo.org/uk/invest/invest.php |title=Invest in Kosovo |author=EU in Kosovo}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Serbian dinar]] is used in the Serbian-populated parts.

===Trade and investment===

Kosovo's 2006 trade balance was total exports(FOB) $154mil and total imports(CIF) $1,612mil.

The [[Republic of Macedonia]] is Kosovo's largest import and export market (averaging €220 million and €9 million, respectively or 20% of whole Kosovo's trade), followed by Serbia (€111 million and €5 million app 12%), Germany (app 10% of total trade), China (app from 5-9% depending on season) and Turkey (app 6% of total imports). In total [[EU]]'s 27 countries are Kosovo's biggest trade partner, 35% of all kosovo's imports are coming from EU and app 50-60% of Kosovo's $150 million exports are going in EU27.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://siteresources.worldbank.org/INTKOSOVO/147270-1121700806276/20953280/Kosovo_Economic_Briefing_april.pdf |format=PDF |title=Kosovo Monthly Economic Briefing: Preparing for next winter |author=The World Bank |date=April 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The economy is hindered by Kosovo's still-unresolved international status, which has made it difficult to attract investment and loans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/business/4509781.stm |title=Brussels offers first Kosovo loan |author=BBC News |date=03/05/05}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
The province's economic weakness has produced a thriving black economy in which smuggled petrol, cigarettes and cement are major commodities. The prevalence of official corruption and the pervasive influence of organised crime gangs has caused serious concern internationally. The United Nations has made the fight against corruption and organised crime a high priority, pledging a &quot;zero tolerance&quot; approach.

Kosovo have an foreign debt of 1,264 billion USD that is currently serviced by Serbia.

According to [http://www.eciks.org/english/invest.php?action=total_invest&amp;main_id=13 ECIKS] from 2001 to 2004 Kosovo received $3,2 Billion of foreign aid. International donnor conference is to be held in Switzerland in June or July of 2008. Until now EU pledged 2 billion €, $350 mil by USA. Serbia also pledged 120 million € to Serb's enclaves in Kosovo.

=== Energy sector ===
At 14,700 Mt, Kosovo possesses the world’s fifth-largest proven reserves of [[lignite]], a type of [[coal]]. The lignite is distributed across the Kosovo, Dukagjin and Drenica basins, although mining has so far been restricted to the Kosovo basin.  Coal reserves are found in two main basins and are currently being mined in the coal mines of [[Bardh open-cast coal mine]] and [[Mirash open-cast coal mine]].

Energy sector presents a major potential for development of Kosovo's economy. There are two large coal-fired electrical power plants named &quot;Kosovo A&quot; and &quot;Kosovo B&quot; and the project to build a larger 2100-MW coal-fired power plant is underway with expected completion in 2012.

=== Mining ===
Kosovo has [[lead]]-[[zinc]]-[[silver]] mines of Artana (Novo Brdo), Belo Brdo, Stan Terg and Hajvalia mines, and the Crnac mine. During the lead-zinc-silver exploitation at Farbani Potok (Artana-Novo Brdo), about 3 Mt of high-grade [[halloysite]] was discovered. Halloysite is an aluminosilicate clay mineral used as a raw material for [[porcelain]] and [[bone china]]. This is only one of five known exploitable deposits of this very high-value (US$140-450/t) clay, the other four being in New Zealand, Turkey, China and Utah, US. Current world production is estimated at 150,000 t/y. There is also [[nickel]] to be found in Kosovo and the largest working mine is in Çikatova (Dushkaja and Suke) and Gllavica. There are significant deposits of [[chromium]], [[bauxite]] and [[magnesite]], but mining has been stalled since 1999.

=== Unemployment ===

Major issue in Kosovo that is undermining Kosovo's development is unemployment. Official unemployment rate stands at 40%. [[The World Bank]] says that even with 6 per cent annual growth (twice what Kosovo manages at the moment), it would take ten years to cut unemployment by half, from 40 to 20 per cent. Persistent unemployment, in particular among the young, will fuel frustration, which would be bad for political peace.[http://centreforeuropeanreform.blogspot.com/2008/02/kosovo-economic-dilemma.html] Unemployment rate among young people age under 25, which contribute to app 50% of Kosovo's population, is much bigger and it stands app at 60%. But, Kosovo has youngest population in Europe, so in coming years, with significant development of educational sector on Kosovo, this fact could be overturned in Kosovo's favour.

==Demographics==
{{main|Demographics of Kosovo}}
{{summarize}}
[[Image:Kosovo ethnic 2005.png|thumb|220px|Ethnic composition of Kosovo in 2005 according to the [[OSCE]]]]
According to the Kosovo in Figures 2005 Survey of the Statistical Office of Kosovo,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ks-gov.net/esk/esk/pdf/english/general/kosovo_figures_05.pdf |format=PDF |title=Kosovo in figures 2005 |author=UNMIK |publisher=Ministry of Public Services}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4385768.stm |title=Muslims in Europe: Country guide |author=BBC News |date=23/12/05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/country_profiles/3524092.stm |title=Regions and territories: Kosovo |author=BBC News |date=20/11/07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kosovo's total population is estimated between 1.9 and 2.2 million in the following ethnic proportions:

* 92% [[Albanians]]
* 4% [[Serbs]]
* 2% [[Bosniaks]] and [[Gorani (ethnic group)|Gorans]]
* 1% [[Roma people|Roma]]
* 1% [[Turkish people|Turks]]

===Ethnic and cultural diversity===
[[Islam]] (mostly [[Sunni]], with a [[Bektashi]] minority) is the predominant [[religion]], professed by most of the majority ethnic Albanian population, the Bosniak, Gorani, and Turkish communities, and some of the Roma/[[Ashkali]]/[[Egyptians (Balkans)|Egyptian]] community. The Serb population, estimated at 100,000 to 120,000 persons, is largely [[Serbian Orthodox]]. Approximately 3 percent of ethnic Albanians are [[Roman Catholic]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.crisisgroup.org/home/index.cfm?id=1591&amp;l=1 |title=Religion in Kosovo |author=International Crisis Group |date=31/01/01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2007/90198.htm#kosovo International Religious Freedom Report 2007 (U.S. Department of States) - Serbia (includes Kosovo)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2006/71405.htm#kosovo International Religious Freedom Report 2006 (U.S. Department of States) - Serbia and Montenegro (includes Kosovo)]&lt;/ref&gt;

Ethnic Albanians in Kosovo have the largest population growth in Europe.&lt;ref&gt;[http://files.osa.ceu.hu/holdings/300/8/3/text/3-13-10.shtml Albanian Population Growth]&lt;/ref&gt; The people’s growth rate in Kosovo is 1.3%. Over an 82-year period (1921-2003) the population grew 4.6 times. If growth continues at such a pace, based on some estimations, the population will be 4.5 million by 2050.&lt;ref&gt;[http://kosovo-hotels.com/index.php?mod=kos_profile Kosovo-Hotels, Prishtina - Kosova-Hotels, Prishtinë]&lt;/ref&gt;

From [[Demographics_of_Kosovo#World_War_II-1968|1948]] to [[Demographics_of_Kosovo#1989-1999:_Centralized_Yugoslav_Control|1991]] period, Serb population on Kosovo incresed for 12% (3 times less than in Serbia), while Albanian population increased for 300% in the same time period.

==Society==
===Cinema and media===
{{main|Music of Kosovo}}
Although in Kosovo the music is diverse, authentic Albanian music (see ''[[World Music]]'') and [[Serbian music]] do still exist. Albanian music is characterized by the use of the ''[[çiftelia]]'' (an authentic Albanian instrument), ''mandolin'', ''mandola'' and ''percussion''. [[European classical music|Classical music]] is also well known in Kosovo and has been taught at [[universities]] (at the [[University of Priština#Albanian university|University of Priština Faculty of Arts]]  and the [[University of Priština#Serbian university|University of Priština at Kosovska Mitrovica]]

===Sports===
{{main|Olympic Committee of Kosovo|Football Federation of Kosovo|Basketball Federation of Kosovo|Handball Federation of Kosovo|Table Tennis Federation of Kosovo}}
Several sports federations have been formed in Kosovo within the framework of Law No. 2003/24 &quot;Law on Sport&quot; passed by the Assembly of Kosovo in 2003. The law formally established a national [[Olympic Committee of Kosovo|Olympic Committee]], regulated the establishment of sports federations and established guidelines for sports clubs. At present only some of the sports federations established have gained international recognition.

==Notes and references==
&lt;!-- Please do not use a scroll box. please see [[Template:Scrollbox]] for more information.(This template should not be used in main article space, as it renders any content obscured within the template unprintable.  This is especially true with text content, such as citations, according to [[Wikipedia:Templates_for_deletion/Log/2007_June_11#Template:Scrollref]]. Please, if you see a scroll box in article space, remove it and put a hidden warning.)--&gt;
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
{{cite book
  | last = Malcolm
  | first = Noel
  | authorlink = Noel Malcolm
  | title = Kosovo: A Short History
  | publisher = [[Harper Perennial]]
  | year = 1999
  | isbn = 0060977752 }}

==See also==
&lt;div style=&quot;-moz-column-count:4; column-count:4;&quot;&gt;
* [[Assembly of Kosovo]]
* [[Government of Kosovo]]
* [[Prime Minister of Kosovo]]
* [[President of Kosovo]]
* [[Serbs in Kosovo]]
* [[Albanians in Kosovo]]
* [[Post and Telecom of Kosovo]]
* [[National awakening and the birth of Albania]]
* [[Demographic history of Kosovo]]
* [[Unrest in Kosovo|Unrest in Kosovo during March 2004]]
* [[Metohija]]
* [[North Kosovo]]
* [[Flag of Kosovo]]
* [[2008 Kosovo declaration of independence]]
&lt;/div&gt;

==External links==
{{portal|Kosovo|Flag of Kosovo.svg}}
{{sisterlinks}}
* {{wikiatlas|Kosovo}}
* [http://www.unmikonline.org/ United Nations Interim Administration in Kosovo]
* [http://www.ks-gov.net/pm/Fillimi/tabid/36/menuid/+/subid/+/lingo/2/language/en-US/Default.aspx The Government of Kosovo and Prime minister's office]
*[http://www.assembly-kosova.org/ Assembly of Kosovo]
*[http://www.president-ksgov.net/?id=1,67,67,67,e/ President of Kosovo]
* [http://www.srbija.sr.gov.yu/kosovo-metohija/?change_lang=en Serbian Government for Kosovo and Metohija]
* {{CIA World Factbook link|kv|Kosovo}}
* [http://www.visitkosova.org/english/index.htm Visit Kosovo - Tourism Website]
* {{wikitravel}}

{{Template group
|title = [[Image:Nuvola apps package network.png|23px]] Geographic national
|list  =
{{Kosovo}}
{{Municipalities of the Republic of Kosovo}}
}}
{{Template group
|title = [[Image:Crystal Clear app browser.png|23px]] Geographic international
|list  =
{{Countries of Europe}}
{{Central European Free Trade Agreement (CEFTA)}}
}}
{{Template group
|title = [[Image:Nuvola apps gaim.png|23px]] Languages
|list  = 
}}

&lt;!--Categories--&gt;
[[Category:Kosovo| ]]
[[Category:Disputed territories]]

[[als:Kosovo]]
[[ang:Kosovo]]
[[ar:كوسوفو]]
[[an:Kosovo]]
[[roa-rup:Cosova]]
[[frp:Kosovo]]
[[ast:Kosovo]]
[[az:Kosovo]]
[[bn:কসোভো]]
[[zh-min-nan:Kosovo]]
[[be:Косава]]
[[be-x-old:Косава]]
[[bs:Kosovo]]
[[br:Kosovo]]
[[bg:Косово]]
[[ca:Kosovo]]
[[cv:Косово]]
[[ceb:Kosovo]]
[[cs:Kosovo]]
[[cy:Kosovo]]
[[da:Kosovo]]
[[de:Kosovo]]
[[et:Kosovo]]
[[el:Κοσσυφοπέδιο]]
[[es:Kosovo]]
[[eo:Kosovo]]
[[eu:Kosovo]]
[[fa:کوزوو]]
[[fr:Kosovo]]
[[ga:An Chosaiv]]
[[gv:Kosovo]]
[[gl:Kosovo]]
[[ko:코소보]]
[[hi:कोसोवो]]
[[hsb:Kosovo]]
[[hr:Kosovo]]
[[io:Kosovo]]
[[id:Kosovo]]
[[is:Kosóvó]]
[[it:Kosovo]]
[[he:קוסובו]]
[[jv:Kosovo]]
[[ka:კოსოვო]]
[[kk:Косово]]
[[kw:Kosova]]
[[lad:Kosovo]]
[[la:Ager Merulensis]]
[[lv:Kosova]]
[[lt:Kosovas]]
[[li:Kosovo]]
[[hu:Koszovó]]
[[mk:Косово]]
[[ms:Kosovo]]
[[nah:Cosovo]]
[[nl:Kosovo]]
[[ja:コソボ]]
[[no:Kosovo]]
[[nn:Kosovo]]
[[nrm:Kosovo]]
[[oc:Kosova]]
[[uz:Kosovo]]
[[pms:Kòsovo]]
[[nds:Kosovo]]
[[pl:Kosowo]]
[[pt:Kosovo]]
[[ksh:Kosovo]]
[[ro:Kosovo]]
[[qu:Kusuwu]]
[[ru:Косово]]
[[sq:Kosova]]
[[simple:Kosovo]]
[[sk:Kosovo]]
[[sl:Kosovo]]
[[sr:Косово и Метохија]]
[[sh:Kosovo i Metohija]]
[[fi:Kosovo]]
[[sv:Kosovo]]
[[ta:கொசோவோ]]
[[th:คอซอวอ]]
[[vi:Kosovo]]
[[tr:Kosova]]
[[uk:Косово]]
[[ur:کوسووہ]]
[[vec:Kosovo]]
[[zh-yue:科索沃]]
[[diq:Kosova]]
[[zea:Kosovo]]
[[bat-smg:Kuosuovs]]
[[zh:科索沃]]</text>
