      <text xml:space="preserve">{{cleanup}}
{| border=1 cellpadding=2 cellspacing=0 align=right width=300px style=&quot;margin: 0 0 1em 1em; font-size: 90%;&quot;
|+&lt;big&gt;'''Republika e Kosovës'''&lt;br&gt;'''Republic of Kosova'''&lt;/big&gt;
| style=background:#deffad; align=center colspan=2 |
|- 
| align=center | [[Image:Albania_flag_large.png|125px|Flag of Albania]]||
|-
| [[Official language]]s || width=60% |  [[Albanian language|Albanian]]
|-
| [[Capital]] || [[Prishtina|Prishtinë]]
|-
| [[Area]]&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;- Total&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;- % water || &lt;br&gt;[[1 E10 m2|10,887]] km&amp;sup2;&lt;br&gt;n/a
|-
| valign=top | [[Population]]&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;- Total ([[2003]])&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;- [[Population density|Density]]&lt;br&gt; || &lt;br&gt;2.0 - 2.2 million (est.)&lt;br&gt;185/km&amp;sup2; (approx)
|-
| valign=top | [[List of ethnic groups|Ethnic groups]]&lt;br&gt;([[2003]]) || [[Albanians]]:88%&lt;br&gt;[[Serbs]]: 7%&lt;br&gt;Others: 5%
|-
| [[Time zone]] || [[UTC]] +1
|-
| valign=top | [[Airline]] carrier || -
|}

'''Kosovo'''  [[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Republika e Kosoves'', it´s a contry in [[Balkan]]. Kosovo bordes with [[Republic of Macedonia]], [[Albania]] and [[Serbia and Montenegro]].

===Geographical regions===

[[Metohija]], called '''Rrafshi i Dukagjinit''' (&quot;Dukagjin plateau&quot;) by Albanians, is the large [[basin]] at the west of the province. The region includes the towns of &lt;!-- following WD flow --&gt; [[Istok]], [[Pec|Pe&amp;#263;]], [[Decani|De&amp;#269;ani]], [[Djakovica|&amp;#272;akovica]], [[Orahovac]], and [[Prizren]]. The second largest region is '''Kosovo''', a basin around the [[Sitnica]] river containing the cities of [[Urosevac|Uro&amp;#353;evac]], [[Pristina]], [[Vucitrn|Vu&amp;#269;itrn]], and [[Kosovska Mitrovica]]. '''Kosovo Polje''' ([[Kosovo Field]]) is just a small field which was the site of the [[Battle of Kosovo]]; when the communist government changed the name of the province to Kosovo in [[1968]], they also started pushing &quot;Kosovo Polje&quot; as the name of entire region. Part of Kosovo along the river [[Lab]] which contains the city of [[Podujevo]] is called [[Malo Kosovo]] (literally &quot;Little Kosovo&quot;). Just between the Metohia and Kosovo is the [[Drenica]] with the cities of [[Srbica]] and [[Klina]] and [[Malisevo|Mali&amp;#353;evo]]. Around the river [[Binacka Morava|Bina&amp;#269;ka Morava]] is [[Binacko Pomoravlje|Bina&amp;#269;ko pomoravlje]]. At the southmost tip of the province, along the border with [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]] lie the [[Gorani|Gora]], [[Sredacka Zupa|Sreda&amp;#269;ka &amp;#381;upa]] and [[Sirinicka Zupa|Sirini&amp;#263;ka &amp;#381;upa]].

==Name==
{{seemain|Names of Kosovo}}
===Former official names===

* [[Dardania]]
* Kosova Sancak ( [[1455]]-[[1878]]
* Kosova Vilajet [[1878]]-[[1912]]
* Autonomous Kosovo-Metohijan Area ([[1945]]-[[1963]])
* Autonomous Province of Kosovo and Metohija ([[1963]]-[[28 November]] [[1968]])
* Socialist Autonomous Province of Kosovo ([[28 November]] [[1968]]-[[1989]])
* Kosovo - Kosova (UN protectorate) ([[2000]] - present)
*Kosovo was also called 
**''Republika e Kosovës'' (26 - 30 September [[1991]]-[[2000]]) by the shadow Kosovo Albanian government between a [[1990]] declaration of independence and the Kosovo War in 1999. Only Albania recognised the province's independence but neither Serbia nor the international community followed suit. The &quot;[[Republic of Kosovo]]&quot; was effectively replaced by the current UN protectorate following the war.
** ''[[Kosovo i Metohija]]'' ([[1989]]-[[2000]])- [[Kosovo War]] and the rise of Slobodan Milosevic international is not recognised

=== Kosovo placenames ===
Most localities in Kosovo have distinct Serbian and Albanian placenames, nearly all very similar, some differing radically, Like that of Ferizaj, for example. It went from Ferizaj to Ferizovic and eventually changed into Urosevac. During the Serbian administration of 1912-1999, Kosovo localities were known internationally almost exclusively by their Serbian names.
Since the United Nations took over administration of the province in June 1999, the administration and some international organisations have adopted a policy of treating both versions equally. For the sake of convenience, this article gives alternative placenames the first time a locality is mentioned, but will use the more familiar Serbian version thereafter. A useful list of Serbian and Albanian forms of Kosovo placenames is available at [[Municipalities of Kosovo]]
== History ==
== Politics and international status ==

{{Politics of Kosovo}}

Kosovo's international status is anomalous in that although it is a province of the Republic of Serbia, actual administration is presently conducted by the [[United Nations]] with no involvement on the part of the Serbian governments (under Security Council resolution 1244 of [[10 June]] [[1999]]; see [http://www.un.org/Docs/scres/1999/sc99.htm Security Council Resolutions 1999]).  The government of the province is the responsibility of the [[United Nations Mission in Kosovo]] (UNMIK). Under the terms of the [[Kumanovo agreement]] and subsequent UN [[Security Council]] [[Resolution 1244]], which ended the [[Kosovo War]], security is provided by the Kosovo Force (KFOR), which is led by [[NATO]] and is answerable to UNMIK.

UNMIK has so far established a provisional assembly, provisional government and the office of provisional president, which are legislative and executive bodies under UNMIK's control. Control of security, justice and external affairs are still under full UNMIK control. The [[Assembly of Kosovo]] was elected in November [[2001]] and [[Ibrahim Rugova]] was elected as president in March [[2002]]. The seat of the assembly, government and president is in [[Pristina]]. So far, the parliament has enacted and UNMIK approved a constitutional framework, customs code, and two criminal codes.

UNMIK is issuing travel documents which serve instead of [[passport]]s in countries which are accepting to recognise them as such; UNMIK is also issuing identity cards and car plates, which again are valid only in countries which are accepting them as such. Kosovo's postal system is also usable only in countries which are accepting to recognise it as such (letters addressed to Kosovo only, or to Serbia and Montenegro have a chance of not arriving; the Universal Postal Union advises correspondents to use &quot;Kosovo (UNMIK)&quot; as the address [http://www.upu.int/post_code/en/countries/KOS.pdf]).

UNMIK has also created a police force (the [[Kosovo Police Service]]) with employees from all ethnic communities (Albanian, Serbian, Roma, Bosniac, Roma, etc), and manages the province's railways and airline ([[Kosova Airlines]]). The airspace of the province is controlled by KFOR. UNMIK uses the United Nations flag.

The Constitutional Framework enacted by the Kosovo assembly (with UNMIK approval) has adopted a policy of [[affirmative action]] in the assembly to ensure that the province's minorities are properly represented. Out of 120 seats, 10 are reserved for Serbs and another 10 for non-Albanian minorities, while the remaining 100 seats are elected through direct voting.

Kosovo is still recognised internationally as a part of Serbia. Its final status has not yet been resolved, though talks on the subject are planned for later in 2005, and considerable difficulties lie ahead in reconciling the apparently incompatible positions of the Serbian and Albanian sides. The Albanians reject Serbian sovereignty; although the fall of the Milosevic government has eased some of the political tensions between the two administrations, most Kosovo Albanians do not believe that the Serbian side will respect Albanian rights. On the other side, Serbia is adamantly opposed to the independence of Kosovo and for historical and religious reasons continues to see the province as the heartland of Serbian culture. The international community is reluctant to see Kosovo become independent, as its independence without Serbia's consent would violate [[international law]] (the principles of [[territorial integrity]] and [[noninterference in internal affairs]]). It could also potentially provide a precedent for the secession of the [[Republika Srpska]] from [[Bosnia]], which could re-ignite the war in that country. The most likely outcome is the indefinite continuation of the current situation (with EU institutions taking over the roles of UN and NATO, a process which can be observed in present-day [[Bosnia]])

== Administrative ==

[[Image:Kosova subdivisions.PNG|thumb|[[Municipalities of Kosovo]]]]


In the present, these towns are adminstrated by UNMIK.
*[[Gjakova District]] 
**[[Gjakova|Gjakovë]] - [[Deqani|Deçan]] - [[Rahoveci|Rahovec]]
*[[Gjlani District]]
**[[Gjlani|Gjilan]] - [[Kamenicë|Kamenicë]] - [[Vitia|Viti]]
*[[Mitrovica District]]
**[[Mitrovica|Mitrovicë]]- [[Leposavici|Albaniku]] - [[Zubin Potok|Zubin Potok]]-[[Skenderaji|Skenderaj]] - [[Vushtrria|Vushtrri]] - [[Zveçani|Zveçan]]
*[[Peja District]]
**[[Peja|Pejë]] - [[Klinë|Klinë]] - [[Istoku|Burim]]
*[[Prishtina District]]
**[[Prishtina|Prishtinë]] - [[Fushë Kosova|Fushë Kosovë]] - [[Lipjan|Lipjani]] - [[Gllogovci|Gllogovc]] - [[Novobërdë|Novobërdë]] - [[Obiliqi|Kastriot]] - [[Podujeva|Podujevë]]
*[[Prizreni District]]
**[[Prizreni|Prizren]] - [[Dragashi|Opojë]] - [[Malisheva|Malishevë]] - [[Suhareka|Suharekë]]
*[[Ferizaji District]]
**[[Ferizaji|Ferizaj]] - [[Shtime]] - [[Kaçaniku|Kaçanik]] - [[Shterpci|Shterpcë]]
*[[Presheva District]]
**[[Presheva|Preshevë]] - [[Bujanoci|Bujanoc]] - [[Medvegja|Medvegjë]]
---- 
&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; [[Presheva District]] with subdivisions [[Preshevë]], [[Bujanoc]], [[Medvegjë]] is administered by Serbien

== Currency ==

[[UNMIK]] declared the [[euro]] to be official currency of the province in [[2001]] in the course of implementing a currency reform. This was undertaken to replace the previous widespread use of the [[Deutschmark]], which had become ''de facto'' currency even before the 1999 war. However, the [[Serbian dinar]] remains an official currency, though used principally by the [[Kosovo Serb enclaves]]; it is only used sporadically outside of them. Most trade is conducted using the euro, Kosovo's administration uses euros exclusively, and all commercial banks use the euro as the primary currency. Of other international currencies, the [[United States dollar]] and [[Swiss franc]] are the most widespread.

== Demographics ==

''Main article: [[Demographic history of Kosovo]]''

[[Albanians]] comprise an almost 90% majority of the population of the province. Their percentage as a proportion of the province's population has increased steadily over time as a result of a high birth rate, immigration from [[Albania]] and concentrion of Albanians from areas formerly under the Sandjak of Nish, southern Serbia. Most of the province's Albanian population became refugees during the war but quickly returned to their homes at its end. In the aftermath of the conflict, several hundred thousand non-Albanians (especially [[Serbs]] and [[Roma (people)|Romas]]) fled the province to escape renewed intercommunal violence. The non-Albanian population of Kosovo has continued to fall in recent years due to a combination of economic hardship and tension (and occasional violence) in ethnically mixed area.

According to the 2000 Living Standard Measurement Survey of the Statistical Office of Kosovo[http://www.sok-kosovo.org/pdf/population/Kosovo_population.pdf], Kosovo's total population is approximately 1,970,000 with the following ethnic proportions:

* 88% Albanians (1,733,600) 
* 7% Serbs (137,900) 
* 1.9% Muslim Slavs (37,400) 
* 1.7% Roma (33,500) 
* 1% Turks (19,700)

==Science and culture==

*National Network Libraries

==See also==

* [[Kosovo i Metohija]] ('''Pro Serb''')
* [[Kosovo]] 
* [[List of Kosovars]] ('''pro EU''')
* [[Assembly of Kosovo]] UNMIK
* [[Government of Kosovo]] UNMIK
* [[Prime Minister of Kosovo]] UNMIK
* [[President of Kosovo]] UNMIK
* [[Battle of Kosovo|Battle of Kosovo (1389)]] History  
* [[National awakening and the birth of Albania]] History
* [[Unrest in Kosovo]] (about the March 2004 unrest) UNMIK






[[Category:History of Kosovo]]</text>
