      <text xml:space="preserve">{{otheruses}}

{| {{prettyinfobox}}
|+&lt;big&gt;&lt;big&gt;''' Kosovo '''&lt;br/&gt;'''Kosova'''&lt;br/&gt;'''Косово и Метохија &lt;/big&gt;&lt;/big&gt;
| align=center | [[Image:SerbiaMontenegro-Kosovo3.png]]
| {{Serbia and Montenegro 2}}
|-
| [[Official language]]s
| [[Albanian language|Albanian]], [[Serbian language|Serbian]], [[English language|English]]{{sup|1}}
|-
| [[Capital]]
| [[Prishtina]]
|-
| [[President of Kosovo|President]]
|[[Fatmir Sejdiu]]
|-
| [[Prime Minister of Kosovo|Prime Minister]]
| [[Bajram Kosumi]]
|-
| [[Area]]&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; Total&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; % water
| &lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;[[1 E10 m²|10,887]] km²&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;n/a
|-
| valign=top | [[Population]]&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; Total ([[2003]])&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; [[Population density|Density]]&lt;br/&gt;
| &lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;2.4 million (est.)&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;185/km² (approx)
|-
| valign=top | [[List of ethnic groups|Ethnic groups]]&lt;br/&gt;([[2003]])
| [[Albanians]]: 88%&lt;br/&gt;[[Serbs]]: 7%&lt;br/&gt;Others: 5%
|-
| [[Time zone]]
| [[UTC]] +1
|-

|colspan=2|{{sup|1}} [[Turkish language|Turkish]] at local levels
|}

'''Kosovo''' ([[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Kosovë'' / ''Kosova'', [[Serbian language|Serbian]]: KOSOVO is a province of [[Serbia]]. It is the subject of an ongoing territorial dispute between Serbia and the province's majority ethnic [[Albanians|Albanian]] population. It lies within Serbia's traditional borders inside the [[Serbian-Montenegrin]] federation, but since the [[Kosovo War]] it has been administered by the [[United Nations]] under the auspices of [[UNMIK]]. The province's final status has yet to be determined; talks on this issue are scheduled for later in [[2006]].

== Geography ==

[[image:UTkosovo rel small 92.jpg|thumb|left|275px|Physical map of Kosovo]]

With an area of [[1 E10 m²|10,887]] [[square kilometre|km²]] (4,203 [[square mile|mi²]]) and a population of over two million on the eve of the 1999 crisis, Kosovo borders [[Montenegro]] to the northwest, with the districts of [[Raška]], [[Toplica District|Toplica]], [[Jablanica]] and [[Pčinja District|Pčinja]] in [[Central Serbia]] to the North and East; [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]] to the south, and [[Albania]] to the southwest. The largest cities are [[Prishtina]]/[[Priština]] the capital, with estimated 500,000 inhabitants, and [[Prizren]] in the southwest with 120,000: five other towns have populations in excess of 50,000.

== History ==
{{main|History of Kosovo}}
In relative terms, the [[Slavs]], notably the [[Serbs]] were latecomers to the region. They came to the territories of roughly modern-day Kosovo in the [[6th century|6th]] and [[7th century|7th centuries]]. 

While [[Metohija]] became an integral part of the [[Principality]], later [[Grand Principality]] of [[Rascia]], Kosovo was ruled by the [[Bulgarians]] since the 850s up to [[1014]]. 

In [[1166]] - [[1168]], a [[Serbian]] nobleman from [[Zeta]], [[Stefan Nemanja|Stephen Nemanja]] asserted to the Grand Princely throne and conquered most of Kosovo in an uprising against the [[Byzantines]]. Nemanja was eventually defeated and had to return some of his conquests, and vouched to the [[Byzantine Emperor]] that he will not raise hand against him. In [[1183]], Nemanja embarked on a new offensive with the Hungarians after the Byzantine Emperor's death. Nemanja's son, [[Stefan Prvovenčani|Stephen II the First-crowned of Nemanja]] recorded Nemanja's conquests, as Nemanja restored the Kosovar lands from the [[Greeks]], the border of the [[History of Serbia|Serbian realm]] reaching the river of [[Lab]]. ''King of [[Serbs]]'' Stephen II finished the inclusion of the Kosovan territories in [[1208]], by which he had conquered [[Prizren]] and [[Lipljan]]; and moved the border of his realm to the [[Šar mountain]]. 

After the [[Empire]] of [[Tsar]] [[Stefan Dušan]] prior to his death fell into disarray in the [[14th century]], feudal anarchy cought up with the country, with Kosovo becoming a part of [[Prince Lazar]] of [[History of Serbia|Moravian Serbia]]'s domain. The Ottomans invaded the realm and met the [[Serbian]] [[Army]] on [[28 June]] [[1389]], near [[Kosovo Polje]]. The famous epic [[Battle of Kosovo]] followed, in which Prince Lazar himself lost his life. Through the cunningness of [[Serbian]] national hero [[Miloš Obilić]], the [[Sultan]] was murdered and the new Sultan had, despite winning the battle, to retreat to consolidate his power. The local House of [[Branković]] came to prominence as the local lords of Kosovo, under [[Vuk Branković]]. With the temporary fall of the [[History of Serbia|Serbian Despotate]] in [[1439]]. Another great battle occurred between the Hungarian troops supported by Skanderbeg, and [[Ottoman]] troops supported by the Brankovićs in [[1448]]. Hungarian King [[John Hunyadi]] lost the battle after a 2-day fight, but essentially stopped the Ottoman advance northwards. Kosovo then became vassalaged to the [[Ottoman Empire]], until its direct incorporation after the final fall of Serbia in [[1459]]. 

The [[Ottomans]] brought [[Islamisation]] with them, particularly in towns, and later also created the [[Viyalet of Kosovo]] as one of the [[Ottoman]] territorial entities. This brought a great shift, as the [[Serb Orthodox Church|Serbian Orthodox Christian]] population began to lose its majority. The 17th century saw numerous demographic changes in [[Metohija]], as a new wave of [[Albanian]] populations started to migrate to the region from northern [[Albania]]. Kosovo was taken by the Austrian forces during the Great War of [[1683]] - [[1699]]. In [[1690]], the Serbian Patriarch Arsenije III led ''30,000'' souls from Kosovo to evade Ottoman wrath, since Kosovo was just retaken by the [[Ottomans]]. Other Serbian migrations from Kosovo continued across the [[18th century]]. 

With the rise of Albanian nationalism, the [[League of Prizren]] was formed in [[1878]] in [[Prizren]]. In [[1910]], an [[Albanian]] uprising spread from [[Prishtina]] and lasted until the Ottoman Sultan's visit of Kosovo in [[June]] [[1911]].

After the [[1912]] and [[1913]] [[Balkan Wars]], Kosovo became an integral part of the [[History of Serbia|Kingdom of Serbia]], while [[Metohija]] became a part of the [[History of Montenegro|Kingdom of Montenegro]]. The [[Albanian]] population was negotiated to be evacuated from [[Kosovo]] to [[Turkey]], but this was not conducted. 

After the [[1918]]-[[1929]] period of the [[Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes]] and the [[1929]]-[[1941]] [[Kingdom of Yugoslavia]], Yugoslavia was invaded by the [[Axis forces]]. The greatest part became a part of [[Italian]]-controlled [[Greater Albania|Fascist Albania]], and smaller bits by the [[Nazi]]-[[Fascist]] [[Greater Bulgaria|Tsardom of Bulgaria]] and [[Nazi]] [[German]]-occupied [[Serbia|Kingdom of Serbia]]. Occasions of genocide and killings occured as 100,000 [[Kosovan]] [[Serbs]] were executed in [[Albanian]] extermination camps like that of the Vulnetari militia, and at least that much more were exiled. 

In the 1980s and 1990s, Kosovo would pass through a period of heavy ethnic tendencies, growing nationalism and separatist movements that would eventually break out into open conflicts known as the [[1999]] [[Kosovar War]], which saw thousands of Kosovar Albanians killed and over one million expelled from their homes, 800,000 of them beyond Kosovo's borders.

''See also first and second [[Battle of Kosovo]], [[1389]] and [[1448]]''

==Disputes over language, culture and citizenship==

[[Image:Flag_of_Serbia (state).svg|right|150px|thumb|Flag of Serbia|The official flag of Serbia is the official flag of Kosovo and Metohija. It is used in all Serb-inhabited areas of Kosovo.]]
The province is most widely known as 'Kosovo' and this has become the standard in international and United Nations usage. In [[Albanian language|Albanian]] this name becomes 'Kosova', which is more often found within Kosovo and in official use by the Provisional Institutions, though both Albanian and Serbian are official languages. Wherever political and cultural sensitivity are particularly important, the international community will use 'Kosovo/Kosova' to describe the province and adopt a similar standard for many place names. Whilst the formal title 'Republic of Kosova' has fallen out of use with the integration of Kosovo Albanian politics into the UNMIK system, the formal Serbian title 'Kosovo i Metohija' remains in colloquial and official use in parts of Kosovo and in Serbia proper, where parallel institutions for Kosovo remain until final status is resolved.

The question of what to call the inhabitants of Kosovo collectively has also aroused debate. The two words accepted by the [[Oxford English Dictionary]] are &quot;Kosovar&quot; (borrowed from Albanian), the most widely used variant in English, by a long way, and &quot;Kosovan&quot; (using the English rules for [[demonym]]s) much less used. As Kosovo has no formal statehood, current international usage is to refer to Kosovo [[Serbs]] and Kosovo [[Albanians]]. Most of the Albanian-descended community in Kosovo would prefer the use of Kosovar or Kosovan because of the attendant political overtones, whilst the Serb minority continue to think of themselves as Serb or Serbian (from Kosovo).

As for language and citizenship, so for cultural and political symbols. The province has never had an official flag of its own. The [[Flag of Albania|Albanian flag]] is used unofficially by the Kosovo Albanian-dominated administration and the vast majority of Kosovo Albanians; although recently the presidential flag of the presidency is being used as an unofficial flag of Kosovo, as could be seen during [[Ibrahim Rugova]]'s funeral [http://sq.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ibrahim_Rugova].

The Serb-inhabited area of north Kosovo uses only the [[flag of Serbia]], which is formally the flag of the whole of Serbia including Kosovo, although this usage is rejected by virtually all Kosovo Albanians.

== Politics and international status ==

Kosovo's international status is anomalous in that although it is a Serbian province within the State Union of Serbia and Montenegro, administration is presently conducted by the [[United Nations]] with little or no involvement on the part of the Serbia government (under Security Council resolution 1244 of [[10 June]] [[1999]]; see [http://www.un.org/Docs/scres/1999/sc99.htm Security Council Resolutions 1999]).  The government of the province is the responsibility of the [[United Nations Mission in Kosovo]] (UNMIK). Under the terms of the [[Kumanovo agreement]] and subsequent UN [[Security Council]] [[Resolution 1244]], which ended the [[Kosovo War]], security is provided by the Kosovo Force (KFOR), which is led by [[NATO]] and is answerable to UNMIK.

{{Politics of Kosovo}}
UNMIK has so far established a provisional assembly, provisional government and the office of provisional president, which are legislative and executive bodies under UNMIK's control. Control of security, justice and external affairs are still under full UNMIK control. Elections for the [[Assembly of Kosovo]] were held in November [[2001]] and again in [[2004]]. [[Ibrahim Rugova]] was elected as president in March [[2002]]. The seat of the assembly, government and president is in [[Prishtina]]/[[Pristina]]. So far, the parliament has enacted and UNMIK approved a constitutional framework, customs code, and two criminal codes.

The Constitutional Framework enacted by the Kosovo assembly (with UN Security Council approval) has adopted a policy of [[affirmative action]] in the assembly to ensure that the province's minorities are properly represented. Out of 120 seats, 10 are reserved for Serbs and another 10 for non-Albanian minorities, while the remaining 100 seats are elected through direct voting. UNIK does not take account, though, of Serbs and other non-Albanians who have left Kosovo as a result of interethnic tension, many of whom are unable to reclaim lost property or safely to attend elections. The process of 'returns' of these displaced persons has yet to begin in earnest, as a result of insufficient funding and a perceived inability of the UN to control violence against minority groups, as well as a concern on the part of Kosovo Albanians that an increased proportion of Serbs will undermine the chances for an independent Kosovo.

Kosovo is still recognised internationally as a part of Serbia. Its final status has not yet been resolved, though talks on the subject are planned for 2006, and considerable difficulties lie ahead in reconciling the irreconcilable Kosovo Albanian, Kosovo Serb and Belgrade positions. The Kosovo Albanians reject Serbian sovereignty and demand secession from the country. On the other side, Serbia is opposed to yielding any of its territory and domestic opinion, supported by the existence of a centuries old written, material and architectural history, continues to see the province as the heartland of Serbian culture.

The international community is reluctant to see Kosovo become independent, as its independence without Belgrade's consent would violate [[international law]] (the principles of [[territorial integrity]] and [[noninterference in internal affairs]]). It could also potentially provide a precedent for the parallel Serb demands of secession for the [[Republika Srpska]] from [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]], re-igniting tension in that country. The [[NATO]] countries insisted on the republican borders as the only acceptable solution during the wars in [[Croatia]] and [[Bosnia-Herzegovina]] in the 1990s, but this does not rule out that they might revisit this in the case of Kosovo vis-à-vis Serbia and Montenegro. Questions have also been raised about whether an independent Kosovo would be politically or economically viable, given its small size, the state of its economy and fears that criminal and smuggling networks have strong positions there.

UNMIK is issuing travel documents which serve instead of [[passport]]s in countries which recognise them, and issues identity cards and car plates, which again are valid only in certain countries. UNMIK has created a police force (the [[Kosovo Police Service]]) with employees from all ethnic communities (Albanian, Serbian, Roma, Bosniac, etc) and manages the province's railways and airline ([[Kosova Airlines]]). The airspace of the province is controlled by KFOR.

On [[January 21]], [[2006]], the President of Kosovo, Dr.[[Ibrahim Rugova]], died aged 61.  On [[February 10]], 2006, [[Fatmir Sejdiu]] was elected to be the second President by a 80-12 vote in parliament.

== Economy ==

[[UNMIK]] declared the [[euro]] to be official currency of the province in [[2001]] in the course of implementing a currency reform. This was undertaken to replace the previous widespread use of the [[Deutschmark]], which had become ''de facto'' currency even before the 1999 war. However, the [[Serbian dinar]] remains an official currency, though used principally in the [[Kosovo Serb enclaves]]; it is only used sporadically outside of them. Most trade is conducted using the euro, Kosovo's administration uses euro exclusively, and all commercial banks use the euro as the primary currency. Of other international currencies, the [[United States dollar]] and [[Swiss franc]] are the most widespread.

== Demographics ==
Ethnic Albanians now comprise almost 90% of the population of the province. In the aftermath of the conflict several hundred thousand non-Albanians, particularly [[Serbs]], [[Janjevci|Janjevs]], and [[Roma people|Roma]], either followed Serb soldiers as they withdrew, were forcibly expelled by the Albanian majority or fled the province to escape continued ethnic violence or to escape the future rule of Kosovo by non-Serbians. The non-Albanian population of Kosovo has continued to fall since the arrival of NATO and the UN as a result of violence, perceived intimidation, and economic hardship. Many still live in communal camps in [[Serbia proper]], cared for by international relief agencies and the Serbian governement. However, there have been many attempts by Kosovo's government to resettle Non-Albanians in the region which have largely been successful, including the resettlement of well over one thousand Serbians and Roma from 2004 - 2005.

According to the 2000 Living Standard Measurement Survey of the Statistical Office of Kosovo[http://www.sok-kosovo.org/pdf/population/Kosovo_population.pdf], Kosovo's total population is estimated between 1,8 and 2,0 million in the following ethnic proportions:
* 88% [[Albanians]] (between 1,584,000 and 1,733,600) 
* 7% [[Serbs]] (between 126,000 and 140,000)	
* 3% [[Muslims by nationality|Muslims]] and [[Bosniaks]] (54 to 60 thousand) 
* 2% [[Roma people|Roma]] (36 to 40 thousand) [[Roma in Mitrovica Camps]]
* 1% [[Turks]] (18 to 20 thousand)
However, the figures are highly disputable and may presently include an Albanian majority well into the 90s in percentile.

==Presidents==
*[[Ibrahim Rugova]], [[1992]]-[[2006]] (deceased)
*[[Fatmir Sejdiu]], [[2006]]-present

==Prime Ministers==

*[[Bajram Rexhepi]], [[2002]]-[[2004]]
*[[Ramush Haradinaj]], [[2004]]-[[2005]]
*[[Bajram Kosumi]], [[2005]]-present

==See also==
* [[Assembly of Kosovo]]
* [[Government of Kosovo]]
* [[Prime Minister of Kosovo]]
* [[President of Kosovo]]
* [[Post and Telecom of Kosovo]]
* [[Battle of Kosovo|Battle of Kosovo (1389)]]
* [[Municipalities of Kosovo]]
* [[National awakening and the birth of Albania]]
* [[Subdivisions of Kosovo]]
* [[Unrest in Kosovo]] (about the March 2004 unrest)
&lt;!--It appears that this is an actual article, but it was removed * [[Sexual trafficking in Kosovo]] --&gt;

==External links==
{{sisterlinks|Kosovo}}
*[https://www.osce.org/documents/mik/1999/11/1620_en.pdf Human Rights in Kosovo: As Seen, As Told. Volume I, October 1998 - June 1999].
* {{wikitravel}}
* [http://www.xixonline.com  Restaurant in Kosovo] - Restaurant in Kosova 
* [http://www.lib.utexas.edu/maps/kosovo.html Kosovo maps from the Perry-Castañeda Library Map Collection]
* [http://www.chmouel.com/geeklog/gallery/gallery_individual.php/mkosovo/ A collection of photos from Kosovo]


===Pro-Albanian===
* [http://BalkanUpdate.blogspot.com Balkan Update]- A blog with news, analysis and the lates updates from Balkans
* [http://www.eciks.org Economic Initiative for Kosovo] - &quot;...latest news, analysis and publications from the Kosovar economy&quot;
* [http://www.rtklive.com  RTK] - Kosova's public television (news in Albanian, Serbian, Turkish and Roma)
* [http://www.albanian.com/main/countries/kosova Albanian.com] - general information
* [http://www.kosovaelire.com/ Kosova e lirë] (Free Kosova) -- Material about Kosovars and Albanians in Albanian language. 
* [http://beqiraj.com/kosova/de/ General information from Beqiraj.com] (in German)
* [http://beqiraj.com/kosova/al/ General information from Beqiraj.com] (in Albanian)
* [http://www.alb-shkenca.org/images/stories/Why%20Independence.pdf Why Independence for Kosovo?] A summary of the case for an independent Kosova by two Prishtina intellectuals

===Pro-Serb===
*[http://www.kosovo.com/sk/history/kosovo_origins/default.htm  Hugo Roth, ''Kosovo Origins'']: a historian's comprehensive overview
* [http://www.kosovo.com/ Kosovo.com] Serbian Orthodox Church's official website on Kosovo

* [http://www.rastko.org.yu/kosovo/crucified/default.htm Account of destroyed Serbian Orthodox churches in Kosovo and Metohija]
* [http://groups.yahoo.com/group/decani/ Kosovo Newsgroup archive]
* [http://www.kc.gov.yu/ Coordination Center of SCG and the Republic of Serbia for Kosovo]
* [http://www.srbija.sr.gov.yu/kosovo-metohija/ Serbian Government Kosovo-Metohija site]
* [http://www.tserkovnost.org/srbija/ Eastern Orthodox Resource Centre]
* [http://www.balkanpeace.org/hed/archive/nov01/hed4304.shtml Al Qaeda involvement in Kosovo] 

{{Serbia and Montenegro}}

[[Category:Disputed territories]]
[[Category:Kosovo| ]]
[[Category:United Nations]]

[[ar:قوصوة]]
[[ast:Kosovo]]
[[bg:Косово]]
[[bs:Kosovo]]
[[ca:Kosovo]]
[[cs:Kosovo]]
[[da:Kosovo]]
[[de:Kosovo]]
[[et:Kosovo]]
[[es:Kosovo]]
[[eo:Kosovo]]
[[fr:Kosovo]]
[[ko:코소보]]
[[hr:Kosovo]]
[[id:Kosovo]]
[[it:Kosovo]]
[[he:קוסובו ומטוחיה]]
[[lt:Kosovas]]
[[hu:Koszovó]]
[[mk:Косово]]
[[nl:Kosovo]]
[[nds:Kosovo]]
[[ja:コソボ]]
[[no:Kosovo]]
[[nn:Kosovo]]
[[pl:Kosowo i Metohija]]
[[pt:Kosovo]]
[[ro:Kosovo]]
[[ru:Косово]]
[[sq:Kosova]]
[[sr:Косово и Метохија]]
[[fi:Kosovo]]
[[sv:Kosovo]]
[[tr:Kosova]]
[[uk:Косово]]
[[zh:科索沃]]</text>
