      <text xml:space="preserve">{{otheruses}}

{{POV}}

[[Image:SerbiaMontenegro-Kosovo.png|framed|Kosovo region]]
 
'''Kosovo and Metohija''' ([[Serbian language|Serbian]]: '''&amp;#1050;&amp;#1086;&amp;#1089;&amp;#1086;&amp;#1074;&amp;#1086; &amp;#1080; &amp;#1052;&amp;#1077;&amp;#1090;&amp;#1086;&amp;#1093;&amp;#1080;&amp;#1112;&amp;#1072;'''; [[Albanian language|Albanian]]: '''Kosova'''), usually called just '''[[Kosovo]]''', is an autonomous province of [[Serbia]] (which together with [[Montenegro]] constitutes [[Serbia and Montenegro]]). It is currently administered by the [[United Nations]] following the recent [[Kosovo War]], and its final status is as yet undetermined. The majority of the mostly Albanian population declared the independence of the '''Republic of Kosova''' in [[1990]], but this parallel government is not recognized internationally except by [[Albania]].

== Geography ==
[[image:UTkosovo rel small 92.jpg|thumb|300px|Map of Kosovo]]

With an area of [[1 E10 m2|10,887]] [[square kilometre|km&amp;sup2;]] and a population of almost 2 million on the eve of the 1999 crisis, Kosovo borders with [[Montenegro]] to the northwest, the rest of [[Serbia]] (often called &quot;[[Serbia proper]]&quot; in English) to the north and east, the [[Former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia]] to the south and [[Albania]] to the southwest. The largest cities are [[Prishtina|Pri&amp;#353;tina]], the capital, with estimated 500,000 inhabitants, and [[Prizren]] in the southwest with 120,000: five other towns have populations in excess of 50,000.

===Geographical regions===

[[Metohija]], called '''Rrafshi i Dukagjinit''' (&quot;Dukagjin plateau&quot;) by Albanians, is the large [[basin]] at the west of the province. The region includes the towns of &lt;!-- following WD flow --&gt; [[Istok]], [[Pec|Pe&amp;#263;]], [[Decani|De&amp;#269;ani]], [[Djakovica|&amp;#272;akovica]], [[Orahovac]], and [[Prizren]]. The second largest region is '''Kosovo''', a basin around the [[Sitnica]] river containing the cities of [[Urosevac|Uro&amp;#353;evac]], [[Pristina]], [[Vucitrn|Vu&amp;#269;itrn]], and [[Kosovska Mitrovica]]. '''Kosovo Polje''' ([[Kosovo Field]]) is just a small field which was the site of the [[Battle of Kosovo]]; when the communist government changed the name of the province to Kosovo in [[1968]], they also started pushing &quot;Kosovo Polje&quot; as the name of entire region. Part of Kosovo along the river [[Lab]] which contains the city of [[Podujevo]] is called [[Malo Kosovo]] (literally &quot;Little Kosovo&quot;). Just between the Metohia and Kosovo is the [[Drenica]] with the cities of [[Srbica]] and [[Klina]] and [[Malisevo|Mali&amp;#353;evo]]. Around the river [[Binacka Morava|Bina&amp;#269;ka Morava]] is [[Binacko Pomoravlje|Bina&amp;#269;ko pomoravlje]]. At the southmost tip of the province, along the border with [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]] lie the [[Gorani|Gora]], [[Sredacka Zupa|Sreda&amp;#269;ka &amp;#381;upa]] and [[Sirinicka Zupa|Sirini&amp;#263;ka &amp;#381;upa]].

==Name==

The province is best known as '''Kosovo''' - this name has been the most widely used by maps and gazetteers within Serbia and abroad. The alternative spelling ''Kossovo'' was frequently used until the early [[20th century]] and before that, ''Cassovo'' or ''Cassua'', an [[Italian language|Italianisation]] of the name.

The name Kosovo (pronounced &quot;KOS-so-vo&quot; by [[Serbs]], &quot;ko-SO-va&quot; by [[Albanians]]) appears to have its roots in the [[Slavic peoples|Slavic]] word ''kos'' which means &quot;[[blackbird]]&quot;. The root word is widely used as a [[toponym]] in Slavic countries and the historical [[German language|German]] name for [[Kosovo Polje]], ''Amselfeld'', does indeed mean &quot;field of the blackbird&quot;. The name &quot;Kosovo&quot; is itself used in other Slavic countries, appearing in [[Belarus]], [[Bosnia]], [[Bulgaria]], [[Croatia]] and [[Russia]] (see [[Kosovo (disambiguation)]]). 

[[Image:Kosov.png|right|thumb|431px|All places in the world whose names begin with &quot;Kosov&quot;]]
'''Kosova''' (pronounced &quot;ko-SO-vah&quot;) is the [[Albanian language|Albanian]] spelling for the province. Albanians tend to use &quot;Kosova&quot; exclusively in preference to the Serbian name, which many of them reject as a symbol of Serbian dominance. It is also occasionally spelled as ''Kosovë''; this is due to the fact that in Albanian, adding the definite article to a noun changes the ending of the word. 

Some Albanian researchers claim that the name is a Serbian form of an old Albanian placename meaning &quot;high plain&quot;, but this is not a widely accepted theory and would not explain the widespread distribution of the name across the Slav countries. The Albanian form is generally thought to be an Albanian version of an originally Slavic placename.

The Albanian-populated areas of the province and Albania itself tend to use &quot;Kosova&quot; exclusively. &quot;Kosovo&quot; is used, again almost exclusively, in the Serb-populated north of the province and in the rest of the former [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]]. The international community tries to steer a middle path by referring formally to &quot;Kosovo/Kosova.&quot; In practice, however, the Serbian variant is still the most frequently used outside of Kosovo while the Albanian variant is widely used by &quot;internationals&quot; within the province.

The use of the two alternative names is a highly sensitive political issue for both Serbs and Kosovo Albanians, who regard the use of the other side's name as being a denial of their own side's territorial rights (in much the same way that [[Macedonian Slavs|Macedonians]] and [[Greece|Greeks]] have disputed the name of the [[Republic of Macedonia]]). During the [[Kosovo War]], [[United States]] President [[Bill Clinton]] was criticised for frequently using &quot;Kosova&quot; and appearing to pronounce &quot;Kosovo&quot; the Albanian way, putting the emphasis on the middle syllable rather than on the first syllable as in the Serbian pronunciation. This may, however, have been a simple mispronunciation.

'''Metohia''' (alternatively spelled ''Metohija'') derives from the [[Greek language|Greek]] word ''&amp;#956;&amp;#949;&amp;#964;&amp;#972;&amp;#967;&amp;#953;&amp;#945;'' (''metochia''), a term which denotes [[church]]-owned land. Historically, the estates of the [[Serbian Orthodox Church]] were located principally in this region. The name does not indicate a modern administrative district. Albanians tend not to use the name, regarding it as a statement of Serbian territorial ownership (which they reject for political reasons), and instead prefer to call it ''Rrafsh i Dukagjinit'', the &quot;Dukagjin plateau&quot;.

The province is occasionally referred to as '''Kosmet''', a contraction of ''Kosovo and Metohia'' which has tended to be used by the Serbian government.

===Former official names===

* Autonomous Kosovo-Metohijan Area ([[1945]]-[[1963]])
* Autonomous Province of Kosovo and Metohija ([[1963]]-[[1968]])
* Socialist Autonomous Province of Kosovo ([[1968]]-[[1989]])
* Autonomous Province of Kosovo and Metohija ([[1989]]-present)

Kosovo has also been called the ''Republic of Kosova'' by Albanians since a [[1990]] declaration of independence, but this is unrecognised by Serbia or the international community and has no official status.

===Adjective form===

The question of what to call the inhabitants of Kosovo collectively has also aroused some debate. They have been called variously &quot;Kosovars&quot;, &quot;Kosovans&quot; and &quot;Kosovians&quot;. The two words accepted by the [[Oxford English Dictionary]] are &quot;Kosovar&quot; (borrowed from Albanian), the most widely used variant in English, by a long way, and &quot;Kosovan&quot; (using the English rules for [[demonym]]s) much less used. &quot;Kosovian&quot; is considered a non-standard word and very little used at all.

As Kosovo has no formal statehood, current international usage is to refer to Kosovo Serbs and Kosovo Albanians. Most of the Albanian-descended community in Kosovo would prefer the use of Kosovar or Kosovan because of the attendant political overtones, whilst the Serb minority continue to think of themselves as Serb or Serbian (from Kosovo).

=== Kosovo placenames ===

Most localities in Kosovo have distinct Serbian and Albanian placenames, nearly all very similar, some differing radically. During the Serbian administration of 1912-1999, Kosovo localities were known internationally almost exclusively by their Serbian names.

Since the United Nations took over administration of the province in June 1999, the administration and some international organisations have adopted a policy of treating both versions equally. For the sake of convenience, this article gives alternative placenames the first time a locality is mentioned, but will use the more familiar Serbian version thereafter. A useful list of Serbian and Albanian forms of Kosovo placenames is available at [http://www.osce.org/kosovo/documents/reports/hr/part1/p5app.htm www.osce.org/kosovo/documents/reports/hr/part1/p5app.htm].

==Flag==

The province never had an official flag of its own. The [[Flag of Albania|Albanian flag]] is used by the Albanian-dominated administration and the vast majority of Kosovo Albanians. The Serb-inhabited area of north Kosovo uses only the [[flag of Serbia and Montenegro]], which is formally the flag of the whole of Serbia including Kosovo, although this usage is rejected by virtually all Kosovo Albanians. The United Nations administration in Kosovo intends to establish a new flag for the province, which will undoubtedly be very different from the two national communities' existing flags. The current [[flag of Bosnia and Herzegovina]] emerged from a similar process of national reconciliation.

== History ==

Modern Kosovo has only existed as a political or territorial entity since [[1945]]. Before then, its territory was ruled entirely or partially by Italian-occupied Albania, Serbia, Montenegro, the [[Ottoman Empire]], the [[Byzantine Empire]], [[Bulgaria]] and the [[Roman Empire]]. Some have suggested that Kosovo has been a single distinctive region since ancient times but this is strongly contradicted by [[archaeology|archaeological]] findings and historic records. Nor has Kosovo's population been ethnically consistent over the years: the province's complex ethnic map has included Latins, [[Turks]], [[Roma (people)|Roma]], [[Gorani]] ([[Slavic Muslims]]), Circassians and [[Jew]]s in addition to Serbs and Albanians. 

=== Kosovo from prehistory to 1455 ===

Little is known about Kosovo before about the [[11th century]] AD. The region was certainly inhabited in [[prehistory|prehistoric]] times: in particular, [[bronze age|Bronze]] and [[Iron Age]] [[tomb]]s have been found only in Metohia, and not in Kosovo. Later, the whole territory of Kosovo became part of the [[Roman Empire]], although it is not clear whether it was part of the province of [[Moesia]] or was divided between Dalmatia and Moesia (a view which is supported by some archaeological evidence). [http://www.rastko.org.yu/kosovo/istorija/malkolm/djankovic-facts.html]

According to most historians, Serbs entered the Balkans around the late [[6th century|6th]] or early [[7th century]] AD, possibly migrating from the northern [[Caucasus]] where [[Ptolemy]] placed the &quot;Serboi&quot; in the [[2nd century]] AD. The initial spread of the [[Slavic peoples|Slavic]] population of the [[Balkans]] was much larger then today, reaching well into [[Greece]] and [[Albania]]. Placenames derived from Slavic root words are still widespread in the remaining non-Slav Balkan countries and particularly northern Albania to this day (Kamenica).

The origins of the Albanians are much less clear. Most believe that they are descended from the [[Illyrian]]s, ancient inhabitants of the western Balkans in Roman times, although [[Romanian]] historians have suggested that they may alternatively be descended from the ancient [[Thracian|Thracians]], who inhabited the Eastern and Central Balkans. Albanian historians claim that in around the [[6th century]] the Illyrians were forced south into what is now Albania by Slav tribes - the predecessors of modern day Serbs. This claim is challenged by the fact that [[Byzantine]] chroniclers date the arrival of Albanians (Alvanoi) from Southern [[Italy]] at [[1043]] in central Albania ([[Durrës]]) as mercenaries in the army of [[Maniakis]]. Some historians, including Serbian, claim the Albanians originate from the [[Caucasus]], particularly [[Caucasian Albania]], but most historians dispute these claims. Albanian linguists suggest that the vocabulary and structure of the [[Albanian language]] points to a much earlier presence in the western Balkans. ''See also: [[Origin of Albanians]]''

The Kosovo region lay on the outer fringes of the Byzantine Empire and lay directly in the path of the Slav expansion. From about the 850s until about [[1014]], it was ruled by [[Bulgaria]]. Byzantine control was subsequently reasserted by the forceful emperor [[Basil II|Basil &quot;the Bulgar Slayer&quot;]]. Serbia at this time did not exist: a number of small Slav kingdoms lay to the north and west of Kosovo, of which [[Raska]] (Rascia, central modern Serbia) and [[Dioclea]] ([[Montenegro]] and norther Albania) were the strongest. In the 1180s, the Serbian ruler [[Stefan Nemanja]] seized control of Dioclea and parts of Kosovo. His successor (also called [[Stefan Prvovencani|Stefan]]) took control of the rest of Kosovo by [[1216]], creating a state incorporating most of modern [[Serbia-Montenegro]].

During the rule of the Nemanjic dynasty, many [[Serbian Orthodox]] churches and monasteries were built throughout Serbian territory, particularly Kosovo which became the economic, demographic, religious and political heartland. The Nemanjic rulers alternatively used both Prizren and Pristina as their capitals. Large estates were given to Serbian monasteries in Metohia (which included parts of Albania and Montenegro), for which the area earned the designation ''Metohia'' or &quot;monastic land&quot;. The most prominent churches in Kosovo - the [[Patriarchate]] at [[Pec]], the church at Gracanica and the monastery at Visoki Decani near Decani - were all founded during this period.  Kosovo was economically important, as the modern Kosovo capital [[Pristina]] was a major trading centre on routes leading to ports on the [[Adriatic Sea]]. As well, mining was an important industry in Novo Brdo and Janjevo which had its communities of émigré [[Saxony|Saxonians]] miners and [[Ragusa]]ns merchants.

The ethnic composition of Kosovo's population during this period is a controversial issue among Serbian and Albanian historians. Serbs, Albanians and [[Vlachs]] were all clearly present, as all three groups were named explicitly in Serbian monastic charters or ''chrysobulls'' along with a token number of [[Greeks]], [[Armenians]] and [[Bulgarians]]. A majority of the names given in the charters are overwhelmingly Slavic rather than Albanian. This has been interpreted as evidence of a crushing Serbian majority. However th chrysobulls show Serbian named sons to Albanian-named fathers and vice-versa. Albanian historians have suggested that this is evidence of cultural  assimilation of an alleged pre-[[Ottoman]] Albanian population in '''Kosovo''' yet this is undermined by records of Serbian-named fathers giving sons Albanian names (which would surely not have happened if the assimilation was a one-way process) and the fact that such cases of mixed names represent a small fraction of less than a twentieth of all the names. This Serbian claim seems to be supported by the Turkish cadastral tax-census ([[defter]]) of 1455 which took into account religion and language and found an overwhelming [[Kosovo_population_data-points|Serb majority]]. 

Ethnic identity in the [[Middle Ages]] was somewhat fluid throughout Europe and people at that time do not appear to have defined themselves rigidly by ethnic group. About all that can be said for sure is that Serbs appear to have been the dominant population culturally, and were probably a demographic majority as well.

In [[1355]], the Serbian state fell apart on the death of Tsar [[Stefan Dusan]] and dissolved into squabbling fiefdoms. The [[Ottoman Empire]] took the opportunity to exploit Serbian weakness and invaded, meeting the Serbian army on the field of [[Kosovo Polje]] on [[June 28]], [[1389]]. The [[Battle of Kosovo]] ended in the deaths of both the Serbian [[Prince Lazar]] and the Ottoman Sultan [[Murad I]]. Although the battle has been mythologised as a great Serbian defeat, at the time opinion was divided as to whether it was a Serbian defeat, a stalemate or even a Serbian victory. Serbia maintained its independence and sporadic control of Kosovo until a final defeat in [[1455]], following which it became part of the Ottoman Empire.

=== Kosovo from 1455 to 1912 ===

Teritorry of today's province was for centuries ruled by the [[Ottoman Empire]]. During this period, several administrative districts (known as [[sancak]]s (&quot;banners&quot; or districts) each ruled by a ''sancakbeyi'' (roughly equivalent to &quot;district lord&quot;)) have included parts of the territory as parts of their territories. Despite the imposition of [[Muslim]] rule, large numbers of [[Christians]] continued to live and sometimes even prosper under the Ottomans. A process of [[Islamisation]] began shortly after the beginning of Ottoman rule but it took a considerable amount of time - at least a century - and was concentrated at first on the towns. It appears that many Christian inhabitants converted directly to [[Islam]], rather than being replaced by [[Muslims]] from outside Kosovo. A large part of the reason for the conversion was probably economic and social, as Muslims had considerably more rights and privileges than Christian subjects. Christian religious life nonetheless continued, with churches largely left alone by the Ottomans, but both the Orthodox and Catholic churches and their congregations suffered from high levels of taxation.

Around the [[17th century]], there is evidence of an increasingly visible Albanian population initially concentrated in Metohia. It has been claimed (often by Serbian historians) that this was the result of migrations out of the south-west (i.e. modern [[Albania]]), and that the putative migrants brought Islam with them. There is certainly evidence of ''some'' migration: many Kosovo Albanians have surnames characteristic of inhabitants of the northern Albanian region of Malësi. However, many others do not. It is also clear that many Slavs - presumably members of the Serbian Orthodox Church - converted to Islam under Ottoman rule. Today, most Slavic Muslims of Serbia live in the [[Sandzak]] region of southern Serbia, northwest of Kosovo. Historians believe that there was probably a pre-existing population of probably [[Catholic]] Albanians in Metohia who mostly converted to Islam, but remained strictly a minority in a still largely Serb-inhabited region.

In [[1689]], Kosovo was greatly disrupted by the [[Ottoman-Habsburg war]] ([[1683]]-[[1699]]), in one of the pivotal events in Serbian national mythology. In October 1689, a small [[Austrians|Austrian]] force under Margrave [[Ludwig of Baden]] breached into Turkey and reached as far as Kosovo, following their earlier capture of [[Belgrade]]. Many Serbs and Albanians pledged their loyalty to the Austrians, some joining Baden's army. This was by no means a universal reaction; many other Serbs and Albanians fought alongside the Ottomans to resist the Austrian advance. A massive Ottoman counter-attack the following summer drove the Austrians back to their fortress at [[Nis]], then back to Belgrade, then finally back across the [[Danube]] into [[Hungary]] from whence they had come in the first place. 

The Ottoman offensive was accompanied by savage reprisals and looting, prompting many Serbs - including [[Arsenije III]], Patriarch of the Serbian Orthodox Church - to flee along with the Austrians. This event has been immortalised in Serbian history as the ''Velika Seoba'' or &quot;Great Migration&quot;. It is traditionally said to have accounted for a huge exodus of hundreds of thousands of Serbian refugees from Kosovo and Serbia proper, which left a vacuum filled by a flood of Albanian immigrants. Arsenije himself wrote of a figure of &quot;30,000 souls&quot; (i.e. individuals) who fled with him to Hungary, a figure confirmed by other sources.

In [[1878]], one of the four [[vilayets]] with Albanian inhabitants that formed the [[League of Prizren]] was [[Vilayet of Kosovo]]. The League's purpose was to resist both Ottoman rule and incursions by the newly emerging Balkan nations.

in [[1910]], an Albanian organised insurrection broke out in [[Pristina]] and soon spread to the entire vilayet of Kosovo; lasting for three months. The Ottoman Sultan visited Kosovo in June [[1911]] during peace settlement talks covering all Albanian-inhabited areas.

===20th century===

Following the [[First Balkan War]] of [[1912]], Kosovo was internationally recognised as a part of Serbia and Metohia as a part of Montenegro at the [[Treaty of London, 1913|Treaty of London]] in May [[1913]]. In [[1918]], Serbia became a part of the newly formed [[Kingdom of Yugoslavia]].

The partition of Yugoslavia, from 1941 and 1945, by the [[Axis Powers]] awarded most of the territory to the Italian-occupied [[Greater Albania]], and smaller part of it to German-occupied Serbia and the [[Greater Bulgaria]. During the occupation, thousands of Kosovo Serbs were expelled by armed Albanian groups, notably the [[Vulnetari]] militia. It is still not known exactly how many fell victim to this, but Serbian estimates put the figures at 10,000-40,000 killed with 70,000-100,000 expelled.

Following the end of the war and the establishment of [[Tito]]'s [[Communist]] regime, Kosovo was granted the status of an autonomous region of Serbia in [[1946]] and became an autonomous province in [[1963]]. The Communist government did not permit the return of many of the refugees.

With the passing of the [[1974]] Yugoslavia constitution, Kosovo gained virtual self-government. The province's government has applied Albanian curriculum to Kosovo's schools: surplus and obsolete textbooks from [[Enver Hoxha]]'s Albania were obtained and put into use.

Throughout the [[1980s]] tensions between the Albanian and Serb communities in the province escalated. The Albanian community favoured greater autonomy for Kosovo, whilst Serbs favoured closer ties with the rest of Serbia. There was little appetite for unification with Albania itself, which was ruled by a [[Stalinist]] government and had considerably worse living standards than Kosovo.

Serbs living in Kosovo complained of being discriminated by the Albanian dominated government of the province[http://www.kosovo.com/press1980.html] and complained of being neglected by the authorities in Belgrade. In August [[1987]], during the dying days of Yugoslavia's communist regime, Kosovo was visited by [[Slobodan Milosevic|Slobodan Milo&amp;#353;evi&amp;#263;]], then a rising politician. He appealed to Serb nationalism to further his career. Having drawn huge crowds to a rally commemorating the Battle of Kosovo, he pledged to Kosovo Serbs that &quot;No one should dare to beat you&quot;, and became an instant hero of Kosovo's Serbs. By the end of the year Milo&amp;#353;evi&amp;#263; was in control of the Serbian government.

In [[1989]], the autonomy of Kosovo and the northern province of [[Vojvodina]] was mostly revoked by a Serbia-wide referendum. The referendum implemented a new constitution which allowed a [[multi-party system]], introduced [[freedom of speech]] and promoted [[human rights]]. Even though in practice it was subverted by the Milosevic's government, which was sometimes rigging the results of elections, controlled the news media to an extent, and was accused of abusing human rights of its opponents and national minorities, this was a step forward from previous Communist constitution. It also significantly reduced the provinces' rights, permitting to the government of Serbia to exert direct control of many previously autonomous areas of governance. The constitutional changes handed control of the police, the court system, the economy, the education system and language policies to the Serbian government.

The new constitution was strongly opposed by many of Serbia's national minorities, who saw it as a means of imposing ethnically-based centralised rule on the provinces. Kosovo's Albanians refused to participate in the referendum, portraying it as illegitimate: as it was a Serbia-wide referendum and Albanians are a minority in Serbia as a whole, their participation would not have changed the outcome of the referendum.

The provincial governments also opposed the new constitution. It had to be ratified by their assemblies, which effectively meant voting for their dissolution. Kosovo's assembly initially opposed the constitution but in March [[1989]], when the assembly met to discuss the proposals, tanks and armored cars surrounded the meeting place, forcing the delegates to accept the amendments.

===1990s===
After the constitutional changes, the parliaments of all Yugoslavian republics and provinces, which until then had MPs only from the [[Communist Party of Yugoslavia]], were dissolved and multi-party elections were held for them. Kosovo Albanians refused to participate in the elections and held their own, unsanctioned elections instead. As election laws required (and still require) turnout higher than 50%, the parliament of Kosovo could not be established.

The new constitution abolished the individual provinces' official media, integrating them within the official media of Serbia while still having programs in the [[Albanian language]]. The Albanian-language media in Kosovo was suppressed. Funding was withdrawn from state-owned media, including that in the Albanian language in Kosovo. The constitution made creating privately-owned media possible, however their functioning was very difficult because of high rents and restricting laws. State-owned Albanian language television or radio was also banned from broadcasting from Kosovo [http://www.hrw.org/worldreport/Helsinki-12.htm]. However, privately-owned Albanian media outlets appeared; of these, probably the most famous is &quot;Koha Ditore&quot;, which was allowed to operate until late [[1998]] when it was closed after it published a calendar which was claimed to be a glorification of ethnic Albanian separatists.

The constitution also transferred control over state-owned companies to the Serbian government (at the time, most of the companies were state-owned and ''[[de jure]]'' they still are). In September [[1990]], up to 123,000 Albanian workers were fired from their positions in government and the media, as were teachers, doctors, and workers in government-controlled industries [http://www.bndlg.de/~wplarre/back337.htm], provoking a [[general strike]] and mass unrest. Some of those who were not sacked quit in sympathy, refusing to work for the Serbian government. Although the government claimed that it was simply getting rid of old communist directors, the sackings were widely seen as a purge of ethnic Albanians.

The old [[Albania]]n educational curriculum and textbooks were revoked and new ones were created. The curriculum was (and still is, as that is the curriculum used for Albanians in Serbia outside Kosovo) basically the same as Serbian and that of all other nationalities in Serbia except that it had education on and in [[Albanian language]]. The new textbooks were (still are) basically the same as those in Serbian, except that they were in Albanian language. Education in the Albanian language was withdrawn in 1992 and re-established in 1994. [http://www.osce.org/kosovo/documents/reports/hr/part1/ch1.htm] At the Pri&amp;#x0161;tina University, which was seen as a centre of Kosovo Albanian cultural identity, education in the Albanian language was abolished and Albanian teachers were also sacked en masse. Albanians responded by boycotting state schools and setting up an unofficial parallel system of Albanian-language education.

Kosovo Albanians were outraged by what they saw as an attack on their rights. Following mass rioting and unrest from Albanians as well as outbreaks of inter-communal violence, in February [[1990]], a state of emergency was declared, and the presence of the Yugoslav Army and police was significantly increased to quell the unrest.

Unsanctioned elections were held in [[1992]], which overwhelmingly elected [[Ibrahim Rugova]] as &quot;president&quot; of a self-declared Republic of Kosovo; however these elections were not recognised by Serbian nor any foreign government. In [[1995]], thousands of Serb refugees from [[Croatia]] settled in Kosovo, which further worsened relations between the two communities. 

Albanian opposition to sovereignty of Yugoslavia and especially Serbia had surfaced in rioting (1968 and March 1981) in the capital [[Prishtina|Pri&amp;#353;tina]]. Ibrahim Rugova advocated non-violent resistance, but later when it became apparent that this was not working, opposition took the form of separatist agitation by opposition political groups and armed action from 1996 by the &quot;[[Kosovo Liberation Army]]&quot; (''Ushtria Çlirimtare e Kosovës'', or UÇK). 

The KLA launched a low-intensity [[guerilla]] war characterised by regular bomb and gun attacks on Serbian security forces, state officials and civilians accused of &quot;collaborating&quot; with the Serbian government. In March 1998 Yugoslav army units joined Serbian police to fight the separatists, using military force on a large scale. In the months that followed, hundreds of people were killed and more than 200,000 fled their homes; most of these people were Albanians. Many Albanian families were forced to flee their homes at gunpoint, as a result of fighting between Serbian and KLA forces and also as the result of expulsions instigated by the security forces and associated paramilitary militias. A full-scale war broke out in March 1999 following the breakdown of negotiations between Serbian and Albanian representatives.

The [[United Nations]] estimated that during the Kosovo War, nearly 640,000 Albanians fled Kosovo between March 1998 and the end of April 1999. Most of the refugees went to [[Albania]], the [[Former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia]], or [[Montenegro]]. In an apparent attempt to erase the identities of many of the refugees, Serbian security forces confiscated their identification papers and vehicle number plates, and many other personal records were destroyed as well. This made it difficult to distinguish with certainty the identity of returning refugees after the war. Serbian sources claim that many Albanians from Macedonia and Albania have since migrated to Kosovo in the guise of refugees.

In [[June]] of 1999, the [[NATO]]-led Kosovo Force ([[KFOR]]) entered the province following the [[Kosovo War]]. Before and during the handover of power, a large number of Serbs (estimated by Serbs to be around 300,000) and other non-Albanians blamed by some for collaborating with the Serbian forces, mostly [[Roma (people)|Romas]], fled the province; large numbers still live in temporary camps and shelters in Serbia proper. In [[2002]], Serbia and Montenegro reported hosting 277,000 internally displaced people (the vast majority being Serbs and Roma from Kosovo), which included 201,641 persons displaced from Kosovo into Serbia proper, 29,451 displaced from Kosovo into Montenegro, and about 46,000 displaced within Kosovo itself, including 16,000 returning refugees unable to inhabit their original homes. [http://www.refugees.org/world/countryrpt/europe/yugoslavia.htm] 

In [[March 17]], [[2004]], serious [[unrest in Kosovo]] led to several deaths and the destruction of a large number of Orthodox churches and monastries in the province, as Albanians clashed with Serbs. Another exodus of Kosovo Serbs was reported to have occurred, although its dimensions are unclear.

== Politics and international status ==

Kosovo's international status is anomalous in that although it is formally a province of the Republic of Serbia, actual administration is presently conducted by the [[United Nations]] with no involvement on the part of the Serbian governments (under Security Council resolution 1244 of [[10 June]] [[1999]]; see [http://www.un.org/Docs/scres/1999/sc99.htm Security Council Resolutions 1999]).  The government of the province is the responsibility of the [[United Nations Mission in Kosovo]] (UNMIK). Under the terms of the [[Kumanovo agreement]] and subsequent UN [[Security Council]] [[Resolution 1244]], which ended the Kosovo War, security is provided by the Kosovo Force (KFOR), which is led by [[NATO]] and is answerable to UNMIK.

UNMIK has so far established a provisional assembly, provisional government and the office of provisional president, which are legislative and executive bodies under UNMIK's control. Control of security, justice and external affairs are still under full UNMIK control. The [[parliament]] was elected in November [[2001]] and [[Ibrahim Rugova]] was elected as president in March [[2002]]. The seat of the assembly, government and president is in [[Pristina]]. So far, the parliament has enacted and UNMIK approved a constitutional framework, customs code, and two criminal codes.

UNMIK is issuing travel documents which serve instead of [[passport]]s in countries which are accepting to recognise them as such; UNMIK is also issuing identity cards and car plates, which again are valid only in countries which are accepting them as such. Kosovo's postal system is also usable only in countries which are accepting to recognise it as such (letters addressed to Kosovo only, or to Serbia and Montenegro have a chance of not arriving; your best bet is Yugoslavia).

UNMIK has also created a police force (the [[Kosovo Police Service]]) with employees from both the Serbian and Albanian communities, and organised railways and airline ([[Kosova Airlines]]). The airspace of the province is controlled by KFOR. UNMIK uses the United Nations flag.

UNMIK has adopted a policy of [[positive discrimination]] in the Kosovo assembly to ensure that the province's minorities are properly represented. Out of 120 seats, 10 are reserved for Serbs and another 10 for non-Albanian minorities, while the remaining 100 seats are elected through direct voting.

Kosovo is still formally recognised internationally as a part of Serbia. Its final status has not yet been resolved, and considerable difficulties lie ahead in reconciling the apparently incompatible positions of the Serbian and Albanian sides. The Albanians reject Serbian sovereignty; although the fall of the Milosevic government has eased some of the political tensions between the two administrations, most Kosovo Albanians do not believe that the Serbian side will respect Albanian rights. On the other side, Serbia is adamantly opposed to the independence of Kosovo and for nationalist, historical and religious reasons continues to see the province as the heartland of Serbian culture. The international community is reluctant to see Kosovo become independent, as its independence without Serbia's consent would violate [[international law]] (the principles of [[territorial integrity]] and [[noninterference in internal affairs]]). It could also potentially provide a precedent for the secession of the [[Republika Srpska]] from [[Bosnia]], which could re-ignite the war in that country. The most likely outcome is the indefinite continuation of the current situation.

== Administrative subdivisions ==
''Main article: [[Subdivisions of Serbia and Montenegro]]''

Administrative subdivisions in Kosovo are known as [[opstina]]s, usually named after the largest town in them. They were originally set up by Yugoslavia and do not precisely parallel the administrative subdivisions set up by the parallel ethnic Albanian government.

== Economy ==

[[UNMIK]] declared the [[Euro]] as the official currency in Kosovo, however the [[Serbian dinar]] remains an official currency. The Dinar is widespread in Kosovo because most trade is done with the rest of Serbia and the [[Kosovo Serb enclaves]] also use it widely. The annual budget of UNMIK's Kosovo administration is calculated in Euros, and all commercial banks use Euro as the primary currency. Of other international currencies, [[Dollar]] and [[Swiss Franc]] are the most widespread.

== Demographics ==
''Main article: [[Demographic history of Kosovo and Metohia]]''

The population is currently comprised of almost a 90% majority of [[Albanian]]s, estimated at 80% prior to the Kosovo War of [[1999]] except for a brief interlude during the war as many non-Serbs fled before the Serbs armies. In the aftermath of 1999 Kosovo War, because of worsening ethnic relations and actions (alleged by the Serbs to be ethnic cleansing) by the Albanian Kosovars, [[Serbs]] and other non-Albanians, especially [[Roma_(people)|Romas]] left the province.

[[2002]] [[UN]] approximation. Total population 1.7 to 1.9 mn. &lt;sup&gt;[[Demographic history of Kosovo and Metohia#References|4]]&lt;/sup&gt;

* 88% Albanians (1,496,000 - 1,672,000)
* 6% Serbs (102,000 - 114,000)
* 3% Muslim Slavs (51,000 to 57,000)
* 2% Roma (34,000 - 38,000)
* 1% Turks (17,000 - 19,000).

==See also==

* [[Battle of Kosovo|Battle of Kosovo (1389)]]   
* [[National awakening and the birth of Albania]]
* [[Unrest in Kosovo]] (about the March 2004 unrest)

==External links==

* [http://www.lib.utexas.edu/maps/kosovo.html Kosovo maps from the Perry-Castañeda Library Map Collection]
* [http://www.chmouel.com/geeklog/gallery/gallery_individual.php/mkosovo/ A collection of photos from Kosovo]

===Pro-Albanian===
* [http://www.kosovo.com/ Kosovo.com]
* [http://www.assembly-kosova.org/ Kosovo Assembly]
* [http://www.pm-ksgov.net/ Kosovo Prime Minister]
* [http://www.kosova.com Kosova Information Center (in Albanian)]
* [http://www.kosovapress.com Kosovapress - Kosovo news agency]
* [http://beqiraj.com/kosova/al/ General information from Beqiraj.com] (in Albanian)
* [http://www.albanian.com/main/countries/kosova General information from Albanian.com]
* [http://www.alb-net.com/warcrimes-img/warcrimes.htm Kosovo Crisis Center - Serbian Massacres of Albanians]

===Pro-Serb===
* [http://www.rastko.org.yu/kosovo/crucified/default.htm Account of destroyed Serbian Orthodox churches in Kosovo and Metohia]
* [http://www.b92.net/english/news/index.php?order=priority&amp;nav_category=19 News from B92 Belgrade]
* [http://www.serbia.sr.gov.yu/news/kosovo News from the Serbian Government]
* [http://www.kosovo.net/ News from the Serbian Orthodox Church] 
** [http://groups.yahoo.com/group/decani/ News archive]
* [http://www.serbia.sr.gov.yu/coordination_centre/index.html Serb Kosovo Coordination Center]

{{Serbia_and_Montenegro}}

[[Category:Disputed territories]]
[[Category:Kosovo]]

[[de:Kosovo]]
[[et:Kosovo]]
[[fr:Kosovo]]
[[ja:&amp;#12467;&amp;#12477;&amp;#12532;&amp;#12457;]]
[[nl:Kosovo]]
[[pt:Kosovo]]</text>
