      <text xml:space="preserve">{{NPOV}}
{{otheruses}}

{| {{prettyinfobox}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
&lt;big&gt;''' Kosovo '''&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/big&gt;&lt;br&gt;
|-
| style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Image:Citys of Kosova.PNG]]
|-
| [[Official language]]s
| [[Albanian language|Albanian]], [[Serbian language|Serbian]]
|-
| [[Capital]]
| [[Prishtinë]]/[[Priština]]
|-
| [[President of Kosovo|President]]
| [[Fatmir Sejdiu]]
|-
| [[Prime Minister of Kosovo|Prime Minister]]
| [[Agim Çeku]]
|-
| [[Area]]&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; Total&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; % water
| &lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;[[1 E10 m²|10,912]] km²&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;n/a
|-
| valign=top | [[Population]]&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; Total ([[2003]])&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; [[Population density|Density]]&lt;br/&gt;
| &lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;2.1 million (est.)&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;220/km² (approx)
|-
| valign=top | [[List of ethnic groups|Ethnic groups]]&lt;br/&gt;([[2003]])
| [[Albanians]]: 88%&lt;br/&gt;[[Serbs]]: 7%&lt;br/&gt;Others: 5%
|-
| [[Time zone]]
| [[Coordinated Universal Time|UTC]] +1
|-

|
|}

'''Kosovo''' ([[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Kosovë'' / ''Kosova'', [[Serbian language|Serbian]]: Косово и Метохија / ''Kosovo i Metohija'') is a territory in South Eastern Europe. By the UN resolution 1244 (adopted in 1999), Kosovo is defined as autonomous territory within former [[Federal Republic of Yugoslavia]] under UN administration. Whether this will remain the case is still unclear, as the final status of Kosovo is the subject of an ongoing dispute between government of Serbia and Kosovo's government. Talks on this issue started in Vienna, on February 20, [[2006]] [http://www.unmikonline.org/news.htm#1703].

== Geography ==
[[image:UTkosovo rel small 92.jpg|thumb|left|275px|Physical map of Kosovo]]

With an area of [[1 E10 m²|10,912]] [[square kilometre|km²]] (4,203 [[square mile|mi²]]) and a population of over two million on the eve of the 1999 crisis, Kosovo borders [[Montenegro]] to the northwest, [[Serbia]] to the North and East; [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]] to the south, and [[Albania]] to the southwest. The largest cities are [[Prishtinë]]/[[Pristina]] the capital, with an estimated 500,000 inhabitants, and [[Prizren]] in the southwest with 120,000: five other towns have populations in excess of 50,000.

== History ==
{{main|History of Kosovo}}
It is likely that the region of Kosovo has been inhabited by [[Illyrians|Illyrian tribes]] since the [[Bronze Age]]. In ancient times the area has been known as [[Dardania (Europe)|Dardania]] and was settled by a tribe with the same name. The [[Dardani]] were of Illyrian and Thracian stock and some (notably Albanians) claim that Albanians are direct descendants of Illyrians. Illyrians organised resistance against [[Greeks]] and [[Ancient Rome|Romans]] for hundreds of years but after the long wars of Illyrian tribes against intruders, the region was later occupied by the [[Roman Empire]] under Emperor [[Augustus]]. When the Roman Empire split in [[395]] A.D., the Kosovo region came under the [[Byzantine Empire|Eastern Roman Empire]], later known as the Byzantine Empire.

According to ''[[De Administrando Imperio|De administrando imperio]]'' the [[Slavic peoples|Slavs]], who later would form the ethnic group of [[Serbs]], came to the territories of roughly modern-day Kosovo in the [[6th century|6th]] and [[7th century|7th centuries]]. They were invited to settle in the area south of [[Danube]] as farmers by Byzantine emperor [[Heraclius]] to protect the area from invading [[Eurasian Avars|Avars]]. The slavs were [[Christianization|Christianized]] in several waves between the [[7th century|7th]] and [[9th century]] with the last wave taking place between [[867]] and [[874]]. But by then Kosovo was ruled by the [[First Bulgarian Empire|Bulgarians]] from the 850s until [[1014]]. 

In [[1166]] - [[1168]], a [[Serbs|Serbian]] nobleman from [[Zeta]], [[Stefan Nemanja]], who called himself the King of Serbs, Albanians and Vallahians, asserted to the Grand Princely throne and conquered most of Kosovo in an uprising against the [[Byzantines]]. Nemanja was eventually defeated and had to return some of his conquests, and vouched to the [[Byzantine Emperor]] that he would not raise his hand against him. In [[1183]], Nemanja embarked on a new offensive with the Hungarians after the Byzantine Emperor's death. Nemanja's son, [[Stefan Prvovenčani|Stephen II the First-crowned of Nemanja]], recorded Nemanja's conquests, as Nemanja restored Kosovo from the [[Greeks]], the border of the [[History of Serbia|Serbian realm]] reaching the river of [[Lab]]. ''King of [[Serbs]]'' Stephen II finished the inclusion of the Kosovo territories in [[1208]], by which time he had conquered [[Prizren]] and [[Lipljan]], and moved the border of his realm to the [[Šar mountain]].

After the [[Empire]] of [[Tsar]] [[Stefan Dušan]] fell into disarray prior to his death in [[1355]], feudal anarchy caught up with the country during the reign of Tsar [[Stefan Uroš V]]. The area of Kosovo became a part of [[Prince Lazar]] of [[History of Serbia|Moravian Serbia]]'s domain. The Ottomans invaded the realm and met the coalition of South East European nobility on [[28 June]] [[1389]], near [[Prishtina]]/[[Priština]]. The coalition consisted of [[Serbs]], [[Bosnians]], [[Albanians]], [[Croats]], [[Hungarians]], [[Poles]] and even a contingent of [[Saxon]] mercenaries. The epic [[Battle of Kosovo]] followed, in which Prince Lazar himself lost his life and the coalition was broken. Through the cunning of [[Miloš Obilić]] [[Sultan]] [[Murad]] was murdered and the new Sultan [[Beyazid]] had, despite winning the battle, to retreat to consolidate his power. Both Prince [[Lazar]] and [[Miloš Obilić]] were canonised by the [[Serbian Ortodox Church]] for their efforts in the battle. The local House of [[Vuk Branković|Branković]] came to prominence as the local lords of Kosovo, under [[Vuk Branković]], with the temporary fall of the [[History of Serbia|Serbian Despotate]] in [[1439]]. Another great battle occurred between the Hungarian troops supported by (self-proclaimed King) Gjergj Kastrioti [[Skanderbeg]], and [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] troops supported by the Brankovićs in [[1448]]. Skanderbeg's troops which were going to help John Hunyadi were stopped by the Brankovic's troops, who was more or less a Turkish [[Vassal]]. Hungarian King [[John Hunyadi]] lost the battle after a 2-day fight, but essentially stopped the Ottoman advance northwards. Kosovo then became vassalaged to the [[Ottoman Empire]], until its direct incorporation after the final fall of Serbia in [[1459]]. 

The [[Ottoman Empire|Ottomans]] brought [[Islamisation]] with them, particularly in towns, and later also created the [[Viyalet of Kosovo]] as one of the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] territorial entities. This brought a great shift, as the Orthodox population (Serbian, Bulgarian, and Greek) began to lose its majority when masses of Turks and Albanians (Muslims or Catholics) moved to Kosovo. During the Islamisation many churches and holy orthodox places were raised to the ground or turned in to [[Mosques]], leaving a hard . Kosovo was taken by the Austrian forces during the Great War of [[1683]] - [[1699]] with great help of 5000 Albanians and their leader, a [[Catholic Archibishop]] [[Pjetër Bogdani]]. The archbishop died of plague during the war, and his grave was later reopened, with his body scattered and given to the dogs by the Ottomans because of his role as a leader of the rebellion. In [[1690]], the [[Serbian Patriarch of Peć]] [[Arsenije III]], who previously escaped a certain death, led 30,000 families from Kosovo, to evade Ottoman wrath since Kosovo had just been retaken by the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottomans]]. The people that followed him were probably mostly [[Serbs]], but it's possible also people of other different ethnic origins followed him. Due to the terror from the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottomans]], other migrations of Orthodox people from the Kosovo and Metohija area continued throughout the [[18th century]]. It is also noted that some [[Serbs]] adopted [[Islam]] and some even gradually fused with the predominantly Albanian Moslems and adopted their culture and even language.

In 1878, with the Berlin Conference, Serbia gained what is today known as Southern Serbia, a region as large as Kosovo. In less than two months, the region was [[ethnic cleansing|ethnically cleansed]] and its population was located in today's Kosovo, Macedonia, and largely Turkey. They inhabited almost every Kosovo and Macedonian town escaping from the Serbian army and population were committing against unarmed civilians. This is best described by [[Leon Trotsky]], who was the reporter for the 'Pravda' newspaper at the time. These populations are now known as 'muhaxher' (which means 'refugee') and are the ancestors of many who are still known by their same surnames, Muhaxheri. It is also estimated that 400.000 Serbs were clensed from the [[Vilayet of Kosovo]] between [[1876]] and [[1912]], especially during the [[Greco-Turkish War (1897)|Greek-Ottoman war]] in [[1897]]. (see [[Demographic history of Kosovo]])

As a response of Serbian, Bulgarian and Greek [[nationalism]], Albanians formed the [[League of Prizren]] in [[Prizren]]. Hundreds of Albanian leaders from all over Albania gathered and discussed the urgent issues concerning them. They succesfully opposed any Serbian invasion attemps. Serbia complained to the Western Powers that the promised territories were not being held because Ottomans were hesitating to do that. Western Powers put pressure to the Ottomans and in 1881, the Ottoman Army started the fighting against Albanians. The Prizren League created a Provisional Government with a President, Prime Minister (Ymer Prizreni)and Ministries of War (Sylejman Vokshi) and Foreign Ministry (Abdyl Frashëri). After three years of war, the Albanians were defeated. Many of the leaders were executed and imprisoned. In [[1910]], an [[Albanian]] uprising spread from [[Prishtina]] and lasted until the Ottoman Sultan's visit to Kosovo in [[June]] [[1911]]. The Aim of the League of Prizren as to unite the four Albanian Vilayets by merging the majority of Albanian inhabitants within the Ottoman Empire into one Albanian State. However at that time Serbs have consisted about 40% of Kosovo's overall population and were opposing the Albanian nationalism along with other Slavs and Turks in Kosovo.

In [[1912]] during the [[Balkan Wars]], Kosovo and [[Albania]] were conquered by [[Serbia]] while eastern part of Kosovo ([[Metohija]] for Ortodox) was captured by [[Montenegro]]. Serbia aimed at ethnically cleansing Kosovo of its Albanian population, but it was negotiated with Turkey for the Albanians to be transferred into [[Turkey]], with relative success. Serbian Academy of Sciences and Art leading member Dr. Vaso Cubrilovic carefully compiled a document describing in detail how the expulsion and colonization of Kosovo with Serbian population should take place. [http://www.elsie.de/pdf/B2002GatheringClouds.pdf] During the next decades, expulsion of Albanians from Kosovo took place.

In 1912, [[Albania]] declared independence and a year later, in 1913 ([[Conference of London]]), Albania was recognized as an independent state without Kosovo, as it already belonged to Serbia. In winter of 1915-16 Kosovo saw a large exodus of its [[Serbia]]n population and army; hundreds of thousands soldiers have died of starvation, extreme weather and Albanian reprisals as they were approaching the [[Allies]] in [[Corfu]] and [[Thessaloniki]]. (See [[Serbia in WWI]]).

After the [[1918]]-[[1929]] period of the [[Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes]] and the [[1929]]-[[1941]] [[Kingdom of Yugoslavia]], Yugoslavia was invaded by the [[Axis forces]]. The greatest part of Kosovo became a part of [[Italy|Italian]]-controlled [[Greater Albania|Fascist Albania]], and smaller bits by the [[Nazism|Nazi]]-[[Fascist]] [[Greater Bulgaria|Tsardom of Bulgaria]] and [[Nazism|Nazi]] [[German]]-occupied [[Serbia|Kingdom of Serbia]]. Since the Albanians had decided in the [[Conference of Bujan]] that Kosovo would remain Albanian, they have started immediately an ethnic cleansing of the non-Albanians in the occupied Kosovo. The infamous [[21st Waffen Mountain Division of the SS Skanderbeg (1st Albanian)|SS Division Skanderbeg]] is known to commited horrible crimes. Tens of thousands of Serbs lost their lives and around 75,000 Serbs fled Kosovo during the war. Hundreds of thousands more would leave in the following decades, following the shift of power in Kosovo.

After the war Kosovo gained the status of a province within [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]]. In the [[1974]] constitution, Kosovo gained more powers and was advanced to a status of which was almost that of a republic, but not in name. It was part of a Yugoslav Federation to some extent and part of Serbia to some extent. It is disputed but there was some intention that Kosovo should become the seventh republic. For a better picture of the position of Kosovo within YU-Federation, it is best to give the example that no decision could be taken at the Federative level without the vote and consent of Kosovo. 

In 1981 Kosovar students organized protests seeking that Kosovo become a republic within Yugoslavia. Those protests were harshly attacked by the Serbian government. In 1986, the Serbian Academy of Sciences and Arts published a document [[Memorandum]] which contained heavily Serbian nationalist rhetoric. With Serbian nationalism on the increase, [[Slobodan Milošević]] came to power. 

In 1989, following Milošević's rise of power (especially the Gazimestan gathering, marking 600 years from the [[Battle of Kosovo]]) the autonomy of Kosovo was revoked. Most Albanians organized a peaceful resistance movement. Most Albanians were expelled from their jobs, Albanian schools and the medical care system were shut down, and Kosovo was put under an effective [[apartheid]]. On July 2, 1990 Kosovo parliament declared Kosovo an independent country. In September of that year, the parliament, meeting in secrecy in the town of [[Kaçanik]], adopted the Constitution of the Republic of Kosovo. Two years later, Kosovo organized a referendum which was observed by international organisations but was not recognized internationally. With an 80% turnout, 98% voted for Kosovo to be independent. In the early nineties, Albanians organized a parallel state system which managed the non-violent resistance movement and organized a parallel system of education and healthcare, among other things.

With the events in Bosnia and Croatia coming to an end, the Serb government started moving Serb refugees from Croatia and Bosnia to Kosovo. In a number of cases, Albanian families were expelled from their apartments to make space for the refugees, only a few of whom remain in Kosovo today.

After the [[Dayton]] Agreement and numerous atrocities committed by Serb security forces inside Kosovo, the disillusioned Albanians organized into the [[Kosovo Liberation Army]] and started a guerrilla war for liberation. The Serb reaction was stiff in plundering Albanian villages and executing civilians. This triggered a 78-day [[NATO]] campaign in [[1999]]. During the conflict, some 12,000 Kosovar Albanians were killed and 500,000 to 800,000 expelled. Some 3,000 Albanians are still missing. The number of Serbian soldier, policemen, and civilian deaths is considered to be around 3,000, but it's also disputed to be much more, as 2,800 people of Serb origin are still missing, believed dead.

With the arrival of NATO, a large number of Serbs fled the region, estimated at 100,000 by the UNHCR. Around 120,000 remain in Kosovo and oppose any rule by Albanians. The Serbian government usually claims that some 250,000 Serbs have fled Kosovo. This instills fear within the Albanians and makes them oppose return projects. There are now, according to the European Stability Initiative, some 65,000 Kosovo Serbs living in Serbia. Some 20,000 may go back, mainly rural Serbs, while urban Serbs have largely integrated into Serbia and will not go back to Kosovo regardless of what their status will be. Many Serbs fear to return to their homes since it's proven not to be safe for them, even with [[UNMIK]] protection, notably the [[Unrest in Kosovo|unrest in 2004]].

The Status talks started in February 2006, it is set to end in the course of the year. The security of the minorities, must be provided by Kosovo Albanian governments, but it is disputed if the Kosovo Albanian Institutions can grant these guarantees. The [[EU]] still is said that they will not raise any demands for an independent Kosovo.

==Disputes over language, culture and citizenship==
The territory is most widely known as 'Kosovo' and this has become the standard in international and United Nations usage. In [[Albanian language|Albanian]] this name becomes 'Kosova', which is more often found within Kosovo and in official use by the Provisional Institutions, though both Albanian and [[Serbian language|Serbian]] are official languages. Wherever political and cultural sensitivity are particularly important, the international community will use 'Kosovo/Kosova' to describe the province and adopt a similar standard for many place names. While the formal title 'Republic of Kosova' has fallen out of use with the integration of Kosovo Albanian politics into the UNMIK system, the formal Serbian title 'Kosovo i Metohija' remains in colloquial and official use in parts of Kosovo and in Serbia proper, where parallel institutions for Kosovo remain until final status is resolved.

The question of what to call the inhabitants of Kosovo collectively has also aroused debate. The two words accepted by the [[Oxford English Dictionary]] are &quot;Kosovar&quot; (borrowed from Albanian), the most widely used variant in English, by far, and &quot;Kosovan&quot; (using the English rules for [[demonym]]s) much less used. As Kosovo has no formal [[state]]hood, current international usage is to refer to Kosovo [[Serbs]] and Kosovo [[Albanians]]. Most of the Albanian-descended community in Kosovo would prefer the use of Kosovar or Kosovan because of the attendant political overtones, while the Serb minority continue to think of themselves as Serb or Serbian (from Kosovo).

As for language and citizenship, so for cultural and political symbols. Kosovo had its own flag, when it used to have a province status within former Yugoslavia. The former province of Kosovo was identified with a flag similar to the one of Albania, but had a large star on the right-handside. The [[Flag of Albania|Albanian flag]] is used unofficially by the Kosovo Albanian-dominated administration and the vast majority of Kosovo Albanians; although recently the [[:Image:Kosovo Presidential Flag.gif|flag of the presidency]] is being used as an unofficial flag of Kosovo, as could be seen during [[Ibrahim Rugova]]'s funeral [http://sq.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ibrahim_Rugova].

The Serb-inhabited area of north Kosovo uses only the [[flag of Serbia]], which is formally the flag of Serbia, although this usage is rejected by virtually all Kosovo Albanians and other smaller minorities apart from Serbs and some Roma.

== Politics and international status ==
Kosovo's international status is anomalous. The administration is presently conducted by the [[United Nations]] with little or no involvement on the part of the Serbian government (under Security Council resolution 1244 of [[10 June]] [[1999]]; see [http://www.un.org/Docs/scres/1999/sc99.htm Security Council Resolutions 1999]).  The supervision of the government of Kosovo is the responsibility of the [[United Nations Mission in Kosovo]] (UNMIK). Under the terms of the [[Kumanovo agreement]] and subsequent UN [[Security Council]] [[Resolution 1244]], which ended the [[Kosovo War]], security is provided by the Kosovo Force (KFOR), which is led by [[NATO]] and is answerable to UNMIK.

{{Politics of Kosovo}}
UNMIK has so far established a provisional assembly, provisional government and the office of provisional president, which are legislative and executive bodies under UNMIK's control. Control of security, justice and external affairs are still under full UNMIK control. Elections for the [[Assembly of Kosovo]] were held in November [[2001]] and again in [[2004]] and were qualified as the most democratic elections in the Balkans. [[Ibrahim Rugova]] was elected as president in March [[2002]]. The seat of the assembly, government and president is in [[Prishtina]]/[[Pristina]]. So far, the parliament has enacted and UNMIK approved a constitutional framework, customs code, two criminal codes and some 200 laws.

The Constitutional Framework enacted by the Kosovo Assembly (with UN Security Council approval) has adopted a policy of [[affirmative action]] in the assembly to ensure that Kosovo's minorities are properly represented. Out of 120 seats, 10 are reserved for Serbs and another 10 for non-Albanian minorities, while the remaining 100 seats are elected through direct voting. UNMIK does not take account, though, the Serbs and other non-Albanians who have left Kosovo as a result of interethnic tension, many of whom are unable to reclaim lost property or safely to attend elections. The process of 'returns' of these displaced persons has yet to begin in earnest, as a result of insufficient funding and a perceived inability of the UN to control violence against minority groups, as well as a concern on the part of Kosovo Albanians that an increased number of Serbs will undermine the chances for an independent Kosovo.

Kosovo is still recognised internationally as a part of former Yugoslavia. Its final status has not yet been resolved, (talks on the subject started on 20 February 2006), and considerable difficulties lie ahead in balancing the irreconcilable Kosovo Albanian, Kosovo Serb and Belgrade positions. The Kosovo Albanians reject Serbian sovereignty and demand secession from the country. On the other side, Serbia is opposed to yielding any of its territory, and domestic opinion, supported by the existence of a centuries-old written, material and architectural history, continues to see the province as the heartland of Serbian culture.

The international community is becoming less and less reluctant to see Kosovo become independent, as the last Contact Group and UN Security Council meetings showed. The [[NATO]] countries insisted on the republican borders as the only acceptable solution during the wars in [[Croatia]] and [[Bosnia-Herzegovina]] in the 1990s, but this does not rule out that they might revisit this in the case of Kosovo vis-à-vis Serbia and Montenegro. Questions have also been raised about whether an independent Kosovo would be politically or economically viable, given its small populationa and the state of its economy. However the population of Kosovo is larger than several European countries including Estonia, Iceland, Luxembourg and Malta. But once its status is resolved and Kosovo has access to international monetary institutions the economic development will be possible. In early 2006, Western diplomats have come out clearly in support of an independent Kosovo, with guarantees for the minorities. 

UNMIK is issuing travel documents which serve instead of [[passport]]s in countries which recognise them, and issues identity cards and car plates, which again are valid only in certain countries[http://www.unmikonline.org/misc/traveldocs.htm]. UNMIK has created a police force (the [[Kosovo Police Service]]) with employees from all ethnic communities (Albanian, Serbian, Roma, Bosniac, etc) and manages the province's railways and airline ([[Kosova Airlines]]). The airspace and borders of Kosovo are controlled by KFOR.

The European Union runs the Kosovo economy in cooperation with the Kosovo institutions. The EU has initiated the [[Stabilisation Tracking Mechanism]], a special and separate track of EU integration for Kosovo. 

On [[January 21]], [[2006]], the President of Kosovo, Dr.[[Ibrahim Rugova]], died at age 61.  On [[February 10]], 2006, [[Fatmir Sejdiu]] was elected to be the second President by an 80-12 vote in parliament. On [[March 10]], 2006, [[Agim Çeku]] was appointed as the Prime Minister of Kosovo, during a voting by the Assembly of Kosovo.

== Economy ==
[[UNMIK]] declared the [[euro]] to be the official currency of the province in [[2001]] in the course of implementing a currency reform. This was undertaken to replace the previous widespread use of the [[Deutschmark]], which had become the ''de facto'' currency even before the 1999 war. However, the [[Serbian dinar]] remains an official currency, used principally in the [[Kosovo Serb enclaves]]; it is only used sporadically outside of them. Most trade is conducted using the euro; Kosovo's administration uses the euro exclusively, and all commercial banks use the euro as the primary currency. Of other international currencies, the [[United States dollar]] and [[Swiss franc]] are the most widespread.

== Demographics ==
Ethnic Albanians comprise almost 90% of the population of the province. In the aftermath of the conflict some one thousand non-Albanians, particularly [[Serbs]] and [[Roma]] either followed Serb soldiers as they withdrew, were forcibly expelled by the Albanian majority or fled the province to escape perceived threats of revenge by Albanians. The non-Albanian population of Kosovo has continued to fall since the arrival of NATO and the UN as a result of violence, perceived intimidation, and economic hardship. Many still live in communal camps in [[Serbia]] or [[Macedonia]] cared for by international relief agencies. However, there have been many attempts by Kosovo's government to resettle non-Albanians in the region which have largely been successful, including the resettlement of well over one thousand Serbians and Roma from 2004 - 2005. The Kosovo government has been widely praised for paying for the rebuilding of Serb houses in the aftermath of the 2004 riots. This has been marked as the first case of reparations in the history of the Balkans. 

According to the 2000 Living Standard Measurement Survey of the Statistical Office of Kosovo[http://www.sok-kosovo.org/pdf/population/Kosovo_population.pdf], Kosovo's total population is estimated between 1,8 and 2,0 million in the following ethnic proportions:
* 88% [[Albanians]] (between 1,584,000 and 1,733,600) 
* 7% [[Serbs]] (between 126,000 and 140,000)	
* 3% [[Muslims by nationality|Muslims]] and [[Bosniaks]] (54 to 60 thousand) 
* 2% [[Roma people|Roma]] (36 to 40 thousand) [[Roma in Mitrovica Camps]]
* 1% [[Turkish people|Turks]] (18 to 20 thousand)
However, the figures are highly disputable and may presently include an Albanian majority well above 90 percent.

==Presidents==
*[[Ibrahim Rugova]], [[1992]]-[[2006]] (deceased)
*[[Fatmir Sejdiu]], [[2006]]-present

==Prime Ministers==
*[[Bajram Rexhepi]], [[2002]]-[[2004]]
*[[Ramush Haradinaj]], [[2004]]-[[2005]]
*[[Bajram Kosumi]], [[2005]]-[[2006]]
*[[Agim Çeku]], [[2006]]-present

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Gjakova.jpg|[[Gjakova]]/[[Đakovica]]
Image:French Peugeot P4 dsc06852.jpg|[[KFOR]]
Image:Prishtina.jpg|[[Prishtina]]/[[Priština]]
Image:Prizen kosovo.jpg|[[Prizreni]]/[[Prizren]]
Image:Rahoveci.jpg|[[Rahovec]]/[[Orahovac]]
Image:Skenderbeuinprishtina.jpg|[[Skenderbeg]]
Image:Slava2005 6.jpg|[[Visoki Dečani monastery]]/[[Deçan monastery]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
* [[Assembly of Kosovo]]
* [[Government of Kosovo]]
* [[Prime Minister of Kosovo]]
* [[President of Kosovo]]
* [[Post and Telecom of Kosovo]]
* [[Battle of Kosovo|Battle of Kosovo (1389)]]
* [[Municipalities of Kosovo]]
* [[National awakening and the birth of Albania]]
* [[Subdivisions of Kosovo]]
* [[Unrest in Kosovo]] (about the March 2004 unrest)
&lt;!--It appears that this is an actual article, but it was removed * [[Sexual trafficking in Kosovo]] --&gt;

==External links==
{{sisterlinks|Kosovo}}
* [http://www.balkanforums.com Kosovo and the Balkans] - Discussion Forum
*[http://digital.library.unt.edu/govdocs/crs/search.tkl?q=kosovo&amp;search_crit=fulltext&amp;search=Search&amp;date1=Anytime&amp;date2=Anytime&amp;type=form  Congressional Research Service (CRS) Reports regarding Kosovo]
* {{wikitravel}}
* [http://www.rtklive.com  RTK - Kosova's public television - news in Albanian, Serbian, Turkish and Roma]
* [http://www.xixonline.com  Restaurant in Kosovo - Restaurant in Kosova]
*[https://www.osce.org/documents/mik/1999/11/1620_en.pdf Human Rights in Kosovo: As Seen, As Told. Volume I, October 1998 - June 1999].
* [http://www.lib.utexas.edu/maps/kosovo.html Kosovo maps from the Perry-Castañeda Library Map Collection]
* [http://www.chmouel.com/geeklog/gallery/gallery_individual.php/mkosovo/ A collection of photos from Kosovo]

===Pro-Albanian===
* [http://BalkanUpdate.blogspot.com Balkan Update]- A blog with news, analysis and the lates updates from Balkans
* [http://www.eciks.org Economic Initiative for Kosovo] - &quot;...latest news, analysis and publications from the Kosovar economy&quot;
* [http://www.albanian.com/main/countries/kosova Albanian.com] - general information
* [http://www.kosovaelire.com/ Kosova e lirë] (Free Kosova) -- Material about Kosovars and Albanians in Albanian language. 
* [http://beqiraj.com/kosova/de/ General information from Beqiraj.com] (in German)
* [http://beqiraj.com/kosova/al/ General information from Beqiraj.com] (in Albanian)
* [http://www.alb-shkenca.org/images/stories/Why%20Independence.pdf Why Independence for Kosovo?] A summary of the case for an independent Kosova by two Prishtina intellectuals

===Pro-Serb===
*[http://www.kosovo.com/sk/history/kosovo_origins/default.htm  Hugo Roth, ''Kosovo Origins'']: a historian's comprehensive overview
* [http://www.kosovo.com/ Kosovo.com] Serbian Orthodox Church's official website on Kosovo
* [http://www.rastko.org.yu/kosovo/crucified/default.htm Account of destroyed Serbian Orthodox churches in Kosovo and Metohija]
* [http://groups.yahoo.com/group/decani/ Kosovo Newsgroup archive]
* [http://www.kc.gov.yu/ Coordination Center of SCG and the Republic of Serbia for Kosovo]
* [http://www.srbija.sr.gov.yu/kosovo-metohija/ Serbian Government Kosovo-Metohija site]
* [http://www.tserkovnost.org/srbija/ Eastern Orthodox Resource Centre]
* [http://www.axisglobe.com/article.asp?article=689 Southern Serbia: The second Kosovo?]

[[Category:Disputed territories]]
[[Category:Kosovo| ]]
[[Category:United Nations]]

[[ar:قوصوة]]
[[ast:Kosovo]]
[[bg:تîٌîâî]]
[[zh-min-nan:Kosovo]]
[[bs:Kosovo]]
[[ca:Kosovo]]
[[cs:Kosovo]]
[[da:Kosovo]]
[[de:Kosovo]]
[[et:Kosovo]]
[[es:Kosovo]]
[[eo:Kosovo]]
[[fr:Kosovo]]
[[ko:ؤع¼ز؛¸]]
[[hr:Kosovo]]
[[id:Kosovo]]
[[it:Kosovo]]
[[he:קוסובו ומטוחיה]]
[[lt:Kosovas]]
[[hu:Koszovó]]
[[mk:Косово]]
[[nl:Kosovo]]
[[nds:Kosovo]]
[[ja:コソボ]]
[[no:Kosovo]]
[[nn:Kosovo]]
[[pl:Kosowo]]
[[pt:Kosovo]]
[[ro:Kosovo]]
[[ru:Косово]]
[[sq:Kosova]]
[[sr:Косово]]
[[fi:Kosovo]]
[[sv:Kosovo]]
[[tr:Kosova]]
[[uk:Косово]]
[[zh:科索沃]]</text>
