      <text xml:space="preserve">Kosova Airlines

'''Kosovo''' (known in [[Albanian language|Albanian]] as '''Kosova''',  and in English language|English] simply as Kosovo).  The province's final status has yet to be determined; talks on this issue are scheduled for later in [[2005]].

== Geography ==
With an area of [[1 E10 m2|10,887]] [[square kilometre|km&amp;sup2;]] and a population of almost 2 million on the eve of the 1999 crisis, Kosovo borders with [[Montenegro]] to the northwest, the rest of [[Serbia]] (often called &quot;[[Serbia proper]]&quot; in English) to the north and east, the [[Republic of Macedonia]] to the south, and [[Albania]] to the southwest. The largest cities are [[Prishtina|Pri&amp;#353;tina]], the capital, with estimated 500,000 inhabitants, and [[Prizren]] in the southwest with 120,000: five other towns have populations in excess of 50,000.

==Name==

The province is best known as '''Kosovo''' - this name has been the most widely used by maps abroad. The alternative spelling ''Kossovo'' was frequently used until the early [[20th century]] and before that, ''Cassovo'' or ''Cassua'', an [[Italian language|Italianisation]] of the name.

The name Kosovo [[Image:Kosov.png|center|thumb|431px|All places in the world whose names begin with &quot;Kosov&quot;]]

'''Kosova''' (pronounced &quot;ko-SO-vah&quot;) is the [[Albanian language|Albanian]] spelling for the province. Albanians tend to use &quot;Kosova&quot; exclusively in preference to the Serbian name, which many of them reject as a symbol of Serbian dominance. It is also occasionally spelled as ''Kosovë''; this is due to the fact that in Albanian, adding the definite article to a noun changes the ending of the word. 


The Albanian-populated areas of the province and Albania itself tend to use &quot;Kosova&quot; exclusively. &quot;Kosovo&quot; is used, again almost exclusively, in the Serb-populated north of the province and in the rest of the former [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]]. The international community tries to steer a middle path by referring formally to &quot;Kosovo/Kosova.&quot; In practice, however, the Serbian variant is still the most frequently used outside of Kosovo while the Albanian variant is widely used by &quot;internationals&quot; within the province.

The use of the two alternative names is a highly sensitive political issue for both Serbs and Kosovo Albanians, who regard the use of the other side's name as being a denial of their own side's territorial rights (in much the same way that [[Macedonian Slavs|Macedonians]] and [[Greece|Greeks]] have disputed the name of the [[Republic of Macedonia]]). During the [[Kosovo War]], [[United States]] President [[Bill Clinton]] was criticised for frequently using &quot;Kosova&quot; and appearing to pronounce &quot;Kosovo&quot; the Albanian way, putting the emphasis on the middle syllable rather than on the first syllable as in the Serbian pronunciation. This may, however, have been a simple mispronunciation.

''Rrafsh i Dukagjinit'', the &quot;Dukagjin plateau&quot;.

Some Kosovo Albanians refer to Kosovo as [[Dardania (Europe)|Dardania]], the name of the ancient Roman province which covered the territory of modern Kosovo and part of the Republic of Macedonia. Kosovo President [[Ibrahim Rugova]] has been an enthusiastic backer of a &quot;Dardanian&quot; identity and his flag and presidential seal refer to this notional identity. However, it is not recognised by any international power and the name &quot;Kosova&quot; remains more widely used among the Albanian population.


Kosovo was also called the ''&quot;Republic of Kosova&quot;'' by the shadow Kosovo Albanian government between a [[1990]] declaration of independence and the Kosovo War in 1999. Only Albania recognised the province's independence but neither Serbia nor the international community followed suit. The &quot;Republic of Kosova&quot; was effectively replaced by the current UN protectorate following the war.

The question of what to call the inhabitants of Kosovo collectively has also aroused some debate. They have been called variously &quot;Kosovars&quot;, &quot;Kosovans&quot; and &quot;Kosovians&quot;. The two words accepted by the [[Oxford English Dictionary]] are &quot;Kosovar&quot; (borrowed from Albanian), the most widely used variant in English, by a long way, and &quot;Kosovan&quot; (using the English rules for [[demonym]]s) much less used. &quot;Kosovian&quot; is considered a non-standard word and very little used at all.

As Kosovo has no formal statehood, current international usage is to refer to Kosovo Serbs and Kosovo Albanians. Most of the Albanian-descended community in Kosovo would prefer the use of Kosovar or Kosovan because of the attendant political overtones, whilst the Serb minority continue to think of themselves as Serb or Serbian (from Kosovo).

=== Kosovo placenames ===

Most localities in Kosovo have distinct Albanian placenames.

Since the United Nations took over administration of the province in June 1999].

==Flag==

The province never had an official flag of its own. The [[Flag of Albania|Albanian flag]] is used by the Albanian-dominated administration and the vast majority of Kosovo Albanians. Kosovo's president, Ibrahim Rugova, has proposed an alternative flag of &quot;Dardania&quot; based on the design of the Albanian flag, but even within Kosovo it is little used. == History ==

''See [[History of Kosovo]].''

== Politics and international status ==
{{Politics of Kosovo}}
Kosovo's international status is anomalous in that although it is formally a province of the Republic of Serbia, actual administration is presently conducted by the [[United Nations]] with no involvement on the part of the Serbian governments (under Security Council resolution 1244 of [[10 June]] [[1999]]; see [http://www.un.org/Docs/scres/1999/sc99.htm Security Council Resolutions 1999]).  The government of the province is the responsibility of the [[United Nations Mission in Kosovo]] (UNMIK). Under the terms of the [[Kumanovo agreement]] and subsequent UN [[Security Council]] [[Resolution 1244]], which ended the [[Kosovo War]], security is provided by the Kosovo Force (KFOR), which is led by [[NATO]] and is answerable to UNMIK.

UNMIK has so far established a provisional assembly, provisional government and the office of provisional president, which are legislative and executive bodies under UNMIK's control. Control of security, justice and external affairs are still under full UNMIK control. The [[Assembly of Kosovo]] was elected in November [[2001]] and [[Ibrahim Rugova]] was elected as president in March [[2002]]. The seat of the assembly, government and president is in [[Pristina]]. So far, the parliament has enacted and UNMIK approved a constitutional framework, customs code, and two criminal codes.

UNMIK is issuing travel documents which serve instead of [[passport]]s in countries which are accepting to recognise them as such; UNMIK is also issuing identity cards and car plates, which again are valid only in countries which are accepting them as such. Kosovo's postal system is also usable only in countries which are accepting to recognise it as such (letters addressed to Kosovo only, or to Serbia and Montenegro have a chance of not arriving; the Universal Postal Union advises correspondents to use &quot;Kosovo (UNMIK)&quot; as the address [http://www.upu.int/post_code/en/countries/KOS.pdf]).

UNMIK has also created a police force (the [[Kosovo Police Service]]) with employees from all ethnic communities (Albanian, Serbian, Roma, Bosniac, Roma, etc), and manages the province's railways and airline ([[Kosova Airlines]]). The airspace of the province is controlled by KFOR. UNMIK uses the United Nations flag.

The Constitutional Framework enacted by the Kosovo assembly (with UNMIK approval) has adopted a policy of [[affirmative action]] in the assembly to ensure that the province's minorities are properly represented. Out of 120 seats, 10 are reserved for Serbs and another 10 for non-Albanian minorities, while the remaining 100 seats are elected through direct voting.

Its final status has not yet been resolved, though talks on the subject are planned for later in 2005, and considerable difficulties lie ahead in reconciling the apparently incompatible positions of the Serbian and Albanian sides. The Albanians reject Serbian sovereignty; although the fall of the Milosevic government has eased some of the political tensions between the two administrations, most Kosovo Albanians do not believe that the Serbian side will respect Albanian rights. 

== Administrative subdivisions ==

Administrative subdivisions in Kosovo are known as komuna.

== Currency ==

[[UNMIK]] declared the [[euro]] to be official currency of the province in [[2001]] in the course of implementing a currency reform. This was undertaken to replace the previous widespread use of the [[Deutschmark]], which had become ''de facto'' currency even before the 1999 war. 

== Demographics ==
''Main article: [[Demographic history of Kosovo]]''

[[Albanians]] comprise an almost 90% majority of the population of the province. Their percentage as a proportion of the province's population has increased steadily over time as a result of a high birth rate, immigration from [[Albania]] and concentrion of Albanians from areas formerly under the Sandjak of Nish, southern Serbia. Most of the province's Albanian population became refugees during the war but quickly returned to their homes at its end. 

According to the 2000 Living Standard Measurement Survey of the Statistical Office of Kosovo[http://www.sok-kosovo.org/pdf/population/Kosovo_population.pdf], Kosovo's total population is approximately 1,970,000 with the following ethnic proportions:

* 88% Albanians (1,733,600) 
* 7% Serbs (137,900) 
* 1.9% Muslim Slavs (37,400) 
* 1.7% Roma (33,500) 
* 1% Turks (19,700)

==See also==

* [[Assembly of Kosovo]]
* [[Government of Kosovo]]
* [[Prime Minister of Kosovo]]
* [[President of Kosovo]]
* [[Battle of Kosovo|Battle of Kosovo (1389)]]   
* [[National awakening and the birth of Albania]]
* [[Unrest in Kosovo]] (about the March 2004 unrest)

==External links==

* [http://www.lib.utexas.edu/maps/kosovo.html Kosovo maps from the Perry-Castañeda Library Map Collection]
* [http://www.chmouel.com/geeklog/gallery/gallery_individual.php/mkosovo/ A collection of photos from Kosovo]
*[http://www.kosovo.com/sk/history/kosovo_origins/default.htm  Hugo Roth, ''Kosovo Origins'']: a historian's objective comprehensive overview

===Provisional Institutions of Self-Government===  
* [http://www.assembly-kosova.org/ Assembly of Kosovo]  
* [http://www.pm-ksgov.net/ Kosovo Prime Minister]

===Pro-Albanian===
* [http://www.albeu.com Albanian National Portal, latest news from kosovo, albania and macedonia.]
* [http://www.kosova.com Kosova Information Center (in Albanian)]
* [http://www.kosovapress.com Kosovapress - Kosovo news agency]
* [http://www.rtklive.com  Radio Television of Kosova (news in Albanian, Serbian and English)]
* [http://beqiraj.com/kosova/de/ General information from Beqiraj.com] (in German)
* [http://beqiraj.com/kosova/al/ General information from Beqiraj.com] (in Albanian)
* [http://www.albanian.com/main/countries/kosova General information from Albanian.com]
* [http://www.alb-net.com/warcrimes-img/warcrimes.htm Kosovo Crisis Center - Serbian Massacres of Albanians]
*[http://mysite.verizon.net/res93m93/ Albanianizm.tk - History, Pictures, Multimedia]</text>
