      <text xml:space="preserve">''The neutrality of this article is [[Wikipedia:NPOV dispute|disputed]]. Please see the article's [[Talk:Kosovo and Metohia|talk page]] for more information.'' 

[[de:Kosovo]]
[[et:Kosovo]]
[[nl:Kosovo]]

'''Kosovo and Metohia''' ([[Serbian language|Serbian]]: &amp;#1050;&amp;#1086;&amp;#1089;&amp;#1086;&amp;#1074;&amp;#1086; &amp;#1080; &amp;#1052;&amp;#1077;&amp;#1090;&amp;#1086;&amp;#1093;&amp;#1080;&amp;#1112;&amp;#1072;; [[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Kosova''), oftenly called just '''Kosovo''', is a province of [[Serbia]], which together with [[Montenegro]] constitute [[Serbia and Montenegro]]. The name &quot;Kosovo&quot; is from &quot;Kosovo Polje&quot; which means &quot;[[Blackbird]]'s field&quot; in [[Serbian language]].  &quot;Metohia&quot; is a [[Greek language|Greek]] word which denotes [[church]]-owned land.

== History ==

The early history of Kosovo is disputed amongst historians, according to Serb historians, Kosovo was entered by Serbs migrating from the north-east around the early [[7th century]] AD, Kosovo was a centre of the medieval Serbian kingdom until its conquest by the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman Turks]] in the late [[14th century]]. 

According to Serb historians, the existing Albanian population is mostly formed by migrants from the south-west (modern [[Albania]]) during the centuries of Ottoman rule (particularly during and after the [[17th century]]), when Islam also became the faith of most of the Albanian people.

However, Albanians claim that they are Kosovo's original inhabitants, being the descendants of the ancient [[Illyrian]]s. According to Albanian historians, in around the [[6th century]] the Illyrians were forced south into what is now Albania by [[Slav]]ic tribes - the predecessors of modern day Serbs. 

Kosovo was for centuries ruled by the [[Ottoman Empire]]. From the [[1870s]] onwards Albanians formed the [[League of Prizren]] to resist Ottoman rule, and a provisional government was formed in [[1881]]. In [[1912]] Kosovo was briefly included in the newly independent state of [[Albania]]. But the following year the Great Powers (Britain, America, France etc) forced Albania to cede the region to [[Serbia]] as at that time about 60% of the population was Serb (see [[Kosovo population data-points]]). In [[1918]], Kosovo became a part of the newly formed [[Yugoslavia]].

Between 1941 and 1945, Kosovo was included under the Italian-occupied [[Greater Albania]]. Following the end of the war and the establishment of [[Tito]]'s [[Communist]] regime, Kosovo was given the status of an autonomous region of Serbia in [[1946]] and an autonomous province in [[1963]].

In [[1974]], new constitution of Yugoslavia was passed, under which Kosovo enjoyed almost complete self-government under predominantly Albanian local communist party leaders. For example, schools had the same curriculum and textbooks as in Albania under [[Enver Hoxha]], even after they were dropped from Albania's school system. 

Throughout the [[1980s]] tensions between the Albanian and serb communities in the province escalated. The Albanian community favoured sovreignty for Kosovo, whilst Serbs favoured closer ties with the rest of Serbia.

Serbs living in Kosovo were discriminated by Albanians. In August [[1987]], during the dying days of Yugoslavia's communist regime. Kosovo was visited by [[Slobodan Milosevic]], then a rising politician. He appealed to Serb nationalism to further his career. Having drawn huge crowds, he pledged to Kosovo Serbs that &quot;No one should dare to beat you&quot;, and became an instant hero of Kosovo's Serbs. By the end of the year Milosovic was in control of the Serbian government.

In [[1989]], the autonomy was revoked by a Serbia wide referendum which implemented a new Serbian constitution which was claimed to be more democratic as it allowed [[multi-party system]], introduced factual [[freedom of speech]] and respect of [[human rights]]. 

It also took away the provinces' rights, which was felt to be a democratic step by Serbs. However, the constitution was strongly opposed by Kosovo Albanians because it stripped Kosovo of its autonomous status. Albanians refused to participate in the referendum. Because it was a republic wide referendum and they were a minority in Serbia as a whole, their participation would not have changed the outcome of the referendum.

However the new constitution had to be ratified by Kosovo's assembly [http://www.wcl.american.edu/hrbrief/06/2kosovo.cfm]. In March [[1989]] when the assembly met to discuss the proposals, tanks and armored cars surrounded the meeting place, forcing the assembly to accept the amendments. The constitutional changes effectively stripped Kosovo of autonomy, and handed control of the police, the court system, the economy, the education system and language policies to the Serb government.

The new constitution took away the right of having official media from provinces and official media were integrated within official media of Serbia. Albanian language media in Kosovo was surpressed. Funding was withdrawn from Albanian language media in Kosovo, and although private media was theoretically allowed, deliberately high rents and laws making distribution difficult, made its functioning almost impossible. Albanian laguage television or radio was also banned from broadcasting from Kosovo [http://www.hrw.org/worldreport/Helsinki-12.htm].

The constitution also gave control over state-owned companies (at the time, most of the companies were state-owned and ''[[de jure]]'' they still are) to Serbian government. In September [[1990]] Up to 123,000 Albanian workers were fired from their positions in government and the media, as were teachers, doctors, and workers in government-controlled industries [http://www.bndlg.de/~wplarre/back337.htm], provoking a [[general strike]] and mass unrest.

Albanian language education was also curtailed [http://www.osce.org/kosovo/documents/reports/hr/part1/ch1.htm]. Following the removal of Kosovo's autonomy, the Serb government moved to standardise the curriculum across Serbia. Albanian language education was ended in schools (although it was re-established for primary schools in 1994), and was also cut at Pristina University. Albanian teachers were also sacked en-masse. Albanians responded by boycotting state schools and attempts to maintain a &quot;parallel&quot; system of Albanian-language education.

Kosovo Albanians were outraged by these developments and in February [[1990]], following mass rioting and unrest from Albanians, a state of emergency was declared, and presence of the Yugoslav Army and police was drastically increased to quell the unrest.

Unsanctioned elections held in [[1992]], overwhelmingly elected [[Ibrahim Rugova]] as &quot;president&quot;, however these elections were not recognised neither by Serbian nor any foreign government. In [[1995]], thousands of Serb refugees from [[Croatia]] settled in Kosovo, which further worsened relations between the two communities. 

Albanian opposition to sovereignty of Yugoslavia and especially Serbia, which had surfaced in rioting (1968 and March 1981) in the capital [[Prishtina|Pri&amp;#353;tina]]. Ibrahim Rugova advocated non-violent resistance, but later when it became apparent that this was not working, opposition took the form of separatist agitation by opposition political groups and armed action from 1996 by the &quot;[[Kosovo Liberation Army]]&quot; (''Ushtria Çlirimtare e Kosovës'', or UÇK). The Serbian police and UÇK actions by 1998 created a state of low intensity warfare with some 2000 dying prior to [[Kosovo War]] of [[1999]].

The KLA repeatedly attacked Serbian police. In March 1998 Yugoslav army units joined Serbian police to fight the KLA separatists. In the months that followed, hundreds of people were killed and more than 200,000 have fled from their homes, most of these people were Albanians. The international media reported Albanian families being forced to flee their homes at gunpoint.

The [[United Nations]] estimated that during the Kosovo War, nearly 640,000 Albanians fled Kosovo between March 1998 and the end of April 1999. Most of the refugees went to [[Albania]], the [[Former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia]], or [[Montenegro]]. Most [[west]]ern media have reported that at some border crossings, some identification papers of some Albanian families were destroyed by Serbian officials.

[[Slobodan Milosevic]] and other senior Serb officials were indicted by the United Nations for [[war crime]]s committed by Serb forces in Kosovo. There were no indictments of [[NATO]] and [[KLA]] officials.

== Politics and international status ==
Its international status is anomalous in that although it is formally a province of the Republic of [[Serbia]], actual administration is presently conducted by the [[United Nations]] with no involvement on the part of the Serbian governments (under Security Council resolution 1244 of [[10 June]] [[1999]]; see [http://www.un.org/Docs/scres/1999/sc99.htm Security Council Resolutions 1999]). A [[parliament]] was elected in November [[2001]] and [[Ibrahim Rugova]] was selected as president in March [[2002]], however the UN retained control of security, justice and external affairs.

Kosovo's anomalous status is the result of the [[Kosovo War]] of March-June [[1999]], in the course of which air strikes against the Federal republic of [[Yugoslavia]]'s armed forces and civilian infrastructure by members of the [[North Atlantic Treaty Organization]], without endorsement by the [[United Nations]], forced the signing of the [[Kumanovo agreement]] which provided for the withdrawal of military and the province's occupation by a NATO-led international force (KFOR) including also [[Russia]]n troops (no longer serving as of July [[2003]]).
 
Since 1998, Yugoslav forces were heavily fighting with the KLA, during which, according to NATO intentionally, a number of Albanian civilians was killed, wounded or temporarily driven out of province, and NATO claims that it began air strikes in order to stop that.

Both [[NATO]] and the [[United Nations|UN]] continue formally to recognise Kosovo as a part of Serbia although Serbia is not allowed to exercise any sovereignty over it, as since 1999 much of the Serb population have departed and local Albanians are reluctant to see Serbian sovereignty in Kosovo restored in practice. On the other side, Serbia would hardly recognize Kosovo's independence, and recognizing the independence of Kosovo without Serbia's consent would violate [[international law]] (the principles of [[territorial integrity]] and [[noninterference in internal affairs]]). The most likely outcome is the indefinite continuation of the current situation.

== Administrative subdivisions ==

== Geography ==
&lt;div style=&quot;float:right; margin-left:1em;
text-align:center;&quot;&gt;[[Image:UTkosovo rel smaller 92.jpg|Map of Kosovo]]&lt;br&gt;[[Media:UTkosovo rel small 92.jpg|Larger version]]&lt;/div&gt;
With an area of [[1 E10 m2|10,887]] [[square kilometre|km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;]] and a population of almost 2 million on the eve of the 1999 crisis, Kosovo borders with [[Montenegro]] to the northwest, rest of [[Serbia]] to the north and east, the [[Former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia]] to the south and [[Albania]] to the southwest. The largest cities are [[Prishtina|Pri&amp;#353;tina]], the capital, with 190,000 inhabitants, and [[Prizren]] in the southwest with 120,000: five other towns have populations in excess of 50,000.

== Economy ==
[[UNMIK]] declared the [[Euro]] as the official currency in Kosovo, however the [[Serbian dinar]] remains an official currency in Kosovo. The Dinar is widespread in Kosovo because most trade is done with the rest of Serbia and the [[Kosovo Serb enclaves]] also use it widely. Other international currencies ([[Dollar]], [[Swiss Franc]]) are also widespread.
== Demographics ==
The population is currently comprised of a majority of [[Albanian]]s (estimated at 80% prior to the international conflict of [[1999]], but now somewhat larger owing to the flight of many [[Serbs]] and other non-Albanians; see [[Kosovo population data-points]]).

== Culture ==

== Miscellaneous topics ==

==See also==
* [[Battle of Kosovo]]   
* [[National awakening and the birth of Albania]] 

==External links==
* [http://www.rastko.org.yu/kosovo/crucified/default.htm Account of destroyed Serbian Orthodox churches in Kosovo and Metohia]
* [http://www.albanian.com/main/countries/kosova General information from Albanian.com]
* [http://beqiraj.com/kosova/al/ General information from Beqiraj.com] (in Albanian)
* [http://www.alb-net.com/warcrimes-img/warcrimes.htm Kosovo Crisis Center - Serbian Massacres of Albanians]
* [http://www.kosova.com Kosova Information Center (in Albanian)]
* [http://www.kosovapress.com Kosovo Press - Kosova news agency]
* [http://www.lib.utexas.edu/maps/kosovo.html Kosovo maps from the Perry-Castañeda Library Map Collection]
* [http://www.b92.net/english/news/index.php?order=priority&amp;nav_category=19 News from B92 Belgrade]
* [http://www.serbia.sr.gov.yu/news/kosovo News from the Serbian Government]
* [http://www.kosovo.com/default4.html News from the Serbian Orthodox Church] 
* [http://www.serbia.sr.gov.yu/coordination_centre/index.html Serb Kosovo Coordination Center]
* [http://www.chmouel.com/geeklog/gallery/gallery_individual.php/mkosovo/ Kosovo collection of pictures around the country]

&lt;hr align=&quot;center&quot; noshade size=&quot;4&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;

'''[[Yugoslavia|Former 6 republics and 2 autonomous provinces of Yugoslavia]]:''' &lt;br&gt;
''[[Bosnia and Herzegovina]]'' ''Bosna i Hercegovina'' &amp;nbsp;|&amp;nbsp; ''[[Croatia]]'' ''Hrvatska'' &amp;nbsp;|&amp;nbsp; ''[[Montenegro]]'' ''Crna gora'' &amp;nbsp;|&amp;nbsp; ''[[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]]'' ''Makedonija'' &amp;nbsp;|&amp;nbsp; ''[[Serbia]]'' ''Srbija'' (''Kosovo'', ''[[Vojvodina]]'') &amp;nbsp;|&amp;nbsp; ''[[Slovenia]]'' ''Slovenija''</text>
