      <text xml:space="preserve">{{otheruses}} {{seealso|Names of Kosovo}}
{{Infobox Kosovo}}&lt;!--

Please be very careful in editing the introduction of this article. The Arbitration Committee has placed this article on probation. If any editor makes disruptive edits, they may be banned by an administrator from this and related articles, or other reasonably related pages. See the talk page for more information.

--&gt;
'''Kosovo''' &lt;!--Please leave the following language order as Albanian [Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Kosova'' or ''Kosovë'') is a country which has been under [[United Nations]] [[United Nations Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo|administration]] since [[1999]]. From 2007 it has become an independent country. The province is governed by the [[United Nations Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo]] (UNMIK) with the help of the local [[Provisional Institutions of Self-Government]] (PISG), as well as security provided by the [[NATO]]-led [[Kosovo Force]] (KFOR). 

The Province of Kosovo borders [[Montenegro]], [[Albania]], and the [[Republic of Macedonia]]. It has a population of just over two million people, predominantly ethnic [[Albanians]], smaller groups of [[Turkish people|Turks]], [[Bosnian people]], [[Romanian people]], and other ethnic groups. [[Pristina]] is the capital and largest city. 

== Geography ==
{{main|Geography of Kosovo}}

[[Image:UTkosovo rel small 92.jpg|thumb|left|Physical map of Kosovo.]]
[[Image:Kosovo map.png|thumb|left|Political map of Kosovo.]]

With an area of 10,887 [[square kilometers]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kosovo-mining.org/kosovoweb/en/home.html Welcome to the Independent Commission for Mines and Minerals (ICMM), Kosovo]&lt;/ref&gt; (4,203 [[square mile|sq&amp;nbsp;mi]]) and a population of nearly two million, Kosovo internationally borders [[Montenegro]] to the northwest, the [[Republic of Macedonia]] to the south, and [[Albania]] to the south west, while internally [[Central Serbia]] to the north and east. The province's present borders were established in [[1953]]. The [[Republic of Serbia]] has one other autonomous province, [[Vojvodina]], located in the north of the country. 

The largest cities are [[Priština]], the capital, with an estimated 600,000 inhabitants, [[Prizren]] in the south west with a population of 165,000, [[peja]] in the west with 154,000, and [[Kosovo Mitrovica]] in the north. Five other towns have populations in excess of 97,000. 

The climate in Kosovo is continental, with warm summers and cold and snowy winters.

There are two main plains in Kosovo. The [[Metohija]] basin is located in the western part of the province, and the Plain of Kosovo occupies the eastern part.

Much of Kosovo's terrain is rugged. The [[Šar Mountain]]s are located in the south and south-east, bordering [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]]. This is one of the region's most popular tourist and skiing resorts, bordering Albania and Montenegro. 

The mountain range dividing Kosovo from Albania is known in English as the [[Prokletije|&quot;Cursed Mountains&quot;]] or as the [[Dinaric Alps]]. The [[Kopaonik]] mountain is located in the north, bordering [[Central Serbia]]. The central region of [[Drenica]], Crnoljevo and the eastern part of Kosovo, known as [[Goljak]], are mainly hilly areas. 

There are several notable rivers and lakes in Kosovo. The main rivers are the [[White Drin]], running towards the [[Adriatic Sea]], with the [[Erenik]] among its [[Tributary|tributaries]]), the [[Sitnica]], the [[South Morava]] in the Goljak area, and [[Ibar River|Ibar]] in the north. The main lakes are Gazivoda (380 million m³) in the north-western part, Radonjić (113 million m³) in the south-west part, Batlava (40 million m³) and Badovac (26 million m³) in the north-east part.

== History ==
{{main|History of Kosovo}}
{{see also|Demographic history of Kosovo}}

The last disputed region of the now defunct communist Yugoslavia, the province of Kosovo has an extensive and rich history. Inhabited by several different groups, it was initially (circa 1300 B.C.E.) inhabited by [[Illyrians]], which eventually became incorporated into the Roman empire and subsequently the Byzantine empire. From c. 6th century AD it was settled by several [[Slavs|Slavic groups]], including Serbs, migrating from the north. It was conquered by the Ottoman empire during their take-over of south-eastern Europe. However, it was regained by the Serbs after the defeat of the Ottoman Empire in the 1912-13 [[Balkan Wars]].  Kosovo has since been a region or province of modern Yugoslavia and its successor state of Serbia.

=== Kosovo in the Middle-Ages ===
{{see also|History of Medieval Kosovo}}
[[Image:Serbia boundaries CIA.jpg|thumb|righ|230px|Map: ''&quot;Kosovo: History of a Balkan Hot Spot&quot;'', 1998]]


KOSOVA IS THE BEST</text>
