      <text xml:space="preserve">{{pp-dispute|expiry=8 March 2008}}

&lt;!-- {{split|Kosovo (region)|Republic of Kosovo}} This tag is quite out of place as split is supported only by a limited number of editors who are persuing an endless debate on this matter. --&gt;
{{pp-semi-protected|small=yes}}
&lt;!--

Please be very careful in editing the introduction of this article. The Arbitration Committee has placed this article on probation. While this occurred in 2006, it was never lifted; thus, this page is still under probation. If any editor makes disruptive edits, they may be banned by an administrator from this and related articles, or other reasonably related pages. See the talk page for more information.

Please also note that the current delicate (and controversial) political situation of Kosovo makes the terms of article probation all the more important. DO NOT ENGAGE IN EDIT-WARRING ON THIS ARTICLE or any related articles. Edit-warring on this article will result in immediate blocking and application of additional sanctions under the terms of probation as administrators and/or the community deem appropriate. Thank you.

--&gt;
{{other uses|Kosovo (disambiguation)}}
{{redirect|Kosova||Kosova (disambiguation)}}
{{NPOV}}
{{Infobox Country
|native_name = {{nowrap|{{lang|sq|'''Republika e Kosovës'''}}&lt;br&gt;{{lang|sr-Cyrl|Република Косово}} / {{lang|sr-Latn|''Republika Kosovo''}}}}
|conventional_long_name   = Kosovo
|common_name              = Kosovo
|image_flag               = Flag of Kosovo.svg
|image_coat               = Coat_of_arms_of_Kosovo.svg&lt;!-- Avoid changing this,it has a reliable source: http://www.kosovapress.com/ks/repository/images/stema_kosoves_thmb.jpg --&gt;
|image_map                = Europe location KOS.png
|map_caption              = Location of Kosovo in [[Europe]]

|national_motto           = 
|national_anthem          =  &lt;!-- ''[[European anthem|Ode to Joy]]''{{Fact|date=February 2008}} --&gt;&lt;!-- I have hidden this, as it has no source. Please only restore this when there's a reliable source confirming that this is the anthem of Kosovo. --&gt;
|official_languages       = [[Albanian language|Albanian]], [[Serbian language|Serbian]]
|regional_languages       = [[Turkish language|Turkish]], [[Našinski|Gorani]], [[Romani language|Romani]], [[Bosnian language|Bosnian]]
|ethnic_groups            = 92% [[Albanians]]&lt;br/&gt;{{spaces|2}}5.3% [[Serbs]]&lt;br/&gt;{{spaces|2}}2.7% others &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ks-gov.net/ESK/esk/english/english.htm Enti i Statistikës së Kosovës]&lt;/ref&gt;
|ethnic_groups_year       = 2007
|capital                  = {{nowrap|[[Pristina]]}}&lt;!--

PLEASE DO NOT CHANGE THE CAPITAL'S NAME! Per talkpage, we currently use Pristina, not Prishtina or Priština.

--&gt;
|latd=42 |latm=40 |latNS=N |longd=21 |longm=10 |longEW=E
|largest_city             = capital
|demonym                  = [[Demographics of Kosovo|Kosovar]]
|government_type          = [[UNMIK|international protectorate]]
|leader_title1            = Special Representative of the Secretary-General
|leader_name1             = [[Joachim Rücker]]
|leader_title2            = [[President of Kosovo|President]]
|leader_name2             = [[Fatmir Sejdiu]] ([[Democratic League of Kosovo|LDK]])
|leader_title3            = [[Prime Minister of Kosovo|Prime Minister]]
|leader_name3             = [[Hashim Thaçi]] ([[Democratic Party of Kosovo|PDK]])
|sovereignty_type         = [[Independence]]{{smallsup|1}}
|sovereignty_note         = from [[Serbia]]
|established_event1       = [[2008 Kosovo declaration of independence|Declared]]
|established_date1        = [[17 February]] [[2008]]
|established_event2       = [[International reaction to the 2008 Kosovo declaration of independence|Recognized]]
|established_date2        = by 27 countries &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=[[United States Secretary of State|US Secretary of State]] [[Condoleezza Rice]]|title=U.S. Recognizes Kosovo as Independent State|publisher=[[U.S. Department of State]]|url=http://www.state.gov/secretary/rm/2008/02/100973.htm|date=[[2008-02-18]]|accessdate=2008-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Britain, France recognise Kosovo|publisher=[[Associated Press]]|url=http://ap.google.com/article/ALeqM5jvieojQfAH0lC-MNOQEfGdVlX1XAD8USR0K01|date=[[2008-02-18]]|accessdate=2008-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes u.s. france&quot;&gt;{{cite news|first=Stephen|last=Castle|title=Kosovo is Recognised by U.S., France and Britain|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/02/19/world/europe/19kosovo.html?ref=world|date=[[2008-02-18]]|accessdate=2008-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|area_rank                = 166
|area_magnitude           = 1 E10
|area_km2                 = 10,887
|area_sq_mi               = 4,203
|percent_water            = n/a
|population_estimate      = 1,900,000&lt;ref&gt;See: [http://enrin.grida.no/htmls/kosovo/SoE/popullat.htm UN estimate], Kosovo’s population estimates range from 1.9 to 2.4 million. The last two population census conducted in 1981 and 1991 estimated Kosovo’s population at 1.6 and 1.9 million respectively, but the 1991 census probably undercounted Albanians. The latest estimate in 2001 by OSCE puts the number at 2.4 Million. The World Factbook gives an estimate of 2,126,708 for the year 2007 (see {{CIA_World_Factbook_link|kv|Kosovo}}).&lt;/ref&gt;
|population_estimate_rank = 141
|population_estimate_year = 2007
|population_census        = 1,956,196{{smallsup|2}}
|population_census_year   = 1991
|population_density_km2   = 220
|population_density_sq_mi = 500
|population_density_rank  = 55
|currency                 = [[Euro]] (€){{smallsup|3}}
|currency_code            = EUR
|time_zone                = [[Central European Time|CET]]
|utc_offset               = +1
|time_zone_DST            = [[Central European Summer Time|CEST]]
|utc_offset_DST           = +2
|cctld                    =  ''None assigned''
|calling_code             = 381{{smallsup|4}}
|footnote1                = [[International reaction to the 2008 Kosovo declaration of independence|Independence has only been partially recognised internationally.]]
|footnote2                = The census is a reconstruction; most of the ethnic Albanian majority boycotted.
|footnote3                = Unilaterally adopted. Kosovo is not a member of the [[European Monetary Union|EMU]].
|footnote4                = Officially; some mobile phone providers use [[Monaco|+377]] or [[Slovenia|+386]] instead.
}}

'''Kosovo''' ({{lang-sq|Kosova}} or ''Kosovë'', {{lang-sr|Косово}}, ''Kosovo'', ''see'': [[Names of Kosovo]]), is a region in the [[Balkans]], presently under the ''[[ad interim]]'' control of the [[United Nations Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo]] and protection of the [[North Atlantic Treaty Organization]]'s [[Kosovo Force]]. Its [[Provisional Institutions of Self-Government]] have recently [[2008 Kosovo declaration of independence|declared independence]] from the [[Republic of Serbia]], which contested the act; as the '''Republic of Kosovo''', it has received [[International reaction to the 2008 Kosovo declaration of independence|partial recognition]].

Kosovo has a population of about two million people, predominantly ethnic [[Albanians]], with smaller populations of [[Serbs]], [[Romani people]], [[Gorani (ethnic group)|Gorani]]s, [[Bosniaks]], [[Turkish people|Turks]] and other ethnic communities. [[Pristina]] is the capital and largest city. Kosovo is [[landlocked]], bordering [[Montenegro]] to the west, [[Albania]] to the southwest, the [[Republic of Macedonia]] to the south and [[Central Serbia]] to the north and east.

Following the [[Kosovo War]] in 1999, [[United Nations]] [[United Nations Security Council|Security Council]] [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 1244|Resolution 1244]] placed Kosovo under the authority of the UNMIK, with security provided by the [[NATO]]-led [[Kosovo Force]] (KFOR), and legally reaffirmed Serbia's [[sovereignty]] over the region and committed the UN Member States to its territorial integrity. After [[Kosovo status process|UN-sponsored negotiations]] failed to reach a consensus on an acceptable [[constitutional status of Kosovo|constitutional status]], [[Provisional Institutions of Self-Government|Kosovo's provisional government]] unilaterally [[declaration of independence|declared independence]] from [[Serbia]] on [[17 February]] [[2008]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/7249034.stm BBC News:  Kosovo MPs proclaim independence - February 17, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt; and received [[International reaction to the 2008 Kosovo declaration of independence#States that formally recognise the independent Republic of Kosovo|partial international recognition]] as a [[sovereign state]] (notably from the [[United States]], the [[United Kingdom]], [[France]], [[Germany]], [[Albania]], [[Italy]], and [[Turkey]]). As of March 5th, 2008, 27 states [[International reaction to the 2008 Kosovo declaration of independence#States that formally recognise the independent Republic of Kosovo|formally recognise]] the Republic of Kosovo while at least another 3 have  [[International_reaction_to_the_2008_Kosovo_declaration_of_independence#UN_member_states_about_to_recognise_the_independent_Republic_of_Kosovo|declared their intention to do so]] at a later date.&lt;!-- Removed {{Fact|date=February 2008}}, as references given on linked [[International_reaction_to_the_2008_Kosovo_declaration_of_independence]] article --&gt;

Kosovo's unilateral declaration of independence is disputed by [[Serbia]], [[Russia]], [[Spain]] and 18 other nations. The official position of these countries is that Kosovo is a Serbian province under ad interim  [[UN]] control.Other countries, including the [[People's Republic of China]], have called for further negotiations or have stated they have made no decision yet.



== Geography ==
{{main|Geography of Kosovo}}
[[Image:Kosovo map-en.svg|thumb|Physical map of Kosovo]]
Kosovo has an area of 10,887 [[square kilometers]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.kosovo-mining.org/kosovoweb/en/home.html |title=Welcome to the Independent Commission for Mines and Minerals (ICMM), Kosovo |author=Independent Commission for Mines and Minerals}}&lt;/ref&gt; (4,203 [[square mile|sq&amp;nbsp;mi]]) and a population of about 2.2 million. The largest cities are [[Prishtina]], the capital, with an estimated 170,000 inhabitants, [[Prizren]] in the south west with a population of 110,000, [[Peja]] in the west with 70,000, and [[Mitrovica]] in the north with 70,000.

The climate in Kosovo is continental, with warm summers and cold and snowy winters. There are two main plains in Kosovo. The [[Dukagjini]] basin is located in the western part of the Kosovo, and the Plain of Kosovo occupies the eastern part.

Much of Kosovo's terrain is mountainous. The [[Shar Mountains]] are located in the south and south-east, bordering the [[Republic of Macedonia]]. This is one of the region's most popular tourist and skiing resorts, with [[Brezovica]] and Prevallac as the main tourist centers. Kosovo's mountainous area, including the highest peak [[Gjeravica]], at 2656&amp;nbsp;m above sea level, is located in the south-west, bordering Montenegro and Albania. 

The [[Kopaonik]] mountains are located in the north. The central region of [[Drenica]], [[Caraleva]] and the eastern part of Kosovo, known as [[Gollak]], are mainly hilly areas. There are several notable rivers and lakes in Kosovo. The main rivers are the [[White Drin]], running towards the [[Adriatic Sea]], with the [[Erenik]] among its [[Tributary|tributaries]]), the [[Sitnica]], the [[South Morava]] in the Gollak area, and [[IbriRiver|Ibri]] in the north. The main lakes are Gazivoda (380 million m³) in the north-western part, Radoniqi (113 million m³) in the south-west part, Batllava (40 million m³) and Badovci (26 million m³) in the north-east part.

[[Image:Prishtina maj 2005.jpg|thumb|[[Prishtina]]]]
[[Image:Pallati i Rinisë.jpg|thumb|Prishtina]]
List of largest cities in Kosovo (with population figures for [[2003-12-31]]):&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.citypopulation.de/Kosovo.html |title=Kosovo |author=City Population}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Prishtina]] (Priština): 165,844
*[[Prizren]] : 107,614
*[[Ferizaj]] (Uroševac) : 71,758
*[[Mitrovica]] : 68,929
*[[Gjakova]] (Đakovica) : 68,645
*[[Peja]] (Peč) : 68,551
*[[Gjilan]] (Gnjilane): 55,781
*[[Vushtrri]] (Vučitrn) : 39,642
*[[Podujevë]] : 37,203

==Politics and governance==
{{main|Politics of Kosovo}}
{{seealso|United Nations Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo|Provisional Institutions of Self-Government}}
{{Politics of Kosovo}}
In 1999, [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 1244|UN Security Council Resolution 1244]] placed Kosovo under transitional UN administration pending a determination of Kosovo's future status. This Resolution entrusted the [[United Nations Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo]] (UNMIK) with sweeping powers to govern Kosovo, but also directed UNMIK to establish interim institutions of self-governance. Resolution 1244 permits Serbia no role in governing Kosovo and since 1999 Serbian laws and institutions have not been valid in Kosovo. NATO has a separate mandate to provide for a safe and secure environment.

In May 2001, UNMIK promulgated the Constitutional Framework, which established Kosovo's [[Provisional Institutions of Self-Government]] (PISG). The PISG replaced the [[Joint Interim Administrative Structure]] (JIAS) established a year earlier. Since 2001, UNMIK has been gradually transferring increased governing competencies to the PISG, while reserving some powers that are normally carried out by sovereign states, such as foreign affairs. Kosovo has also established municipal government and an internationally-supervised Kosovo Police Service.

According to the Constitutional Framework, Kosovo shall have a 120-member Kosovo Assembly. The Assembly includes twenty reserved seats: ten for Kosovo Serbs and ten for non-Serb minorities (Bosniaks, Roma, etc). The Kosovo Assembly is responsible for electing a President and Prime Minister of Kosovo.

The largest political party in Kosovo, the Democratic League of Kosovo (LDK), has its origins in the 1990s non-violent resistance movement to Miloševic's rule. The party was led by Ibrahim Rugova until his death in 2006. The two next largest parties have their roots in the Kosovo Liberation Army (KLA): the Democratic Party of Kosovo (PDK) led by former KLA leader Hashim Thaci and the Alliance for the Future of Kosovo (AAK) led by former KLA commander Ramush Haradinaj. Kosovo publisher Veton Surroi formed his own political party in 2004 named &quot;Ora.&quot; Kosovo Serbs formed the Serb List for Kosovo and Metohija (SLKM) in 2004, but have boycotted Kosovo's institutions and never taken their seats in the Kosovo Assembly.

In November 2001, the [[OSCE]] supervised the first elections for the Kosovo Assembly. After that election, Kosovo's political parties formed an all-party unity coalition and elected [[Ibrahim Rugova]] as President and Bajram Rexhepi (PDK) as Prime Minister.

After Kosovo-wide elections in October 2004, the LDK and AAK formed a new governing coalition that did not include PDK and Ora. This coalition agreement resulted in [[Ramush Haradinaj]] (AAK) becoming Prime Minister, while Ibrahim Rugova retained the position of President. PDK and Ora were critical of the coalition agreement and have since frequently accused the current government of corruption.

[[Image:Coat of arms of the PISG of Kosovo.svg|thumb|100px|left|The [[Approved logo of the Provisional Institutions of Self-Government|Approved Logo]] of the [[Provisional Institutions of Self-Government]]]]
Ramush Haradinaj resigned the post of Prime Minister after he was indicted for war crimes by the International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia (ICTY) in March 2005. He was replaced by Bajram Kosumi (AAK). But in a political shake-up after the death of President Rugova in January 2006, Kosumi himself was replaced by former Kosovo Protection Corps commander [[Agim Ceku]]. Ceku has won recognition for his outreach to minorities, but Serbia has been critical of his wartime past as military leader of the KLA and claims he is still not doing enough for Kosovo Serbs. The Kosovo Assembly elected [[Fatmir Sejdiu]], a former LDK parliamentarian, president after Rugova's death. Slaviša Petkovic, Minister for Communities and Returns, was previously the only ethnic Serb in the government, but resigned in November 2006 amid allegations that he misused ministry funds.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.adnki.com/index_2Level_English.php?cat=Politics&amp;loid=8.0.363650179&amp;par=0 Kosovo: Serb minister resigns over misuse of funds] &quot;, Adnkronos international (AKI), November 27, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.reliefweb.int/rw/RWB.NSF/db900SID/LZEG-6VUQUS?OpenDocument Sole Kosovo Serb cabinet minister resigns: PM] &quot;, Agence France-Presse (AFP), November 24, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Today two of the total thirteen ministries in Kosovo's Government have ministers from the minorities. Branislav Grbic, ethnic Serb, leads Minister of Returns and Sadik Idriz, ethnic Bosnjak, leads Ministry of Health&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ks-gov.net/pm/?menuid=2&amp;subid=20&amp;subs=56&amp;lingo=1 Fillimi&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Kosovan parliamentary election, 2007|Parliamentary elections]] were held on [[17 November]] [[2007]]. After early results, [[Hashim Thaçi]] who was on course to gain 35 per cent of the vote, claimed victory for PDK, the [[Democratic Party of Kosovo|Albanian Democratic Party]], and stated his intention to declare independence. Thaci is likely to form a coalition with current [[Fatmir Sejdiu|President Fatmir Sejdiu]]'s [[Democratic League of Kosovo|Democratic League]] which was in second place with 22 percent of the vote. The turnout at the election was particularly low with most Serbs refusing to vote.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.euronews.net/index.php?page=info&amp;article=454473&amp;lng=1 EuroNews: Ex-guerrilla chief claims victory in Kosovo election]. Retrieved 18 November 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Health ==

Access to health care is free for all residents of Kosovo. Currently there is no health insurance, however, the Ministry of Health is in the process of preparing a legislative infrastructure, which is scheduled to be implemented in 2008.

There are hospitals in all major cities. A total of 6 regional hospitals provide tertiary health care, and family centers in small municipalities.

Medical Education is available at the University Clinical Center of Kosovo (UCCK), in Prishtina.

== Economy ==
{{main|Economy of Kosovo}}
Kosovo has one of the most under-developed economies in Europe, with a per capita income estimated at [[Euro|€]]1,565 (2004).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://web.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/COUNTRIES/ECAEXT/KOSOVOEXTN/0,,contentMDK:20629286~menuPK:297777~pagePK:1497618~piPK:217854~theSitePK:297770,00.html |title=Kosovo Brief 2006 |author=The World Bank |date=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite substantial development subsidies from all Yugoslav republics, Kosovo was the poorest province of Yugoslavia.&lt;ref&gt;Christian Science Monitor 1982-01-15, &quot;Why Turbulent Kosovo has Marble Sidewalks but Troubled Industries&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, over the course of the 1990s a blend of poor economic policies, international sanctions, poor external commerce and ethnic conflict severely damaged the economy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://web.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/COUNTRIES/ECAEXT/KOSOVOEXTN/0,,menuPK:297775~pagePK:141159~piPK:141110~theSitePK:297770,00.html |title=World Bank Mission in Kosovo |author=The World Bank |date=2006/2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kosovo's economy remains weak. After a jump in 2000 and 2001, growth in [[Gross Domestic Product]] (GDP) was negative in 2002 and 2003 and is expected to be around 3 percent 2004-2005, with domestic sources of growth unable to compensate for the declining foreign assistance. [[Inflation]] is low, while the budget posted a deficit for the first time in 2004. Kosovo has high external deficits. In 2004, the deficit of the balance of goods and services was close to 70 percent of GDP. Remittances from Kosovars living abroad accounts for an estimated 13 percent of GDP, and foreign assistance for around 34 percent of GDP.

Most economic development since 1999 has taken place in the trade, retail and the construction sectors. The private sector that has emerged since 1999 is mainly small-scale. The industrial sector remains weak and the electric power supply remains unreliable, acting as a key constraint. Unemployment remains pervasive, at around 40-50% of the labor force.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.eciks.org/english/lajme.php?action=total_news&amp;main_id=386 |title=May finds Kosovo with 50% unemployed |author=eciks |date=04/05/06}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

UNMIK introduced ''de-facto'' an external trade regime and customs administration on [[September 3]], [[1999]] when it set customs border controls in Kosovo. All goods imported in Kosovo face a flat 10% customs duty fee.&lt;ref name=&quot;BuyUSA&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.buyusa.gov/kosovo/en/doingbusinessinkosovo.html |title=Doing Business in Kosovo |author=U.S. Commercial Service}}&lt;/ref&gt; These taxes are collected from all Tax Collection Points installed at the borders of Kosovo, including those between Kosovo and Serbia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.seerecon.org/kosovo/documents/wb_econ_report/wb-kosovo-econreport-2-2.pdf |format=PDF |title=External Trade and Customs |author=Economic Reconstruction and Development in South East Europe}}&lt;/ref&gt; UNMIK and Kosovo institutions have signed Free Trade Agreements with [[Croatia]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.b92.net/eng/news/globe-article.php?yyyy=2006&amp;mm=10&amp;dd=02&amp;nav_category=123&amp;nav_id=37090 |title=Croatia, Kosovo sign Interim Free Trade Agreement |author=B92 |authorlink=B92 |date=02/10/06 |publisher=mrt.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.euinkosovo.org/upload_press/4.06%20-%20UNMIK%20and%20Bosnia%20and%20Herzegovina%20Initial%20Free%20Trade%20Agreement%2017.2.06.pdf |format=PDF |title=UNMIK and Bosnia and Herzegovina Initial Free Trade Agreement |author=EU in Kosovo |date=17/02/06 |publisher=UNMIK}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Albania]] and [[Republic of Macedonia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BuyUSA&quot;/&gt;

The [[Republic of Macedonia]] is Kosovo's largest import and export market (averaging €220 million and €9 million, respectively), followed by Serbia-Montenegro (€111 million and €5 million), Germany and Turkey.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://siteresources.worldbank.org/INTKOSOVO/147270-1121700806276/20953280/Kosovo_Economic_Briefing_april.pdf |format=PDF |title=Kosovo Monthly Economic Briefing: Preparing for next winter |author=The World Bank |date=April 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[euro]] is the official currency of Kosovo and used by UNMIK and the government bodies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.euinkosovo.org/uk/invest/invest.php |title=Invest in Kosovo |author=EU in Kosovo}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Serbian dinar]] is used in the Serbian-populated parts.

The economy is hindered by Kosovo's still-unresolved international status, which has made it difficult to attract investment and loans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/business/4509781.stm |title=Brussels offers first Kosovo loan |author=BBC News |date=03/05/05}}&lt;/ref&gt; The province's economic weakness has produced a thriving black economy in which smuggled petrol, cigarettes and cement are major commodities. The prevalence of official corruption and the pervasive influence of organised crime gangs has caused serious concern internationally. The United Nations has made the fight against corruption and organised crime a high priority, pledging a &quot;zero tolerance&quot; approach.

== Demographics ==
{{main|Demographics of Kosovo}}
[[Image:Kosovo ethnic 2005.png|thumb|220px|Ethnic composition of Kosovo in [[2005]] according to the [[OSCE]]]]
According to the Kosovo in Figures 2005 Survey of the Statistical Office of Kosovo,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ks-gov.net/esk/esk/pdf/english/general/kosovo_figures_05.pdf |format=PDF |title=Kosovo in figures 2005 |author=UNMIK |publisher=Ministry of Public Services}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4385768.stm |title=Muslims in Europe: Country guide |author=BBC News |date=23/12/05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/country_profiles/3524092.stm |title=Regions and territories: Kosovo |author=BBC News |date=20/11/07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kosovo's total population is estimated between 1.9 and 2.2 million in the following ethnic proportions:

* 92% [[Albanians]]
* 4% [[Serbs]]
* 2% [[Bosniaks]] and [[Gorani (ethnic group)|Gorans]]
* 1% [[Roma people|Roma]]
* 1% [[Turkish people|Turks]]

[[Islam]] (mostly [[Sunni]], with a [[Bektashi]] minority) is the predominant [[religion]], professed by most of the majority ethnic Albanian population, the Bosniak, Gorani, and Turkish communities, and some of the Roma/[[Ashkali]]/[[Egyptians (Balkans)|Egyptian]] community. The Serb population, estimated at 100,000 to 120,000 persons, is largely [[Serbian Orthodox]]. Approximately 3 percent of ethnic Albanians are [[Roman Catholic]]. Catholic communities are concentrated around Catholic churches in [[Prizren]], [[Klina]], and [[Gjakova]]. [[Protestant]]s make up less than 1 percent of the population and have small populations in most cities, with the largest concentration located in Pristina. There are no synagogues or [[Jewish]] institutions; there are reportedly two families whose members have Jewish roots. The number of [[atheist]]s or those who do not practice any religion are difficult to determine, and estimates are largely unreliable.
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.crisisgroup.org/home/index.cfm?id=1591&amp;l=1 |title=Religion in Kosovo |author=International Crisis Group |date=31/01/01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2007/90198.htm#kosovo International Religious Freedom Report 2007 (U.S. Department of States) - Serbia (includes Kosovo)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2006/71405.htm#kosovo International Religious Freedom Report 2006 (U.S. Department of States) - Serbia and Montenegro (includes Kosovo)]&lt;/ref&gt;

Ethnic Albanians in Kosovo have the largest population growth in Europe.&lt;ref&gt;[http://files.osa.ceu.hu/holdings/300/8/3/text/3-13-10.shtml Albanian Population Growth]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.srpska-mreza.com/Kosovo/demographic-explosion.html Demographic explosion in Kosovo]&lt;/ref&gt; The people’s growth rate in Kosovo is 1.3%. Over an 82-year period (1921-2003) the population grew 4.6 times. If growth continues at such a pace, based on some estimations, the population will be 4.5 million by 2050.&lt;ref&gt;[http://kosovo-hotels.com/index.php?mod=kos_profile Kosovo-Hotels, Prishtina - Kosova-Hotels, Prishtinë]&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Demographics_of_Kosovo#World_War_II-1968|1948]] to [[Demographics_of_Kosovo#1989-1999:_Centralized_Yugoslav_Control|1991]] period, Serb population on Kosovo incresed for 12% (3 times less than in Serbia), while Albanian population increased for 300% in the same time period.

== Administrative divisions ==
{{main|Subdivisions of Kosovo}}
{{see also|Municipalities of Kosovo}}
Kosovo, for administrative reasons, is considered as consisting of seven districts.
[[North Kosovo]] maintains its own government, infrastructure and institutions by its dominant ethnic [[Serb]] population in the [[Mitrovica District]], viz. in the [[Albanik]], [[Zveçan]] and [[Zubin Potok]] municipalities and the northern part of [[Mitrovica]].

Kosovo is also divided into 30 municipalities :

{{Municipalities of Kosovo}}

== Culture ==
===Music===
{{main|Music of Kosovo}}
{{see|Music of Serbia}}

Although in Kosovo the music is diverse (influenced to an extent by the cultures of the various regimes who controlled the region), authentic Albanian music (see ''[[World Music]]'') and [[Serbian music]] do still exist. Albanian music is characterized by the use of the ''[[çiftelia]]'' (an authentic Albanian instrument), ''mandolin'', ''mandola'' and ''percussion''. In Kosovo, [[folk]] music is very popular alongside modern music. There are a number of folk [[singers]] and ensembles (both Albanian and Serbian). [[European classical music|Classical music]] is also well known in Kosovo and has been taught at [[universities]] (at the [[University of Prishtina#Albanian university|University of Prishtina Faculty of Arts]]  and the [[University of Pristina#Serbian university|University of Prishtina at [[Mitrovica]]  [[Faculty of Arts of Priština|Faculty of Arts]]) and several pre-[[college]] [[List of pre-college music schools|music school]]s

There are some notable music festivals in Kosovo:
* ''Rock për Rock'' - contains [[Rock (music)|rock]] and [[Heavy Metal music|metal]] music
* ''Polifest'' - contains all kinds of genres (usually [[Hip hop music|hip hop]] and commercial [[Pop (music)|pop]])
* ''Showfest'' - contains all kinds of genres (usually [[Hip hop music|hip hop]] and commercial [[Pop (music)|pop]])
* ''Videofest'' - contains all kinds of genres
* ''Kush Këndon Lutet Dy Herë'' - contains [[Christian music]]
* ''North City Jazz &amp; Blues festival'', an international [[music festival]] held annually in [[Zveçan]] ({{lang-sq|Zveçani}}), near Mitrovica,
Kosovo Radiotelevisions like ''RTK'', ''21'' and ''KTV'' have their musical charts.

===Sport===
Several sports federations have been formed in Kosovo within the framework of Law No. 2003/24 &quot;Law on Sport&quot; passed by the Assembly of Kosovo in 2003. The law formally established a national Olympic Committee, regulated the establishment of sports federations and established guidelines for sports clubs. At present only some of the sports federations established have gained international recognition.

Federations that have so far gained membership or recognition by their international governing body:
* [[Handball Federation of Kosovo]]
* [[Table Tennis Federation of Kosovo]]

Federations that have not yet gained international recognition:
* [[Basketball Federation of Kosovo]]
* [[Football Federation of Kosovo]] and the [[Kosovo national football team]]
* [[Olympic Committee of Kosovo]]
* [[Tennis Federation of Kosovo]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
{{cite book
  | last = Malcolm
  | first = Noel
  | authorlink = Noel Malcolm
  | title = Kosovo: A Short History
  | publisher = [[Harper Perennial]]
  | year = 1999
  | isbn = 0060977752 }}

== See also ==
&lt;div style=&quot;-moz-column-count:4; column-count:4;&quot;&gt;
* [[Assembly of Kosovo]]
* [[Government of Kosovo]]
* [[Prime Minister of Kosovo]]
* [[President of Kosovo]]
* [[Serbs in Kosovo]]
* [[Albanians in Kosovo]]
* [[Post and Telecom of Kosovo]]
* [[National awakening and the birth of Albania]]
* [[Demographic history of Kosovo]]
* [[Unrest in Kosovo|Unrest in Kosovo during March 2004]]
* [[Metohija]]
* [[North Kosovo]]
* [[Flag of Kosovo]]
* [[2008 Kosovo declaration of independence]]
&lt;/div&gt;

==External links==
{{portal|Kosovo|Flag of Kosovo.svg}}
{{sisterlinks}}
* {{wikiatlas|Kosovo}}
* [http://www.unmikonline.org/ United Nations Interim Administration in Kosovo]
* [http://www.ks-gov.net/pm/Fillimi/tabid/36/menuid/+/subid/+/lingo/2/language/en-US/Default.aspx The Government of Kosovo and Prime minister's office]
*[http://www.assembly-kosova.org/ Assembly of Kosovo]
*[http://www.president-ksgov.net/?id=1,67,67,67,e/ President of Kosovo]
* [http://www.srbija.sr.gov.yu/kosovo-metohija/?change_lang=en Serbian Government for Kosovo and Metohija]
* {{CIA World Factbook link|kv|Kosovo}}
* [http://www.visitkosova.org/english/index.htm Visit Kosovo - Tourism Website]
* {{wikitravel}}

{{Template group
|title = Geographic locale
|list  =
{{Kosovo}}
}}
{{Municipalities of the Republic of Kosovo}}
{{Template group
|title = International membership and history
|list  =
{{Countries of Europe}}
}}

&lt;!--Categories--&gt;
[[Category:Kosovo| ]]

&lt;!--Other languages--&gt;

[[als:Kosovo]]
[[ang:Kosovo]]
[[ar:كوسوفو]]
[[an:Kosovo]]
[[roa-rup:Cosova]]
[[frp:Kosovo]]
[[ast:Kosovo]]
[[az:Kosovo]]
[[bn:কসোভো]]
[[zh-min-nan:Kosovo]]
[[be:Косава]]
[[be-x-old:Косава]]
[[bs:Kosovo]]
[[br:Kosovo]]
[[bg:Косово]]
[[ca:Kosovo]]
[[cv:Косово]]
[[ceb:Kosovo]]
[[cs:Kosovo]]
[[ny:Kosovo]]
[[cy:Kosovo]]
[[da:Kosovo]]
[[de:Kosovo]]
[[et:Kosovo]]
[[el:Κοσσυφοπέδιο]]
[[es:Kosovo]]
[[eo:Kosovo]]
[[eu:Kosovo]]
[[fa:کوزوو]]
[[fr:Kosovo]]
[[ga:An Chosaiv]]
[[gl:Kosovo]]
[[ko:코소보]]
[[hi:कोसोवो]]
[[hsb:Kosovo]]
[[hr:Kosovo]]
[[io:Kosovo]]
[[id:Kosovo]]
[[is:Kosóvó]]
[[it:Kosovo]]
[[he:קוסובו]]
[[jv:Kosovo]]
[[ka:კოსოვო]]
[[kk:Косово]]
[[kw:Kosova]]
[[lad:Kosovo]]
[[la:Ager Merulensis]]
[[lv:Kosova]]
[[lt:Kosovas]]
[[li:Kosovo]]
[[hu:Kosovo]]
[[mk:Косово]]
[[ms:Kosovo]]
[[nah:Cosovo]]
[[nl:Kosovo]]
[[ja:コソボ]]
[[no:Kosovo]]
[[nn:Kosovo]]
[[nrm:Kosovo]]
[[oc:Kosova]]
[[uz:Kosovo]]
[[pms:Kòsovo]]
[[nds:Kosovo]]
[[pl:Kosowo]]
[[pt:Kosovo]]
[[ro:Kosovo]]
[[qu:Kusuwu]]
[[ru:Косово]]
[[sq:Kosova]]
[[simple:Kosovo]]
[[sk:Kosovo]]
[[sl:Kosovo]]
[[sr:Косово и Метохија]]
[[sh:Kosovo i Metohija]]
[[fi:Kosovo]]
[[sv:Kosovo]]
[[ta:கொசோவோ]]
[[th:คอซอวอ]]
[[vi:Kosovo]]
[[tr:Kosova]]
[[uk:Косово]]
[[ur:کوسووہ]]
[[vec:Kosovo]]
[[zh-yue:科索沃]]
[[diq:Kosova]]
[[zea:Kosovo]]
[[bat-smg:Kuosuovs]]
[[zh:科索沃]]</text>
