      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;div style=&quot;float:right; margin-left:1em;
text-align:center;&quot;&gt;[[Image:UTkosovo rel smaller 92.jpg|Map of Kosovo]]&lt;br&gt;[[Media:UTkosovo rel small 92.jpg|Larger version]]&lt;/div&gt;
''The neutrality of this article is [[Wikipedia:NPOV dispute|disputed]]. Please see the article's [[Talk:Kosovo and Metohia|talk page]] for more information.'' 

[[de:Kosovo]]
[[et:Kosovo]]
[[fr:Kosovo]]
[[nl:Kosovo]]

'''Kosovo and Metohia''' ([[Serbian language|Serbian]]: &amp;#1050;&amp;#1086;&amp;#1089;&amp;#1086;&amp;#1074;&amp;#1086; &amp;#1080; &amp;#1052;&amp;#1077;&amp;#1090;&amp;#1086;&amp;#1093;&amp;#1080;&amp;#1112;&amp;#1072;; [[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Kosova''), often called just '''Kosovo''', is a province of [[Serbia]], which together with [[Montenegro]] constitutes [[Serbia and Montenegro]].

== Geography ==
With an area of [[1 E10 m2|10,887]] [[square kilometre|km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;]] and a population of almost 2 million on the eve of the 1999 crisis, Kosovo borders with [[Montenegro]] to the northwest, rest of [[Serbia]] to the north and east, the [[Former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia]] to the south and [[Albania]] to the southwest. The largest cities are [[Prishtina|Pri&amp;#353;tina]], the capital, with 190,000 inhabitants, and [[Prizren]] in the southwest with 120,000: five other towns have populations in excess of 50,000.

===Geographical regions===
'''Metohia''' is the large valley at the west of the province; it could be seen as dark crescent on the left side of the map. It could be said that rest of the province is '''Kosovo''', though it is comprised of several geographical regions. '''Malo Kosovo''' (perhaps the best translation is &quot;Kosovo Proper&quot;) is the valley containing the cities of [[Pristina]] and [[Kosovska Mitrovica]]. Around the river [[Binacka Morava]] is '''Binacko pomoravlje'''. At the southmost tip of the province lies [[Gorani|Gora]].

==Origins of Kosovo's name==

The name &quot;Kosovo&quot; is apparently being related to the [[Slavic]] word ''kos'' (or &quot;[[blackbird]]&quot;). It is a widely used placename in Slav countries, appearing in [[Belarus]], [[Bosnia]], [[Bulgaria]], [[Croatia]] and [[Russia]], among other countries. Some Albanian researchers claim that the name is a Serbian form of an old Albanian placename meaning &quot;high plain&quot;, but this is not a widely accepted theory and would not explain the widespread distribution of the name across the Slav countries.

&quot;Metohia&quot; (alternatively spelled ''Metohija'') derives from the [[Greek language|Greek]] word ''metochia'' which denotes [[church]]-owned land. Albanians tend not to use this name for political reasons and instead prefer to call it ''Rrafsg i Dukagjinit'', the &quot;Dukagjin plateau&quot;.

The province is occasionally called '''Kosmet''', a contraction of ''Kosovo and Metohia'' which has tended to be used by the Serbian government and Serbian communists. Historically it has also been known as ''Kossovo'' (until the early 20th century) and before that, ''Cassovo'' or ''Cassua'' by (mainly Italian) geographers. 

Most localities in Kosovo have distinct Serbian and Albanian placenames, some very similar, some differing radically. During the period of Serbian rule from [[1912]]-[[1999]], Kosovo placenames were known internationally exclusively by their Serbian versions. Since the United Nations took over administration of the province in June 1999, the international community has adopted a policy of treating both versions equally. For the sake of convenience, this article gives alternative placenames the first time a locality is mentioned, but will use the more familiar Serbian version thereafter. A useful list of Serbian and Albanian forms of Kosovo placenames is available at [http://www.osce.org/kosovo/documents/reports/hr/part1/p5app.htm http://www.osce.org/kosovo/documents/reports/hr/part1/p5app.htm].

== History ==

Modern Kosovo has only existed as a political or territorial entity since [[1945]]. Before then, its territory was ruled entirely or partially by Italian-occupied Albania, Serbia, Montenegro, the [[Ottoman Empire]], the [[Byzantine Empire]], [[Bulgaria]] and the [[Roman Empire]]. Some have suggested that Kosovo has been a single distinctive region since ancient times but this is strongly contradicted by [[archaeology|archaeological]] findings and historic records. Nor has Kosovo's population been ethnically consistent over the years: the province's complex ethnic map has included Latins, [[Turks]], [[Roma]], [[Gorani]] (Slav Muslims), Circassians and [[Jews]] in addition to Serbs and Albanians. 

=== Kosovo from prehistory to 1455 ===

Little is known about Kosovo before about the [[11th century]] AD. The region was certainly inhabited in [[prehistory|prehistoric]] times: in particular, [[bronze age|Bronze]] and [[Iron Age]] [[tomb]]s have been found only in Metohia, and not in Kosovo. Later, the whole territory of Kosovo became part of the [[Roman Empire]], although it is not clear whether it was part of the province of [[Moesia]] or was divided between Dalmatia and Moesia (a view which is supported by some archaeological evidence). [http://www.rastko.org.yu/kosovo/istorija/malkolm/djankovic-facts.html]

According to most historians, Serbs entered the Balkans around the late [[6th century|6th]] or early [[7th century]] AD, possibly migrating from the northern [[Caucasus]] where [[Ptolemy]] placed the &quot;Serboi&quot; in the [[2nd century]] AD. The initial spread of the [[Slavic]] population of the [[Balkans]] was much larger then today, reaching well into [[Greece]] and [[Albania]]. Placenames derived from Slavic root words are still widespread in the remaining non-Slav Balkan countries.

The origins of the Albanians are much less clear. Many historians believe that they are descended from the [[Illyrian|Illyrians]], the original inhabitants of the western Balkans in Roman times, although [[Romanian|Romania]] historians have suggested that they may alternatively be descended from the ancient [[Thracian|Thracians]], who inhabited the eastern Balkans. Albanian historians claim that in around the [[6th century]] the Illyrians were forced south into what is now Albania by [[Slav]] tribes - the predecessors of modern day Serbs. Some Serb historians claim that Albanians came to the Balkans in the [[11th century]] AD from the [[Caucasian Albania|Caucasus]], but this theory is not widely accepted outside of Serbia. [http://www.geocities.com/highduke/albanians.html][http://www.geocities.com/CapitolHill/Lobby/7681/albanian_toponyms.html] The first surviving documentary evidence of the Albanians dates only to [[1043]], but many historical linguists suggest that the vocabulary and structure of the [[Albanian language]] points to a much earlier presence in the western Balkans.

The Kosovo region lay on the outer fringes of the Byzantine Empire and lay directly in the path of the Slav expansion. From about the 850s until about [[1014]], it was ruled by Bulgarian and Macedonian Slavs. Byzantine control was subsequently reasserted by the forceful emperor [[Basil II|Basil &quot;the Bulgar Slayer&quot;]]. Serbia at this time did not exist: a number of small Slav kingdoms lay to the north and west of Kosovo, of which [[Raska]] or Rascia (in central modern Serbia) and Dioclea (Montenegro) were the strongest. In the 1180s, the Serbian ruler [[Stefan Nemanja]] seized control of Dioclea, northern Albania, northern Macedonia and parts of Kosovo. His successor (also called [[Stefan Prvovencani|Stefan]]) took control of the rest of Kosovo by [[1216]], creating a state incorporating most of modern Serbia and Montenegro.

During the rule of the Nemanjid dynasty, many [[Serbian Orthodox]] churches and monasteries were built throughout Serbian territory, including in Kosovo. Large estates were given to Serbian monasteries in Metohia, for which the area earned the designation ''Metohia'' or &quot;monastic land&quot;. The most prominent churches in Kosovo - the [[Patriarchate]] at [[Pec]]/Peja, the church at Gracanica/Ulpiana and the monastery at Visoki Decani/Decane in Metohia - were all founded during this period. Kosovo had relatively little political significance, however, as the medieval Serbian state was ruled principally from other towns: Ras (near [[Novi Pazar]]), [[Skopje]] in modern [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]] and [[Krusevac]] in central Serbia. Kosovo was economically important, as the modern Kosovar capital [[Pristina]]/Pristine was a major trading centre on routes leading to ports on the [[Adriatic Sea]].

The ethnic composition of Kosovo's population during this period is a controversial issue among Serbian and Albanian nationalists. Serbs, Albanians and [[Vlach|Vlachs]] were all clearly present, as all three groups were named explicitly in Serbian monastic charters or ''chrysobulls''. Their relative numbers are unknowable - no censuses have survived - but a majority of the names given in the charters are Serbian rather than Albanian. This has been interpreted as evidence of a Serbian majority, though the names alone do not appear to be a wholly reliable guide: some chrysobulls show Albanian-named fathers giving their sons Serbian names, and vice-versa. Albanian historians have suggested that this is evidence of forced assimilation of Kosovo's Albanian population, but this is undermined by records of Serbian-named fathers giving sons Albanian names (which would surely not have happened if the assimilation was a one-way process). Ethnic identity in the [[Middle Ages]] was somewhat fluid throughout Europe and people at that time do not appear to have defined themselves rigidly by ethnic group. About all that can be said for sure is that Serbs appear to have been the dominant population culturally, and were probably a demographic majority as well.

In [[1355]], the Serbian state fell apart on the death of Tsar [[Stefan Dusan]] and dissolved into squabbling fiefdoms. The [[Ottoman E</text>
