      <text xml:space="preserve">{{POV-check}}
{{otheruses}}
{| {{prettyinfobox}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
&lt;big&gt;''' Kosovo '''&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/big&gt;&lt;br&gt;
|-
| style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Image:Citys of Kosova.PNG|160px]] 
|-
|-

| [[Official language]]s
| [[Albanian language|Albanian]], [[Serbian language|Serbian]]
|-
| [[Capital]]
| [[Prishtinë]]/[[Priština]]
|-
| [[President of Kosovo]]
| [[Fatmir Sejdiu]]
|-
| [[Prime Minister of Kosovo]]
| [[Agim Çeku]]
|-
| [[Area]]&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; Total&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; % water
| &lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;[[1 E10 m²|10,912]] km²&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;4,213&amp;nbsp;[[square mile|sq.&amp;nbsp;mi]]&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;n/a
|-
| valign=top | [[Population]]&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; Total ([[2003]])&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; [[Population density|Density]]&lt;br/&gt;
| &lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;2.1 million (est.)&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;220/km² (approx)&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;570/sq.&amp;nbsp;mi
|-
| valign=top | [[List of ethnic groups|Ethnic groups]]&lt;br/&gt;([[2003]])
| [[Albanians]]: 88%&lt;br/&gt;[[Serbs]]: 7%&lt;br/&gt;Others: 5%
|-
| [[Time zone]]
| [[Coordinated Universal Time|UTC]] +1
|-
| [[Currency]]
| [[Euro]] and [[Serbian dinar]] 
|-
|}

'''Kosovo''' ([[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Kosovë''/''Kosova'', [[Serbian language|Serbian]]: Косово и Метохија/''Kosovo i Metohija'') is a [[UN]]-administered province. By the [[UN Security Council Resolution 1244]] (adopted in 1999), Kosovo is defined as autonomous province within former [[Federal Republic of Yugoslavia]] under UN administration. Kosovo is presently run by the [[Provisional Institutions of Selfgovernment]] of the [[UN]] and the [[EU]], while the security is maintained by the [[NATO]]-led [[KFOR]]. The talks on the future status of Kosovo have started in [[Vienna]], on February 20, [[2006]], with the future of the province should be determined by the end of the year. 

== Geography ==
[[image:UTkosovo rel small 92.jpg|thumb|left|275px|Physical map of Kosovo]]
With an area of [[1 E10 m²|10,912]] [[square kilometre]]s (4,213 [[square mile|sq.&amp;nbsp;mi]]) and a population of over two million of the eve of the 1999 crisis, Kosovo borders [[Montenegro]] to the northwest, [[Serbia proper]] to the North and East; [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]] to the south, and [[Albania]] to the southwest. The largest cities are [[Priština]] (''Prishtinë'', in [[Albanian language|Albanian]]) the capital, with an estimated 500,000 citizens, and [[Prizren]] in the southwest with 120,000 citizens; five other towns have populations in excess of 50,000. The name [[Metohija]] is used by mostly [[Serbian people|Serbs]] for the western part of the land (''Rrafshi i Dukagjinit'', in [[Albanian language|Albanian]]).

== History ==
{{main|History of Kosovo}}
:''See also: [[Demographic history of Kosovo]]''
=== Ancient ===
It is likely that the region of Kosovo has been inhabited by [[Illyrians|Illyrian tribes]] since the [[Bronze Age]]. In ancient times the area has been known as [[Dardania (Europe)|Dardania]] and was settled by a tribe with the same name. The south of Kosovo was ruled by [[Macedonia]] since [[Alexander the Great]]'s reign in the 4th century BC. The local [[Dardani]] were of [[Illyrian]] or [[Thracian]] stock. Illyrians organised resistance against the [[Greeks]] and [[Ancient Rome|Romans]] for centuries but after the long wars of Illyrian tribes against intruders, the region was later occupied by the [[Roman Empire]] under Emperor [[Augustus]]. When the Roman Empire split in [[Anno Domini|A.D.]]&amp;nbsp;[[395]], the area of Kosovo came under the [[Byzantine Empire|Eastern Roman Empire]], the [[Byzantine Empire]]. [[Dardania]] gave numerous leaders to both Rome and [[Constantinopolis]]. [[Justinian the Great]] was among them.

=== Medieval ===
==== Great Migrations ====
[[Slavic peoples|Slavs]] came to the territories roughly modern-day Kosovo in the [[6th century|6th]]-[[7th century]], with the largest waves coming in the 630s. The Slavs were [[Christianization|christianized]] in several waves, between the [[7th century|7th]] and [[9th century]], with the last wave taking place between [[867]] and [[874]]. From the [[850]]s until [[1014]] Kosovo was ruled by the [[First Bulgarian Empire|Bulgarians]] and the [[Byzantines]] , while the area of [[Metohija]] ([[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Rrafshi i Dukagjinit''). became a part of the [[Serb]] [[Principality of Rascia]], with [[Desnik|Dostinik]] in [[Hvosno]] as the Principality's Capital.

==== Serbian takeover ====
The full Serbian takeover was carried out under a branch of the [[House of Vojislavljević|House of Voislav]] [[Grand Prince|Grand Princes]] of [[Rascia]]. In [[1093]], Prince Vukan advanced all the way to [[Lipljan]], burned it down and raided the neighbouring areas. The Byzantine Emperor himself came to [[Zvečan]] for negotiations. [[Zvečan]] served as the Byzantine line-of-defence against constant invasions from the neigbouring Serbs. A peace was concluded, but Vukan broke it and defeated the army of John Comnenus, the Emperor's nephew. His armies stormed Kosovo. [[Alexius I Comnenus|Byzantine Emperor Alexius]] had to come to Ulpiana in [[1094]] and negotiated again. Peace was concluded and Vukan gave hostages to the Emperor, including his two nephews Uroš and Stefan Vukan. Prince Vukan renewed the warring in [[1106]], once again defeating John Comnenus' army, but Vukan's following death put a halt to a total conquest of Kosovo. 

In [[1166]], a Serbian nobleman from [[Zeta (state)|Zeta]], [[Stefan Nemanja]], the founder of the [[Nemanjić|House of Nemanja]] asserted to the Rascian Grand Princely throne and conquered most of Kosovo, in an uprising against the Byzantine Emperor [[Manuel I Comnenus]]. He defeated the previous Grand Prince of Rascia Tihomir's army at Pantino, near Pauni. Tihomir, who was Stefan's brother, was drowned in the [[Sitnica]] river. Stefan was eventually defeated and had to return some of his conquests, and vouched to the Emperor that he would not raise his hand against him. In [[1183]], Stefan Nemanja embarked on a new offensive with the [[Hungarians]] after the death of [[Manuel I Comnenus]] in [[1180]], which marked the end of Byzantine domination of Kosovo. 

Nemanja's son, [[Stefan Prvovenčani|Stefan II]], recorded Nemanja's conquests, as Nemanja restored Kosovo from the Greeks, the border of the Serbian realm reaching the river of Lab. Grand Prince Stephen II finished the inclusion of the Kosovo territories in 1208, by which time he had conquered Prizren and Lipljan, and moved the border of his realm to the Šar mountain.

==== Kingdom of the Serbs ====
In [[1217]], the [[History of Serbia|Serbian Kingdom]] achieved recognition. In [[1219]], an autocephalous [[Serbian Orthodox Church]] was created, with [[Hvosno]], Prizren and Lipljan being the Orthodox Christian [[Episcopates]] on Kosovo. By the end of the [[13th century]], the centre of the [[Serbian Orthodox Church|Serbian Church]] was moved to [[Peć]] from [[Žiča]].

In the 13th century, Kosovo becomes the heart of the Serbian political and religious life with the Šar mountain becoming the political center of the Serbian rulers. The main chatteu was that in Pauni. On an island was [[Svrčin]] and on the coast [[Štimlji]], and in the mountains was the Castle of [[Nerodimlje]]. The Complexes were used for counciling, crowning of rulers, negotiating and as the rulers' living quarters. After 1291, the Tartars broke all the way to Peć. [[List of Serbian rulers|Serbian King]] [[Stefan Milutin]] managed to defeat them and then chase them further. He raised the Temple of the [[Mother of Christ]] of Ljeviška in Prizren around 1307, which became the seat of the Prizren Episcopric and the magnificent [[Gračanica]] in 1335, the seat of the Lipljan Episcopric. In 1331, Juvenille King Dušan attacked his father, Serbian King Stefan of Dechani at his castle in Nerodimlje. King Stefan closed in his neighbouring fortress of [[Petrič]], but Dušan captures him and closed him with his second wife Maria Palailogos and their children in Zvečan, where the dethroned King died on [[11 November]] [[1331]].

In 1327 and 1328, Serbian King Stefan of Dechani started forming the vast Dečani domain, although, Serbian King Dušan would finish it in 1335. Stefan of Dechani issued that Dechani Charter in 1330. Listing every single citizen in every household under the Church Land's demesne.

==== [[Serbian Empire]] and [[History of Serbia|Despotate]] ====
[[Monarch|King]] [[Stefan Dušan]] founded the vast Monastery of Saint Archaengel near Prizren in [[1342]]-[[1352]]. The Kingdom was transformed into an [[Serbian Empire|Empire]] in 1345 and officially in 1346. Stefan Dušan received [[John VI Cantacuzenus]] in [[1342]] in his Castle in [[Pauni]] to discuss a joint War against the Byzantine Emperor. In [[1346]], the Serbian [[Archbishopric|Archepiscopric]] at Peć was upgraded into a [[Patriarchate]], but it was not recognized before [[1370]]. 

After the Empire fell into disarray prior to Dušan's death in [[1355]], feudal anarchy caught up with the country during the reign of Tsar [[Stefan Uroš V]]. Kosovo became a domain of the [[Vukašin Mrnjavčević|House of Mrnjavčević]], but Prince Voislav Voinović expanded his demesne further onto Kosovo. The armies of King [[Vukašin Mrnjavčević]] from [[Priština]] and his allies defeated Voislav's forces in [[1369]], putting a halt to his advances. After the [[Battle of Marica]] on [[26 September]] [[1371]] in which the Mrnjavčević brothers lost their lives, [[House of Balšić|Đurađ I Balšić]] of [[Zeta (state)|Zeta]] took Prizren and Peć in [[1372]]. A part of Kosovo became the demesne of the [[Prince Lazar|House of Lazarević]].

The [[Ottomans]] invaded the Serbian Realm and met the Christian coalition under [[Prince Lazar]] on [[28 June]] [[1389]], near [[Priština]], at Gazi Mestan. The Serbian Army was assisted by various allies. The epic [[Battle of Kosovo]] followed, in which Prince Lazar himself lost his life. Prince Lazar amassed 70,000 men on the battlefield and the Ottomans had 140,000. Through the cunning of [[Miloš Obilić]], [[Sultan]] [[Murad I|Murad]] was murdered and the new Sultan [[Beyazid]] had, despite winning the battle, to retreat to consolidate his power. The Ottoman Sultan was buried with one of his sons at Gazi Mestan. Both [[Prince Lazar]] and [[Miloš Obilić]] were canonised by the [[Serbian Ortodox Church]] for their efforts in the battle. The local House of [[Vuk Branković|Branković]] came to prominence as the local lords of Kosovo, under [[Vuk Branković]], with the temporary fall of the [[History of Serbia|Serbian Despotate]] in [[1439]]. Another great battle occurred between the Hungarian troops supported by the Albanian ruler Gjergj Kastrioti [[Skanderbeg]] on one side, and Ottoman troops supported by the [[House of Branković|Branković]]s in [[1448]]. Skanderbeg's troops which were going to help John Hunyadi were stopped by the Brankovic's troops, who was more or less a Turkish [[Vassal]]. Hungarian King [[John Hunyadi]] lost the battle after a 2-day fight, but essentially stopped the Ottoman advance northwards. Kosovo then became vassalaged to the [[Ottoman Empire]], until its direct incorporation as the [[Viyalet of Kosovo]] after the final fall of Serbia in 1459.

In [[1455]], new castles rose to prominence in [[Priština]] and [[Vučitrn]], centres of the Ottoman vassalaged [[Vuk Branković|House of Branković]].

=== [[Ottoman]] rule ===
{{main|Viyalet of Kosovo}}
The [[Ottoman Empire|Ottomans]] brought [[Islamisation]] with them, particularly in towns, and later also created the [[Viyalet of Kosovo]] as one of the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] territorial entities. This brought a great shift, as the Orthodox Serb population began to lose its majority when masses of [[Turks]] and [[Albanians]] ([[Muslims]]) moved to Kosovo. During the Islamisation many Churches and Holy Orthodox Christian places were raised to the ground or turned in to Mosques. The big Monastery of Saint Archangel near Prizren was teared down at the end of the 16th century and the material used to build the Mosque of Sinan-pasha, an Islamized Serb, in Prizren. Although the [[Serbian Orthodox Church]] was officially abolished in 1532, an Islamized Serb from Bosnia, Vizier [[Mehmed-pasha Sokolović]] influenced the restoration of the [[Patriarchate of Peć]] in 1557. Special privalages were provided, which helped the survival of Serbs and other Christians on Kosovo. 

Kosovo was taken by the Austrian forces during the Great War of [[1683]] - [[1699]] with help of 5,000 Albanians and their leader, a [[Catholic Archibishop]] [[Pjetër Bogdani]]. The archbishop died of plague during the war, and his grave was later reopened, with his body scattered and given to the dogs by the Ottomans because of his role in the rebellion. In [[1690]], the [[Serbian Patriarch of Peć]] [[Arsenije III]], who previously escaped a certain death, led 37,000 families from Kosovo, to evade [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] wrath since Kosovo had just been retaken by the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottomans]]. The people that followed him were mostly [[Serbs]], but there where numerous Orthodox Albanians and others too. 20,000 Serbs abandoned [[Prizren]] alone. Due to the oppression from the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottomans]], other migrations of Orthodox people from the Kosovo area continued throughout the [[18th century]]. It is also noted that some [[Serbs]] adopted [[Islam]] and some even gradually fused with the predominantly Albanianians and adopted their culture and even language. By the end of the 19th century, [[Albanians]] replaced the Serbs as the dominating nation of Kosovo.

In 1766 the Ottomans abolished the [[Patriarchate of Peć]] and the position of [[Christians]] on Kosovo was greatly reduced. All previous privilages were lost and the Christian population had to suffer the full weight of the Empire's extensive and losing wars, even to take the blame for the losses. 

=== Modern ===
The arising [[History of Serbia|Principality of Serbia]] planned a restoration of its rule on Kosovo as the Ottoman might crumbled on the Balkan peninsular. The period witnessed a rise of Serbian nationalism, as the Serb elite refused to admit the Albanian national spirit and referred to the [[Albanians]] as ''Arvanites'', &quot;Albanians of Serbian origin&quot; or &quot;[[Albanian language|Albanian]]-speaking Serbs&quot;. Serbia's plans for a post-Ottoman period included the return of Kosovo.  

Moslem refugees from the territories conquered in the [[1876]]-[[1877]] Serbo-Turkish war and the [[1877]]-[[1878]] Russo-Turkish are now known as '[[muhajir (Albania)|muhaxher]]' (which means 'refugee', from [[Arabic]] [[muhajir]]) and are the ancestors of many who are still known by their same surnames, ''Muhaxheri''. It is also estimated that 200,000 to 400,000 Serbs were cleansed out of the [[Vilayet of Kosovo]] between [[1876]] and [[1912]], especially during the [[Greco-Turkish War (1897)|Greek-Ottman War]] in [[1897]]. 

Albanians formed the nationalistic [[League of Prizren]] in [[Prizren]] in the [[19th century]]. Hundreds of Albanian leaders from Albania gathered and discussed the urgent issues concerning protection of Albanian populated regions from being divided among neighbouring countries. They successfully opposed any Serbian invasion attempts. Serbia complained to the Western Powers that the promised territories were not being held because the Ottomans were hesitating to do that. Western Powers put pressure to the Ottomans and in 1881, the Ottoman Army started the fighting against Albanians. The Prizren League created a Provisional Government with a President, Prime Minister (Ymer Prizreni) and Ministries of War (Sylejman Vokshi) and Foreign Ministry (Abdyl Frashëri). After three years of war, the Albanians were defeated. Many of the leaders were executed and imprisoned. In [[1910]], an [[Albanian]] uprising spread from [[Prishtina]] and lasted until the Ottoman Sultan's visit to Kosovo in [[June]] [[1911]]. The Aim of the League of Prizren was to unite the four Albanian Vilayets by merging the majority of Albanian inhabitants within the Ottoman Empire into one Albanian State. However at that time Serbs have consisted about ''40%'' of the whole Vilayt of Kosovo's overall population and were opposing the Albanian nationalism along with Turks and other Slavs in Kosovo, which disabled the Albanian movements to occupy Kosovo. 

:''See also: [[Serbia in WWI]]''

In [[1912]] during the [[Balkan Wars]], most of Kosovo was liberated by the [[History of Serbia|Kingdom of Serbia]], while the region of [[Metohija]] ([[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Dukagjini Valley'') was taken by the [[History of Montenegro|Kingdom of Montenegro]]. An exodus of the local Albanian population occured. This is best described by [[Leon Trotsky]], who was the reporter for the 'Pravda' newspaper at the time. The Serbian authorities planned a recolonization of Kosovo&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.elsie.de/pdf/B2002GatheringClouds.pdf Elsie, R. (ed.) (2002): ''Gathering Clouds. The roots of ethnic cleansing in Kosovo. Early twentieth-century documents''. Dukagjini Balkan Books, Peja (Kosovo, Serbia). ISBN 9951-05-016-6&lt;/ref&gt;. Numerous colonist Serb families moved-in to Kosovo, equalizing the demographic balance between Albanians and Serbs. 

In the winter of [[1915]]-[[1916]] during [[World War I]] Kosovo saw a large exodus of Serbian army; tens of thousands of soldiers have died of starvation, extreme weather and Albanian reprisals as they were approaching the [[Allies]] in [[Corfu]] and [[Thessaloniki]]. In 1918 the Serbian Army pushed the [[Central Powers]] out of Kosovo. Kosovo was unified as Montenegro subsequently joined the Kingdom of Serbia. The Monarchy was then transformed into the [[Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes]]. 

==== Kingdom of Yugoslavia and WWII ====
The [[1918]]-[[1929]] period of the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes witnessed a raise of the Serbian population in the region and a decline in the non-Serbian. In the Kingdom Kosovo was split onto four counties - three being a part of the entity of Serbia: Zvečan, Kosovo and southern Metohija; and one of Montenegro: northern Metohija. However, the new administration system since [[26 April]] [[1922]] split Kosovo among three Areas of the Kingdom: Kosovo, [[Rascia]] and [[Zeta]]. 

In 1929 the Kingdom was transformed into the [[Kingdom of Yugoslavia]] which the ''[[Yugoslav]]'' nationality unifying all Kosovan [[Slavs]]. The territories of Kosovo were split among the [[Zeta Banovina|Banate of Zeta]], the [[Morava Banovina|Banate of Morava]] and the [[Vardar Banovina|Banate of Vardar]]. The Kingdom lasted until the [[World War II]] [[Axis_powers|Axis]] invastion of 1941. 

The greatest part of Kosovo became a part of [[Italy|Italian]]-controlled [[Greater Albania|Fascist Albania]], and smaller bits by the [[Nazism|Nazi]]-[[Fascist]] [[Greater Bulgaria|Tsardom of Bulgaria]] and [[Nazism|Nazi]] [[Germany|German]]-occupied [[Serbia|Kingdom of Serbia]]. Since the Albanian Fascist political leadership had decided in the [[Conference of Bujan]] that Kosovo would remain a part of Albania they started an ethnic cleansing campaign of the non-Albanian population in the Kosovo. The infamous [[21st Waffen Mountain Division of the SS Skanderbeg (1st Albanian)|SS Division Skanderbeg]] committed crimes. {{citation needed}}. Tens of thousands of Serbs lost their lives and around 75,000 Serbs fled Kosovo during the war. Hundreds of thousands more would leave in the following decades, following the shift of power in Kosovo. 

Prior to the surrender of [[History of Italy|Fascist Italy]] in [[1943]], the German forces took over direct control of the region. After numerous uprisings of [[Serbs|Serbian]] [[Chetniks]] and [[Yugoslav]] [[Partisans]], the latter being lead by [[Fadil Hoxha]], Kosovo was liberated after [[1944]] with the help of the Albanian partisans of the [[Comintern]], and became a province of [[Serbia]] within the [[Yugoslavia|Democratic Federal Yugoslavia]]. 

==== Kosovo in the Second Yugoslavia ====
The Province of Kosovo was formed in 1945 as an autonomous region to protect its regional [[Albanians|Albanian]] majority within the [[History of Serbia|People's Republic of Serbia]] as a member of the [[SFRJ|Federal People's Republic of Yugoslavia]] under the leadership of the former Partisan leader, [[Josip Broz Tito]], but with no factual autonomy. After the Yugoslavia's name change to the [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia]] and Serbia's to the [[History of Serbia|Socialist Republic of Serbia]] in [[1953]], the Autonomous Region of Kosovo and gained inner autonomy in the 1960s. In the [[1974]] constitution, the Socialist Autonomous Province of Kosovo's government received higher powers, including the highest governmental titles - President and Premier and a seat in the Federal Presidency which made it a ''de facto'' Socialist Republic within the Federation, but remaining as a Socialist Autonomous Region within the Socialist Republic of Serbia. [[Serbo-Croatian]] and [[Albanian language|Albanian]] were defined official on the Provincial level marking the two largest linguistic Kosovan groups: Serbs and Albanians. In the 1970s, an Albanian nationalist movement pursued full recognition of the Province of Kosovo as another Republic within the Federation, while the most extreme elements aimed for full-scale independence. Tito's arbitrary regime dealt with the situation swiftly, but only giving it a temporary solution. The ethnic balance of Kosovo witnessed unproportional increase as the number of [[Albanians]] tripled gradually rising from almost ''65%'' to over ''80%'' and the number [[Serbs]] barely increased and dropped in the full share of the total population from some ''25%'' down to ''10%''.

In [[1981]] the Kosovar Albanian students organized protests seeking that Kosovo becomes a Republic within Yugoslavia. Those protests were harshly contained by the centralist Yugoslav and Serbian governments. In [[1986]], the [[SANU|Serbian Academy of Sciences and Arts]] (SANU) was working on a document, which later would be known as the [[SANU Memorandum]]. An unfinished edition was filtered to the press. In the essay, SANU portrayed the Serbian people as a victim and called for the revival of Serb nationalism, using both true and greatly exaggerated facts for propaganda. During this time, [[Slobodan Milošević]]'s rise to power started in the League of the Socialists of Serbia. Milošević used the discontent reflected in the SANU memorandum for his political goals.

==== Kosovo War ====
{{main|Kosovo War}}
One of the events that contributed to Milošević's rise of power was the ''Gazimestan Speech'', delivered in front of 100,000 Serb citizens at the central celebration marking the 600th anniversary of the [[Battle of Kosovo]], held at [[Gazimestan]] on 28 June, 1989. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.balkanpeace.org/cib/kam/kams/kams19.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; In the speech, Milošević criticised the &quot;dramatical national divisions&quot; and called Yugoslavia &quot;a multinational community [which] can survive only under the conditions of full equality for all nations that live in it.&quot; 

Soon afterwards, as approved by the Assembly in 1990, the autonomy of Kosovo was revoked back to the old status. Milošević, however, did not remove Kosovo's seat from the Federal Presidency, installing in it his own supporters to seize more power in the Federal government. After [[Slovenia]]'s secession from Yugoslavia in 1991, Milošević used the seat to attain dominance over the Federal government, outvoting his opponents. 

Many Albanians organized a peaceful active resistance movement, following the job losses suffered by some of them. Albanian schools and the medical care system were shut down{{fact}}. 

On [[July 2]], [[1990]] an unconstitutional Kosovo parliament declared Kosovo an independent country, although this was not recognized by the Government. In September of that year, the parliament, meeting in secrecy in the town of [[Kaçanik]], adopted the ''Constitution of the Republic of Kosovo''. Two years later, in 1992, the Parliament organized a referendum which was observed by international organisations but was not recognized internationally. With an ''80%'' turnout, ''98%'' voted for Kosovo to be independent. In the early nineties, Albanians organized a parallel state system which managed the non-violent resistance movement and organized a parallel system of education and healthcare, among other things. With the events in [[Bosnia]] and [[Croatia]] coming to an end, the Serb government started relocating Serbian refugees from Croatia and Bosnia to Kosovo. In a number of cases, Albanian families were expelled from their apartments to make space for the refugees{{fact}}.

After the [[Dayton]] Agreement in 1995, Albanians organized into the [[Kosovo Liberation Army]]. Yugoslav forces allegedly committed war crimes in Kosovo, although the Serbian government claims that the army was only going after suspected Albanian &quot;terrorists&quot;. This triggered a 78-day [[NATO]] campaign in [[1999]]. During the conflict, some 12,000 Kosovars were killed, of whom 9,000-10,000 were [[Albanians]] and 1,000-2,000 others ([[Serbs]] and [[Roma]]) and up to 700,000 Albanians and over 100,000 Serbs expelled. Some 3,000 Albanians are still missing. The number of Serbian soldier, policemen, and civilian deaths is considered to be around 3,000, but it's also disputed to be much more, as 2,800 people of Serb origin are still missing, believed dead{{fact}}. According to OSCE numbers and Kosovar Albanian sources on population size and distribution, an estimated ''45.7%'' of the Albanian population and ''59.5%'' of the Serb population had fled Kosovo during the bombings (i.e. from 23 March to 9 June 1999).

With the arrival of NATO, a large number of Serbs fled the region, estimated at 100,000 by the UNHCR. Around 120,000 remain in Kosovo and oppose any rule by Albanians. Many Serbs fear to return to their homes since they perceive not to be safe for them, even with [[UNMIK]] protection, notably the [[Unrest in Kosovo|unrest in 2004]], when 900 Serbian houses were burned and other property destroyed while the Serbian populace was closed into enclaves and had to concentrate to the north of Kosovo until today, causing a wave of 3,500 Serbian refugees. Among the numerous [[UNESCO]] World Heritage sites destroyed by the Albanian para-military forces is King [[Stefan Milutin]]'s grave, [[Our Lady of Ljeviš Orthodox Cathedral]] from the 12th century in [[Prizren]]. In total, 156 Orthodox Serb Churches and Monasteries were destroyed during the unrest in Kosovo. Many of the Churches and Monasteries were dating back to the 12th, 13th and 14th century. 

The Status talks started in February 2006, it is set to end in the course of the year. The security of the minorities, must be provided by Kosovo Albanian governments, but it is disputed if the Kosovo Albanian Institutions can grant these guarantees.

== Economy ==
[[UNMIK]] declared the [[Euro]] to be the official currency of the province in [[2001]] in the course of implementing a currency reform. This was undertaken to replace the previous widespread use of the [[Deutschmark]], which had become the ''de facto'' currency even before the 1999 war. However, the [[Serbian dinar]] remains an official currency, used principally in the [[Kosovo Serb enclaves]]; it is only used sporadically outside of them. Most trade is conducted using the euro; Kosovo's administration uses the euro exclusively, and all commercial banks use the euro as the primary currency. Of other international currencies, the [[United States dollar]] and [[Swiss franc]] are the most widespread.

== Demographics ==

According to the 2000 Living Standard Measurement Survey of the Statistical Office of Kosovo[http://www.sok-kosovo.org/pdf/population/Kosovo_population.pdf], Kosovo's total population is estimated between 1,8 and 2,0 million in the following ethnic proportions:
* ''88%'' [[Albanians]] (between 1,584,000 and 1,733,600) 
* ''7%'' [[Serbs]] (between 126,000 and 140,000)	
* ''3%'' [[Muslims by nationality|Muslims]] and [[Bosniaks]] (54 to 60 thousand) 
* ''2%'' [[Roma people|Roma]] (36 to 40 thousand) (see also [[Roma in Mitrovica Camps]])
* ''1%'' [[Turkish people|Turks]] (18 to 20 thousand)

However, the figures are highly disputable. Some estimates are that there is an Albanian majority well above 90 percent. Others give much higher figures for Roma and Turks [http://www.siri-us.com/backgrounders/Archives_Kosovo/Kosovo-Milosevic.html][http://www.salon.com/news/1999/03/31newsa.html][http://www.serbianunity.net/news/world_articles/Dragnich1098.html]. There was a small minority of [[Circassians]] in [[Kosovo Polje]](Fushë-Kosovë in Albanian) but they were repatriated to the [[Republic of Adygea]], in Southern [[Russia]], following threats by the [[KLA]]&lt;ref&gt;BBC News: ''Circassians flee Kosovo conflict''. Sunday, August 2, 1998 Published at 01:01 GMT 02:01 UK&lt;/ref&gt;

== List of Presidents ==
* [[Ibrahim Rugova]], [[1992]]-[[2006]] (deceased)
* [[Fatmir Sejdiu]], [[2006]]-present

== List of Prime Ministers ==
* [[Bajram Rexhepi]], [[2002]]-[[2004]]
* [[Ramush Haradinaj]], [[2004]]-[[2005]]
* [[Bajram Kosumi]], [[2005]]-[[2006]]
* [[Agim Çeku]], [[2006]]-present

== Gallery ==
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Prishtina maj 2005.jpg|[[Prishtina]]/[[Priština]]
Image:Prizen kosovo.jpg|[[Prizreni]]/[[Prizren]]
Image:Gjakova.jpg|[[Gjakova]]/[[Đakovica]]
Image:French Peugeot P4 dsc06852.jpg|[[KFOR]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== See also ==
* [[History of Kosovo]]
* [[Assembly of Kosovo]]
* [[Government of Kosovo]]
* [[Prime Minister of Kosovo]]
* [[President of Kosovo]]
* [[Post and Telecom of Kosovo]]
* [[Battle of Kosovo|Battle of Kosovo (1389)]]
* [[Subdivisions of Kosovo]]
* [[National awakening and the birth of Albania]]
* [[Demographic history of Kosovo]]
* [[Unrest in Kosovo]] (the unrests of March 2004)
* [[Sexual trafficking in Kosovo]]
* [[Metohija]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

== External links ==
{{sisterlinks|Kosovo}}
* [http://www.balkanforums.com Kosovo and the Balkans] - Discussion Forum
* [http://digital.library.unt.edu/govdocs/crs/search.tkl?q=kosovo&amp;search_crit=fulltext&amp;search=Search&amp;date1=Anytime&amp;date2=Anytime&amp;type=form  Congressional Research Service (CRS) Reports regarding Kosovo]
* {{wikitravel}}
* [http://www.rtklive.com  RTK - Kosova's public television - news in Albanian, Serbian, Turkish and Roma]
* [https://www.osce.org/documents/mik/1999/11/1620_en.pdf Human Rights in Kosovo: As Seen, As Told. Volume I, October 1998 - June 1999].
* [http://www.lib.utexas.edu/maps/kosovo.html Kosovo maps from the Perry-Castañeda Library Map Collection]
* [http://www.kosovakosovo.com/ A source of information reflecting both sides’ claims in the dispute] 
* [http://www.nato.int/kosovo/ KFOR] [[NATO]] led peacekeeping force in Kosovo.
* [http://www.unmikonline.org/ UNMIK] [[UN]] led civilian administration in Kosovo.
* [http://www.chmouel.com/geeklog/gallery/gallery_individual.php/mkosovo/ A collection of photos from Kosovo]
* [http://www.otvoreno.org.yu/ A place where Serbian politicians speak openly of Kosovo issue]
* [http://www.iom.ipko.org/ IOM International Organization for Migration]
* [http://www.crisisgroup.org/home/index.cfm?id=1243&amp;l=1 (ICG)] International Crisis Group, a source of independent analysis on Kosovo issues.

=== Pro-Albanian ===
* [http://BalkanUpdate.blogspot.com Balkan Update]- A blog with news, analysis and the lates updates from Balkans
* [http://www.eciks.org Economic Initiative for Kosovo] - &quot;...latest news, analysis and publications from the Kosovar economy&quot;
* [http://www.albanian.com/main/countries/kosova Albanian.com] - general information
* [http://www.kosovaelire.com/ Kosova e lirë] (Free Kosova) -- Material about Kosovars and Albanians in Albanian language. 
* [http://www.alb-shkenca.org/images/stories/Why%20Independence.pdf Why Independence for Kosovo?] A summary of the case for an independent Kosovo by two Prishtina intellectuals
* [http://www.newkosovo.org/news.htm Alliance for New Kosovo] A policy resource on Kosovo Independence
* [http://www.kosovareport.org/news.htm Kosovareport] A collection of news on Kosovo, in English, gathered from many agencies.
* [http://www.alb-net.com/index.htm Kosova Crisis Center] A collection of articles on Kosovo, in English.
* [http://www.aacl.com/indexmain.html AACL] Albanian American Civic League. 

=== Pro-Serbian ===
* [http://www.srbija.sr.gov.yu/kosovo-metohija/ Serbian Government Kosovo-Metohija site]
* [http://www.kosovo.net/ Kosovo.net] Serbian Orthodox Church's official website on Kosovo
* [http://www.rastko.org.yu/kosovo/crucified/default.htm Account of destroyed Serbian Orthodox churches in Kosovo and Metohija]
* [http://groups.yahoo.com/group/decani/ Kosovo Newsgroup archive]
* [http://www.kc.gov.yu/ Coordination Center of SCG and the Republic of Serbia for Kosovo]
* [http://www.tserkovnost.org/srbija/ Eastern Orthodox Resource Centre]
* [http://www.axisglobe.com/article.asp?article=689 Southern Serbia: The second Kosovo?]
* [http://serbo.blogspot.com Kosovo News blog]
* [http://www.b92.net/english/news/index.php?style=headlines&amp;nav_category=19 B92] Serbian Independent news agency
* [http://www.kosovo.net/sk/history/kosovo_origins/default.htm Hugo Roth, ''Kosovo Origins'']: a historian's comprehensive overview


[[Category:Disputed territories]]
[[Category:Kosovo]]
[[Category:UN_peacekeeping_missions_and_operations]]
[[ar:قوصوة]]
[[ast:Kosovo]]
[[bg:تîٌîâî]]
[[zh-min-nan:Kosovo]]
[[bs:Kosovo]]
[[ca:Kosovo]]
[[cs:Kosovo]]
[[da:Kosovo]]
[[de:Kosovo]]
[[et:Kosovo]]
[[es:Kosovo]]
[[eo:Kosovo]]
[[fr:Kosovo]]
[[ko:코소보]]
[[hr:Kosovo]]
[[id:Kosovo]]
[[it:Kosovo]]
[[he:קוסובו ומטוחיה]]
[[lt:Kosovas]]
[[hu:Koszovó]]
[[mk:Косово]]
[[nl:Kosovo]]
[[nds:Kosovo]]
[[ja:コソボ]]
[[no:Kosovo]]
[[nn:Kosovo]]
[[pl:Kosowo]]
[[pt:Kosovo]]
[[ro:Kosovo]]
[[ru:Косово]]
[[sq:Kosova]]
[[sr:Косово]]
[[fi:Kosovo]]
[[sv:Kosovo]]
[[tr:Kosova]]
[[uk:Косово]]
[[zh:科索沃]]</text>
