      <text xml:space="preserve">{{dablink|For other uses of the name Kosovo, see [[Kosovo (disambiguation)]]. For other uses of the name Kosova, see [[Kosova (disambiguation)]].}}
{{Kosovo-InfoBox}}
&lt;!-- Please be very careful in editing the introduction of this article. The Arbitration Committee has placed this article on probation. If any editor makes disruptive edits, they may be banned by an administrator from this and related articles, or other reasonably related pages. See the talk page for more information. --&gt;
'''Kosovo''' [[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Kosovë'' or ''Kosova''),([[Serbian language|Serbian]]: Косово и Метохија or ''Kosovo i Metohija'', also Космет or ''Kosmet'';  is a province in southern [[Serbia]] which has been under [[United Nations]] [[United Nations Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo|administration]] since [[1999]]. While Serbia's nominal [[sovereignty]] is recognised by the international community, in practice Serbian governance in the province is virtually non-existent (''see also [[Constitutional status of Kosovo]]''). The province is governed by the [[United Nations Mission in Kosovo]] (UNMIK) and the local [[Provisional Institutions of Self-Government]], with security provided by the [[NATO]]-led [[Kosovo Force]] (KFOR). 

Kosovo borders [[Montenegro]], [[Albania]] and the [[Republic of Macedonia]]. The mountainous province's capital and largest city is [[Priština]]. Kosovo has a population of around two million people, predominately ethnic [[Albanians]], with smaller populations of [[Serbs]], [[Turkish people|Turks]], [[Bosniaks]] and other ethnic groups.

The province is the subject of a long-running political and territorial dispute between the Serbian (and previously, the [[Yugoslavia|Yugoslav]]) government and Kosovo's Albanian population. International negotiations began in [[2006]] to determine the final status of Kosovo (''See [[Kosovo Future Status Process]]''). According to the [[news media]], it had been widely expected that the talks would lead to some form of independence.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.economist.com/displaystory.cfm?story_id=4489028 Kosovo's status - the wheels grind on]&quot;, ''The Economist'', October 6, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.economist.com/world/europe/displaystory.cfm?story_id=8115800 A province prepares to depart]&quot;, ''The Economist'', November 2, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/02/world/europe/02kosovo.html?_r=1&amp;adxnnl=1&amp;oref=slogin&amp;ref=world&amp;adxnnlx=1162848637-NqqL4KPuLsP8lqxEzYdhGQ Kosovo May Soon Be Free of Serbia, but Not of Supervision]&quot;, by Nicholas Wood, ''The New York Times'', November 2, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://abcnews.go.com/International/wireStory?id=2665691&amp;CMP=OTC-RSSFeeds0312 Serbia shrinks, and sinks into dejection]&quot;, by WILLIAM J. KOLE, ''The Associated Press'', November 19, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

:''See also [[Names of Kosovo]].''

== Geography ==
''For administrative divisions, see [[Municipalities of Kosovo]]''
[[image:UTkosovo rel small 92.jpg|thumb|left|275px|Physical map of Kosovo.]]
With an area of [[1 E10 m²|10,912]] [[square kilometre]]s (4,213 [[square mile|sq.&amp;nbsp;mi]]) and a population of over two million on the eve of the 1999 crisis, Kosovo borders [[Montenegro]] to the northwest, [[Central Serbia]] to the North and East, the [[Republic of Macedonia]] to the south and [[Albania]] to the southwest. The province's present borders were established in [[1945]]. The republic of [[Serbia]] has one other autonomous province, [[Vojvodina]], located in the far north of the country.

The largest cities are [[Priština]], the capital, with an estimated 600,000 citizens, and [[Prizren]] in the southwest with 120,000 citizens; five other towns have populations in excess of 50,000. The climate in Kosovo is continental with warm summers and cold and snowy winters.

There are two main plains in Kosovo. The [[Metohija]]/Rrafshi i Dukagjinit basin is located in the western part of the province, and the Plain of Kosovo ([[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Rrafshi i Kosovës'', [[Serbian language|Serbian]]: ''Kosovska Dolina'') occupies the central area.

Much of Kosovo's terrain is rugged. The [[Šar Mountain]] is located in the south and south-east, bordering [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]]. It is one of the region's most popular tourist and skiing resorts, with [[Brezovica]] and Prevalac/Prevallë as the main tourist centres. Kosovo's mountainous area, including the highest peak Deravica/Gjeravica (2656 m above sea level), is located in the south-west, bordering [[Albania]] and [[Montenegro]]. 

The mountain range dividing Kosovo from Albania is known in English as the [[Prokletije|Cursed Mountains]] or Albanian Alps (Alb: ''Bjeshkët e Nemuna'', Ser: ''Prokletije''). The Kopaonik mountain is located in the north, bordering [[Central Serbia]]. The central region of [[Drenica]], Carraleva/Crnoljevo and the eastern part of Kosovo, known as Gallap/Golak, are mainly hilly areas. 

There are several notable rivers and lakes in Kosovo. The main rivers are the [[White Drin]] -several other waterways flow into it, including the [[Erenik]], and the river runs towards the [[Adriatic Sea]]-, [[Sitnica]], [[South Morava]] in the [[Goljak]] area and [[Ibar River|Ibar]] in the north. The main lakes are [[Badovc]] in the north-east and [[Gazivoda]] in the north-western part.

== History ==
{{History of Kosovo}}
{{main|History of Kosovo}}
=== Ancient ===
The region was certainly inhabited in [[prehistory|prehistoric]] times, it appears, by two different cultures: [[Bronze Age|Bronze]] and [[Iron Age]] [[tomb]]s have been found only in [[Metohia]], and not in other parts of Kosovo.&lt;ref name=Jankovic&gt;[[Djordje Janković]]: [http://www.rastko.org.yu/kosovo/istorija/malkolm/djankovic-facts.html Middle Ages in Noel Malcolm's &quot;Kosovo. A Short History&quot; and Real Facts]&lt;/ref&gt; After the [[Proto-Indo-Europeans|Indo-European invasion]], Kosovo became inhabited by [[Illyria]]n and [[Thracian]] tribes, such as the [[Dardani]] and the [[Triballi]]; the territory of today's province was a part of [[Dardania (Europe)|Dardania]]. Its south was ruled by [[Macedon]] since [[Alexander the Great]]'s reign in the [[4th century BC]]. Illyrians resisted rule by the [[Greeks]] and [[Ancient Rome|Romans]] for centuries but after the long periods of conflict between Illyrian tribes and invading empires, the region was eventually occupied by the [[Roman Empire]] under Emperor [[Augustus]] in [[28 BC]]; it is not clear whether it was part of the province of [[Moesia]] or was divided between [[Dalmatia]] and Moesia (a view which is supported by some archaeological evidence).&lt;ref name=Jankovic/&gt; Emperor [[Diocletian]] later (c. [[284]]) made Dardania into a separate province with its capital at [[Naissus]] ([[Niš]]). When the Roman Empire split in [[Anno Domini|A.D.]] [[395]], the area came under the [[Byzantine Empire|Eastern Roman Empire]], the [[Byzantine Empire]]. Many inhabitants of Dardania became leaders in Rome and [[Constantinopolis]], including [[Justinian the Great]].

=== Medieval ===
==== Great Migrations and Interregnums ====
[[Serbs]] came to the territories that form modern Kosovo in the [[7th century|7th centuries]] migrations of [[White Serbs]] under the [[Unknown Archont]], with the largest influx of migrants in the 630s; although the region was increasingly populated by Slavs since the 6th or even 5th century. These Slavs were [[Christianization|Christianized]] in several waves between the [[7th century|7th]] and [[9th century]], with the last wave taking place between [[867]] and [[874]]. The northwestern part of Kosovo, [[Hvosno]], became a part of the Byzantine [[Serb]] vassal state the [[Principality of Rascia]], with [[Desnik|Dostinik]] as the principality's capital.

In the late 800s, the whole of Kosovo was seized by the [[First Bulgarian Empire]]. Although [[Serbia]] restored control over [[Metohija]] throughout the 10th century, the rest of Kosovo was returned to the Byzantine Empire in a period of Bulgarian decline. However, Tsar [[Samuil of Bulgaria]] reconquered the whole of Kosovo in the late 10th century until the Byzantines restored their control over the area as they subjugated the Bulgarian Empire. In 1040-1041, Bulgarians, led by the Samuil of Bulgaria's grandson Petar Delyan staged a rebellion against the Eastern Roman Empire that temporarily encompassed Kosovo. After the rebellion was crushed, the Byzantine control over the region continued. 

Throughout the following decades, numerous foreign peoples invading the Byzantine Empire stormed Kosovo, among them the [[Cumans]]. 

In 1072, local Bulgarians, under George Voiteh, pushed a final attempt to restore Imperial Bulgarian power and invited the last heir of the [[House of Comitopuli]] - [[Duklja]]'s prince [[Constantine Bodin (Peter III)|Konstantin Bodin]] of the [[House of Vojislavljevic]], son of the [[List of Serbian rulers|Serbian King]] [[Mihailo Voislav]] - to assume power. The Serbs decided to conquer the entire Byzantine region of Bulgaria. King Mihailo dispatched his son with 300 elite Serb fighters led by Duke Petrilo. Constantine Bodin was crowned in [[Prizren]] as ''Petar III'', [[List of Bulgarian monarchs|Tsar of the Bulgarians]] by Goerge Voiteh and the Slavic Boyars. The Empire swept across Byzantine territories in months, until the significant losses on the south had forced Czar Petar to withdraw. In 1073, the Byzantine forces chased Constantine Bodin, defeated his army at [[Pauni]], and imprisoned him.

==== Incorporation into Serbia ====
The full Serbian takeover was carried out under a branch of the [[House of Vojislavljević|House of Voislav]] [[Grand Prince]]s of [[Rascia]]. In [[1093]], Prince Vukan advanced on [[Lipljan]], burned it down and raided the neighbouring areas. The Byzantine Emperor himself came to [[Zvečan]] for negotiations. Zvečan served as the Byzantine line-of-defence against constant invasions from the neighboring Serbs. A peace agreement was made, but Vukan broke it and defeated the army of John Comnenus, the Emperor's nephew. Vukan's armies stormed Kosovo. In [[1094]], [[Alexius I Comnenus|Byzantine Emperor Alexius]] attempted to renew peace negotiations in Ulpiana. A new peace agreement was concluded and Vukan handed over hostages to the Emperor, including his two nephews Uroš and Stefan Vukan. Prince Vukan renewed the conflict in [[1106]], once again defeating John Comnenus' army. However, his death halted the total Serb conquest of Kosovo.

In [[1166]], a Serbian nobleman from [[Zeta (state)|Zeta]], [[Stefan Nemanja]], the founder of the [[Nemanjić|House of Nemanja]] ascended to the Rascian Grand Princely throne and conquered most of Kosovo, in an uprising against the Byzantine Emperor [[Manuel I Comnenus]]. He defeated the previous Grand Prince of Rascia Tihomir's army at Pantino, near Pauni. Tihomir, who was Stefan's brother, was drowned in the [[Sitnica]] river. Stefan was eventually defeated and had to return some of his conquests. He pledged to the Emperor that he would not renew hostilies, but in [[1183]], Stefan Nemanja embarked on a new offensive with the [[Hungarians]] after the death of [[Manuel I Comnenus]] in [[1180]], marking the end of Byzantine domination of Kosovo.

Nemanja's son, [[Stefan Prvovenčani|Stefan II]], recorded that the border of the Serbian realm reached the river of Lab. Grand Prince Stephen II completed the inclusion of the Kosovo territories under Serb rule in 1208, by which time he had conquered Prizren and Lipljan, and moved the border of territory under his control to the Šar mountain.

==== Kingdom of the Serbs ====
In [[1217]], the [[History of Serbia|Serbian Kingdom]] achieved recognition. In [[1219]], an autocephalous [[Serbian Orthodox Church]] was created, with [[Hvosno]], Prizren and Lipljan being the Orthodox Christian [[Episcopates]] on Kosovo. By the end of the [[13th century]], the centre of the [[Serbian Orthodox Church|Serbian Church]] was moved to [[Peć]] from [[Žiča]].

In the 13th century, Kosovo became the heart of the Serbian political and religious life, with the Šar mountain becoming the political center of the Serbian rulers. The main chatteu was in Pauni. On an island was [[Svrčin]], and on the coast [[Štimlji]], and in the mountains was the Castle of [[Nerodimlje]]. The Complexes were used for counciling, crowning of rulers, negotiating, and as the rulers' living quarters. After 1291, the Tartars broke all the way to Peć. [[List of Serbian rulers|Serbian King]] [[Stefan Milutin]] managed to defeat them and then chase them further. He raised the Temple of the [[Mother of Christ]] of Ljeviška in Prizren around 1307, which became the seat of the Prizren Episcopric, and the magnificent [[Gračanica]] in 1335, the seat of the Lipljan Episcopric. In 1331, Juvenille King Dušan attacked his father, Serbian King Stefan of Dechani at his castle in Nerodimlje. King Stefan closed in his neighbouring fortress of [[Petrič]], but Dušan captured him and closed him with his second wife Maria Palailogos and their children in Zvečan, where the dethroned King died on [[11 November]] [[1331]].

In 1327 and 1328, Serbian King Stefan of Dechani started forming the vast Dečani domain, although, Serbian King Dušan would finish it in 1335. Stefan of Dechani issued the Dechani Charter in 1330, listing every single citizen in every household under the Church Land's demesne.

==== Serbian Empire and Despotate ====
[[Monarch|King]] [[Stefan Dušan]] founded the vast Monastery of Saint Archaengel near Prizren in [[1342]]-[[1352]]. The Kingdom was transformed into an [[Serbian Empire|Empire]] in 1345 and officially in 1346. Stefan Dušan received [[John VI Cantacuzenus]] in [[1342]] in his Castle in [[Pauni]] to discuss a joint War against the Byzantine Emperor. In [[1346]], the Serbian [[Archbishopric|Archepiscopric]] at Peć was upgraded into a [[Patriarchate]], but it was not recognized before [[1370]]. 

After the Empire fell into disarray prior to Dušan's death in [[1355]], feudal anarchy caught up with the country during the reign of Tsar [[Stefan Uroš V]]. Kosovo became a domain of the [[Vukašin Mrnjavčević|House of Mrnjavčević]], but Prince Voislav Voinović expanded his demesne further into Kosovo. The armies of King [[Vukašin Mrnjavčević]] from [[Pristina]] and his allies defeated Voislav's forces in [[1369]], putting a halt to his advances. After the [[Battle of Marica]] on [[26 September]] [[1371]], in which the Mrnjavčević brothers lost their lives, [[House of Balšić|Đurađ I Balšić]] of [[Zeta (state)|Zeta]] took Prizren and Peć in [[1372]]. A part of Kosovo became the demesne of the [[Prince Lazar|House of Lazarević]].

The [[Ottoman Empire|Ottomans]] invaded and met the Christian coalition of Serbs, Albanians and Vlahcs under [[Prince Lazar]] on [[28 June]] [[1389]], near [[Pristina]], at Gazi Mestan. The Serbian Army was assisted by various allies. The epic [[Battle of Kosovo]] followed, in which Prince Lazar himself lost his life. Prince Lazar amassed 70,000 men on the battlefield and the Ottomans had 140,000. Through the cunning of [[Miloš Obilić]], [[Sultan]] [[Murad I|Murad]] was murdered and the new Sultan [[Beyazid]] had, despite winning the battle, to retreat to consolidate his power. The Ottoman Sultan was buried with one of his sons at Gazi Mestan. Both [[Prince Lazar]] and [[Miloš Obilić]] were canonised by the [[Serbian Orthodox Church]] for their efforts in the battle. The local House of [[Vuk Branković|Branković]] came to prominence as the local lords of Kosovo, under [[Vuk Branković]], with the temporary fall of the [[History of Serbia|Serbian Despotate]] in [[1439]]. Another great battle occurred between the Hungarian troops supported by the Albanian ruler Gjergj Kastrioti [[Skanderbeg]] on one side, and Ottoman troops supported by the [[House of Branković|Branković]]s in [[1448]]. Skanderbeg's troops that were going to help John Hunyadi were stopped by the Branković's troops, who was more or less a Turkish [[Vassal]]. Hungarian King [[John Hunyadi]] lost the battle after a 2-day fight, but essentially stopped the Ottoman advance northwards. Kosovo then became vassalaged to the Ottoman Empire, until its direct incorporation after the final fall of Serbia in 1459. 

In 1455, new castles rose to prominence in Priština and [[Vučitrn]], centres of the Ottoman vassalaged House of Branković.

=== Ottoman rule ===
{{POV-check}}
{{main|Kosovo Province, Ottoman Empire}}
The [[Ottoman Empire|Ottomans]] brought [[Islamisation]] with them, particularly in towns, and later also created the [[Kosovo Province, Ottoman Empire|Vilayet of Kosovo]] as one of the Ottoman territorial entities. This brought a great shift, as the Orthodox Serb population began to lose its majority when large numbers of [[Turkic peoples|Turks]] and [[Albanians]] moved to Kosovo. During the Islamisation, many Churches and Holy Orthodox Christian places were destroyed or turned into Mosques. The big Monastery of Saint Archangel near Prizren was torn down at the end of the 16th century and the material used to build the Mosque of Sinan-pasha, an Islamized Serb, in Prizren. Although the [[Serbian Orthodox Church]] was officially abolished in 1532, an Islamized Serb from Bosnia, Vizier [[Mehmed-pasha Sokolović]] influenced the restoration of the [[Patriarchate of Peć]] in 1557. Special privileges were provided, which helped the survival of Serbs and other Christians in Kosovo. 

Kosovo was taken by the Austrian forces during the [[Great Turkish War#War of the Holy League (1683–1699)|Great War of 1683-1699]] with help of 5,000 Albanians and their leader, a [[Catholic Archibishop]] [[Pjetër Bogdani]]. The archbishop died of plague during the war, and his grave was later reopened, with his body scattered and given to the dogs by the Ottomans because of his role in the rebellion. In [[1690]], the [[Serbian Patriarch of Peć]] [[Arsenije III Čarnojević]], who previously escaped a certain death, led 37,000 families from Kosovo, to evade [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] wrath since Kosovo had just been retaken by the Ottomans. The people that followed him were mostly [[Serbs]] – 20,000 Serbs abandoned [[Prizren]] alone - but they were likely followed by other ethnic groups. Due to the oppression from the Ottomans, other migrations of Orthodox people from the Kosovo area continued throughout the [[18th century]]. It is also noted that some [[Serbs]] adopted [[Islam]], while some even gradually fused with other groups, predominantly Albanians, adopting their culture and even language. By the end of the 19th century, [[Albanians]] replaced the Serbs as the dominating nation of Kosovo.

In 1766, the Ottomans abolished the [[Patriarchate of Peć]] and the position of [[Christians]] in Kosovo was greatly reduced. All previous privileges were lost, and the Christian population had to suffer the full weight of the Empire's extensive and losing wars, even having blame forced upon them for the losses.

=== Modern ===
{{Copyedit|date=February 2007}}
In 1871, a massive Serbian meeting was held in Prizren at which the possible retaking and reintegration of Kosovo and the rest of &quot;Old Serbia&quot; was discussed, as the [[History of Serbia|Principality of Serbia]] itself had already made plans for expansions towards Ottoman territory.

Albanian refugees from the territories conquered in the [[1876]]-[[1877]] Serbo-Turkish war and the [[1877]]-[[1878]] Russo-Turkish war are now known as '[[muhajir (Albania)|muhaxher]]' (which means 'refugee', from [[Arabic]] [[muhajir]]). Their descendents still have the same surname, ''Muhaxheri''. It is estimated that 200,000 to 400,000 Serbs were cleansed out of the [[Vilayet of Kosovo]] between [[1876]] and [[1912]], especially during the [[Greco-Turkish War (1897)|Greek-Ottoman War]] in [[1897]]. 

In 1878, a Peace Accord was drawn that left the cities of Priština and [[Kosovska Mitrovica]] under civil Serbian control,  and outside the juristiction of the Ottoman authorities, while the rest of Kosovo would be under Ottoman control. As a response, the Albanians formed the nationalistic and conservative [[League of Prizren]] in [[Prizren]] later the same year. Over 300 Albanian leaders from Kosovo and western Macedonia gathered and discussed the urgent issues concerning protection of Albanian populated regions from division among neighbouring countries. The League was supported by the Ottoman Sultan because of its Pan-Islamic ideology and political aspirations of a [[Greater Albania|unified Albanian people]] under the Ottoman umbrella. The movement gradually became anti-Christian and spread great anxiety among Christian Albanians and especially among Christian Serbs. As a result, more and more Serbs left Kosovo northwards. Serbia complained to the World Powers that the promised territories were not being held{{huh}} because the Ottomans were hesitating to do that. The World Powers put pressure on the Ottomans and in 1881, the Ottoman Army began fighting the Albanian forces. The Prizren League created a Provisional Government with a President, Prime Minister (Ymer Prizreni) and Ministries of War (Sylejman Vokshi) and Foreign Ministry (Abdyl Frashëri). After three years of war, the Albanians were defeated. Many of the leaders were executed and imprisoned. The subsequent Treaty of San Stefano in 1878 restored most Albanian lands to Ottoman control, but the Serbian forces had to retreat from Kosovo along with some Serbs that were expelled as well{{Fact|date=February 2007}}. 

In 1908, the Sultan brought a new democratic decrete that was valid only for Turkish-speakers. As the vast majority of Kosovo spoke Albanian or Serbian, the Kosovar population was very unhappy. The Young Turk movement supported a centralist rule and opposed any sort of autonomy desired by Kosovars, and particularely the Albanians. In 1910, an [[Albanian]] uprising spread from Priština and lasted until the Ottoman Sultan's visit to Kosovo in June of 1911. The Aim of the League of Prizren was to unite the four Albanian Vilayets by merging the majority of Albanian inhabitants within the Ottoman Empire into one Albanian State. However, at that time Serbs have consisted about 40% of the whole Vilayt of Kosovo's overall population and were opposing the Albanian nationalism along with Turks and other Slavs in Kosovo, which disabled the Albanian movements to occupy Kosovo. 

:''See also: [[Serbia in WWI]]''

In [[1912]] during the [[Balkan Wars]], most of Kosovo was taken by the [[History of Serbia|Kingdom of Serbia]], while the region of [[Metohija]] ([[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Dukagjini Valley'') was taken by the [[History of Montenegro|Kingdom of Montenegro]]. An exodus of the local Albanian population occurred. This is best described by [[Leon Trotsky]], who was a reporter for the 'Pravda' newspaper at the time. The Serbian authorities planned a recolonization of Kosovo.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.elsie.de/pdf/B2002GatheringClouds.pdf Elsie, R. (ed.) (2002): ''Gathering Clouds. The roots of ethnic cleansing in Kosovo. Early twentieth-century documents''. Dukagjini Balkan Books, Peja (Kosovo, Serbia). ISBN 9951-05-016-6&lt;/ref&gt; Numerous colonist Serb families moved-in to Kosovo, equalizing the demographic balance between Albanians and Serbs. Many Albanians fled into the mountains and numerous Albanian and Turkish houses were razed. The reconquest of Kosovo was noted as a vengeance for the 1389 [[Battle of Kossovo]]. At the Conference of Ambassadors in London in 1912 presided over by Sir Edward Grey, the British Foreign Secretary, the Kingdoms of Serbia and Montenegro were acknowledged sovereignty over Kosovo. 

&lt;!-- removed unlicensed image [[Image:1Serbian_army_retreat_WW1.jpg|thumb|left|Serbian army retreat]] --&gt;
In the winter of [[1915]]-[[1916]] during [[World War I]] Kosovo saw a large exodus of Serbian army which became known as the ''Great Serbian Retreat''. Defeated and worn out in battles against Austro-Hungarians, they had no other choice than to retreat, as Kosovo was occupied by [[Third Bulgarian Empire|Bulgarians]] and [[Austro-Hungarians]]. The Albanians joined and supported the [[Central Powers]]. As opposed to Serbian schools, numerous Albanian schools were opened during the 'occupation' (the majority Albanian population considered it a liberation). Allied ships were awaiting for Serbian people and soldiers at the banks of the Adriatic sea and the path leading them there went across Kosovo and Albania. Tens of thousands of soldiers have died of starvation, extreme weather and Albanian reprisals as they were approaching the [[Allies]] in [[Corfu]] and [[Thessaloniki]], amassing a total of 100,000 dead retreaters.{{Fact|date=February 2007}} Transported away from the front lines, Serbian army managed to heal many wounded and ill soldiers and get some rest. Refreshed and regrouped, it decided to return to the battlefield. In 1918 the Serbian Army pushed the [[Central Powers]] out of Kosovo. During their re-occupation of Kosovo, the Serbian Army committed atrocities against the population in revenge. Serbian Kosovo was unified with Montengrin as Montenegro subsequently joined the Kingdom of Serbia. After the World War I ended, the Monarchy was then transformed into the [[Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenians]] ''(&quot;Mbretëria Serbe, Kroate, Sllovene&quot; in Albanian, &quot; &quot;Kraljevina Srba, Hrvata i Slovenaca&quot; in Serbo-Croatian)'' on '''[[1 December]] [[1918]]''', gathering territories gained in victory. 

==== Kingdom of Yugoslavia and WWII ====
The 1918-1929 period of the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenians witnessed a rise of the Serbian population in the region and a decline in the non-Serbian. In the Kingdom Kosovo was split onto four counties - three being a part of the entity of Serbia: Zvečan, Kosovo and southern Metohija; and one of Montenegro: northern Metohija. However, the new administration system since [[26 April]] [[1922]] split Kosovo among three Areas of the Kingdom: Kosovo, [[Rascia]] and [[Zeta]]. In 1921 the Albanian elite lodged an official protest of the government to the League of Nations, claiming that 12,000 Albanians had been killed and over 22,000 imprisoned since 1918 and seeking a [[Greater Albania|unification of Albanian-populated lands]]. The League of Nations did not respond, as the appeal was found unfounded. As a result, an armed ''Kachak'' resistance movement was formed whose main goal was to unite Albanian-populated areas of the Kingdom to Albania. 

In 1929 the Kingdom was transformed into the [[Kingdom of Yugoslavia]] which the ''[[Yugoslavs|Yugoslav]]'' nationality unifying all Kosovan [[Slavs]]. The territories of Kosovo were split among the [[Zeta Banovina|Banate of Zeta]], the [[Morava Banovina|Banate of Morava]] and the [[Vardar Banovina|Banate of Vardar]]. The Kingdom lasted until the [[World War II]] [[Axis powers|Axis]] invasion of 1941. 

The greatest part of Kosovo became a part of [[Italy|Italian]]-controlled [[Greater Albania|Fascist Albania]], and smaller bits by the [[Nazism|Nazi]]-[[Fascist]] [[Greater Bulgaria|Tsardom of Bulgaria]] and [[Nazism|Nazi]] [[Germany|German]]-occupied [[Serbia|Kingdom of Serbia]]. Since the Albanian Fascist political leadership had decided in the [[Conference of Bujan]] that Kosovo would remain a part of Albania they started an ethnic cleansing campaign of the non-Albanian population in the Kosovo.{{Fact|date=February 2007}} The infamous [[21st Waffen Mountain Division of the SS Skanderbeg (1st Albanian)|SS Division Skanderbeg]] committed crimes. {{Fact|date=February 2007}}. Tens of thousands of Serbs lost their lives and around 75,000 Serbs fled Kosovo during the war.{{Fact|date=February 2007}} Hundreds of thousands more would leave in the following decades, following the shift of power in Kosovo. {{Fact|date=February 2007}}

Prior to the surrender of [[History of Italy|Fascist Italy]] in [[1943]], the German forces took over direct control of the region. After numerous uprisings of [[Serbs|Serbian]] [[Chetniks]] and [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Yugoslav]] [[Partisans]], the latter being lead by [[Fadil Hoxha]], Kosovo was liberated after [[1944]] with the help of the Albanian partisans of the [[Comintern]], and became a province of [[Serbia]] within the [[Yugoslavia|Democratic Federal Yugoslavia]].

==== Kosovo in the second Yugoslavia ====
The province was first formed in 1945 as the Autonomous Kosovo-Metohian Area to protect{{Fact|date=February 2007}} its regional [[Albanians|Albanian]] majority within the [[History of Serbia|People's Republic of Serbia]] as a member of the [[SFRJ|Federal People's Republic of Yugoslavia]] under the leadership of the former Partisan leader, [[Josip Broz Tito]], but with no factual autonomy. After Yugoslavia's name change to the [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia]] and Serbia's to the [[History of Serbia|Socialist Republic of Serbia]] in [[1953]], Kosovo gained inner autonomy in the 1960s. In the [[1974]] constitution, the Socialist Autonomous Province of Kosovo's government received higher powers, including the highest governmental titles — President and Premier and a seat in the Federal Presidency which made it a ''de facto'' Socialist Republic within the Federation, but remaining as a Socialist Autonomous Province within the Socialist Republic of Serbia. [[Serbo-Croatian]] and [[Albanian language|Albanian]] were defined as official languages on the provincial level marking the two largest linguistic Kosovan groups: Albanians and Serbs. In the 1970s, an Albanian nationalist movement pursued full recognition of the Province of Kosovo as another Republic within the Federation, while the most extreme elements aimed for full-scale independence. Tito's arbitrary regime dealt with the situation swiftly, but only giving it a temporary solution. The ethnic balance of Kosovo witnessed unproportional increase as the number of [[Albanians]] tripled gradually rising from almost 65% to over 80%, but the number of [[Serbs]] barely increased and dropped in the full share of the total population from some 25% down to 10%.

Beginning in March [[1981]], Kosovar Albanian students organized protests seeking that Kosovo become a republic within Yugoslavia. Those protests rapidly escalated into violent riots &quot;involving 20,000 people in six cities&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt19810419&quot;&gt;New York Times 1981-04-19, &quot;One Storm has Passed but Others are Gathering in Yugoslavia&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; that were harshly contained by the Yugoslav government. During the 1980s, ethnic tensions continued with frequent violent outbreaks against Serbs and Yugoslav state authorities resulting in increased emigration of Kosovo Serbs and other ethnic groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;reuters19860527&quot;&gt;Reuters 1986-05-27, &quot;Kosovo Province Revives Yugoslavia's Ethnic Nightmare&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;csm19860728&quot;&gt;Christian Science Monitor 1986-07-28, &quot;Tensions among ethnic groups in Yugoslavia begin to boil over&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The Yugoslav leadership tried to suppress protests of Kosovo Serbs seeking protection from ethnic discrimination and violence.&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt19870627&quot;&gt;New York Times 1987-06-27, &quot;Belgrade Battles Kosovo Serbs&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[1986]], the Serbian Academy of Sciences and Arts (SANU) was working on a document which later would be known as the [[SANU Memorandum]], a warning to the Serbian President and Assembly of the existing crisis and where it would lead. An unfinished edition was filtered to the press. In the essay, SANU criticised the state of Yugoslavia and made remarks that the only member state contributing at the time to the development of Kosovo and Macedonia (by then, the poorest territories of the Federation) was Serbia. According to SANU, Yugoslavia was suffering of ethnic strives and the disintegration of the Yugoslav economy into separate economic sectors and territories, which was transforming the federal state into a loose confederation.&lt;ref&gt;SANU (1986): [http://www.balkan-archive.org.yu/kosta/memorandum/contents.html Serbian Academy of Sciences and Arts Memorandum]. GIP Kultura. Belgrade.&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, some think that [[Slobodan Milošević]] used the discontent reflected in the SANU memorandum for his own political goals, during his rise to power in [[Serbia]] at the time.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.opendemocracy.net/articles/ViewPopUpArticle.jsp?id=2&amp;articleId=3361 Julie A Mertus: &quot;Slobodan Milošević: Myth and Responsibility&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

By the end of the 1980s, calls for increased federal control in the crisis-torn autonomous province were getting louder. [[Slobodan Milošević]] pushed for constitutional change amounting to suspension of autonomy for both Kosovo and [[Vojvodina]].&lt;ref name=&quot;reuters19880730&quot;&gt;Reuters 1988-07-30, &quot;Yugoslav Leaders Call for Control in Kosovo, Protests Loom&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Kosovo and the Breakup of Yugoslavia ====

Inter-ethnic tensions continued to worsen in Kosovo throughout the 1980s. In particular, Kosovo's ethnic Serb community, a minority of Kosovo population, complained about mistreatment from the Albanian majority.  Milosevic capitalized on this discontent to consolidate his own position in Serbia.  In 1987, Serbian President Ivan Stambolic sent Milošević to Kosovo to &quot;pacify restive Serbs in Kosovo.&quot; On that trip, Milošević broke away from a meeting with ethnic Albanians to mingle with angry Serbians in a suburb of Pristina. As the Serbs protested they were being pushed back by police with batons, Milošević told them, &quot;No one is allowed to beat you.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cnn.com/SPECIALS/2000/kosovo/stories/past/milosevic/&lt;/ref&gt;  This incident was later seen as pivotal to Milosevic's rise to power.

On June 28, 1989, Milosevic delivered a speech in front of a large number of Serb citizens at the main celebration marking the 600th anniversary of the [[Battle of Kosovo]], held at [[Gazimestan]]. This speech was widely interpreted as being a pivotal moment in Milosevic's rise to power.

In 1989, Milošević, employing a mix of intimidation and political maneuvering, drastically reduced Kosovo's special autonomous status within Serbia.  Soon thereafter Kosovo Albanians organized a non-violent separatist movement, employing widespread civil disobedience, with the ultimate goal of achieving the independence of Kosovo.  Kosovo Albanians boycotted state institutions and elections and established separate Albanian schools and political institutions. On [[July 2]], [[1990]] an unconstitutional Kosovo parliament declared Kosovo an independent country, although this was not recognized by Belgrade or any foreign states. Two years later, in 1992, the parliament organized an unofficial referendum which was observed by international organizations but was not recognized internationally. With an ''80%'' turnout, ''98%'' voted for Kosovo to be independent.

==== Kosovo War ====
{{main|Kosovo War}}

In 1995, as the issues that sparked wars in [[Bosnia and Herzegovina|Bosnia]] and [[Croatia]] were largely addressed in the Dayton peace agreement, the Kosovo situation remained without resolution.  As Kosovo Albanian complaints over Serb oppression mounted, an armed resistance movement led by the [[Kosovo Liberation Army]] (KLA) began to employ guerilla-style tactics against Serbian security forces. Violence escalated dramatically in 1998 through a cycle of KLA attacks and Serbian reprisals.  Both sides sometimes targeted civilians.

In the fall of 1998, as the violence worsened and displaced more people, representatives of the international community brokered a ceasefire.  Under an agreement negotiated by [[Richard Holbrooke]], observers from the [[OSCE]] moved into Kosovo to monitor the ceasefire, while Yugoslav military forces partly pulled out of Kosovo. 

But the ceasefire did not hold and new violence erupted over the winter.  On January 16, 1999, the bodies of 45 Albanians were found in the village of [[Racak]].  OSCE monitors alleged they were the victims of a massacre by Serb forces.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/1812847.stm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hrw.org/press/1999/jan/yugo0129.htm&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Racak incident]] in particular brought new international attention to the conflict in Kosovo. 

Within weeks, representatives of Russia, the European Union and the United States convened a conference in [[Rambouillet]], France, to seek a way to end the violence. A draft agreement was prepared (the &quot;[[Rambouillet Accords]]&quot;) that would have resulted in a NATO peacekeeping force deployed to Kosovo and the establishment of meaningful autonomy in Kosovo; the agreement also would have led to an international conference in three years to resolve the issue of Kosovo's status.  After more than a month of talks, Yugoslavia refused to sign an agreement.  Kosovo Albanians, after initially rejecting the accords because they did not promise immediate independence, eventually agreed.

Largely as a result of the failure of the Raimbouillet conference, NATO launched a 78-day [[NATO]] aerial bombing campaign in the spring of [[1999]] with the announced goal of compelling Milosevic to withdraw his forces from Kosovo.  Milosevic capitulated in June 1999, agreeing to the full withdrawal of all security forces from Kosovo.  

During the conflict roughly a million ethnic Albanians fled Kosovo, several thousand were killed (the numbers and the ethnic distribution of the casualties are uncertain and highly disputed). An estimated 10,000-12,000 ethnic Albanians and 3,000 Serbs are believed to have been killed during the conflict. Some 3,000 people are still missing, of which 2,500 are Albanian, 400 Serbs and 100 Roma.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/781310.stm&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Kosovo After the War ====

After the war ended, the UN Security Council passed Resolution 1244 that placed Kosovo under transitional UN administration ([[UNMIK]]) and authorized [[Kosovo Force|KFOR]], a NATO-led peacekeeping force.  Almost immediately returning Kosovo Albanians began to attack the remaining Kosovo Serbs, causing large numbers of Serbs and other non-Albanians to flee. The number of registered refugees is around 250,000&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20040203102745/http://www.serbia.sr.gov.yu/coordination_centre/index.html Coordination Centre of Federal Republic of Yugoslavia and Republic of Serbia for Kosovo and Metohija]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[UNHCR]]: 2002 Annual Statistical Report: Serbia and Montenegro, pg. 9&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[U.S. Committee for Refugees and Immigrants]]: [http://www.refugees.org/countryreports.aspx?id=1624 Country report: Serbia and Montenegro 2006].&lt;/ref&gt; though it is possible that the actual number of refugees is far{{dubious}} smaller; subsequent international{{dubious}} studies have put the number at as few as 65,000. &lt;ref&gt;UNHCR, Critical Appraisal of Responsee Mechanisms Operating in Kosovo for Minority Returns, Pristina, February 2004, p. 14&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.esiweb.org/index.php?lang=en&amp;id=156&amp;document_ID=53]&lt;/ref&gt;  Many displaced Serbs are afraid to return to their homes, even with [[UNMIK]] protection.  Around 120,000 Serbs remain in Kosovo, but are subject to ongoing harassment and discrimination.

In 2001, UNMIK promulgated a Constitutional Framework or Kosovo that established the [[Provisional Institutions of Self-Government]] (PISG), including an elected Kosovo Assembly, Presidency and office of Prime Minister.  Kosovo held its first free, Kosovo-wide elections in late 2001 (municipal elections had been held the previous year).  UNMIK oversaw the establishment of a professional, multi-ethnic Kosovo Police Service.  

In March 2004, Kosovo experienced its worst inter-ethnic violence since the Kosovo War.  The [[2004 unrest in Kosovo|unrest in 2004]] was sparked by a series of minor events that soon cascaded into large-scale riots.  Kosovo Albanians mobs burned hundreds of Serbian houses, Serbian Orthodox Church sites (including some medieval churches and monasteries) and UN facilities for which no albanians were punished.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=International Religious Freedom Report 2005|publisher=US Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labour|url=http://belgrade.usembassy.gov/policy/reports/051108.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Kosovo Politics and Governance ==
&lt;!--Please add new information into relevant articles of the series--&gt;
{{morepolitics|country=Kosovo}}
:''see also [[United Nations Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo]] (UNMIK) and [[Provisional Institutions of Self-Government]] (PISG)''
{{Politics of Kosovo}}
UN Security Council Resolution 1244 placed Kosovo under transitional UN administration pending a determination of Kosovo's future status.  This Resolution entrusted UNMIK with sweeping powers to govern Kosovo, but also directed UNMIK to establish interim institutions of self-governance.  Resolution 1244 permits Serbia no role in governing Kosovo and since 1999 Serbian laws and institutions have not been valid in Kosovo.  NATO has a separate mandate to provide for a safe and secure environment.

In May 2001, UNMIK promulgated the Constitutional Framework, which established Kosovo's Provisional Institutions of Self-Government (PISG).  Since 2001, UNMIK has been gradually transferring increased governing competencies to the PISG, while reserving some powers that are normally carried out by sovereign states (e.g., foreign affairs).  Kosovo has also established municipal government and an internationally-supervised Kosovo Police Service.

According to the Constitutional Framework, Kosovo shall have a 120-member Kosovo Assembly.  The Assembly includes twenty reserved seats: ten for Kosovo Serbs and ten for non-Serb minorities (e.g., Bosniak, Roma, etc.).  The Kosovo Assembly is responsible for electing a President and Prime Minister of Kosovo.  

The largest political party in Kosovo, the Democratic League of Kosovo (LDK), has its origins in the 1990s non-violent resistance movement to Milosevic's rule.  The party was led by Ibrahim Rugova until his death in 2006.  The two next largest parties have their roots in the Kosovo Liberation Army (KLA): the Democratic Party of Kosovo (PDK) led by former KLA leader Hashim Thaci and the Alliance for the Future of Kosovo (AAK) led by former KLA commander Ramush Haradinaj.  Kosovo publisher Veton Surroi formed his own political party in 2004 named &quot;Ora.&quot;  Kosovo Serbs formed the Serb List for Kosovo and Metohija (SLKM) in 2004, but have boycotted Kosovo's institutions and never taken their seats in the Kosovo Assembly.  

In November 2001, the [[OSCE]] supervised the first elections for the Kosovo Assembly.  After that election, Kosovo's political parties formed an all-party unity coalition and elected [[Ibrahim Rugova]] as President and Bajram Rexhepi (PDK) as Prime Minister.  

After Kosovo-wide elections in October 2004, the LDK and AAK formed a new governing coalition that did not include PDK and Ora.  This coalition agreement resulted in [[Ramush Haradinaj]] (AAK) becoming Prime Minister, while Ibrahim Rugova retained the position of President.  PDK and Ora were critical of the coalition agreement and have since frequently accused the current government of corruption.  

Ramush Haradinaj resigned the post of Prime Minister after he was indicted for war crimes by the International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia (ICTY) in March 2005.  He was replaced by Bajram Kosumi (AAK).  But in a political shake-up after the death of President Rugova in January 2006, Kosumi himself was replaced by former Kosovo Protection Corps commander [[Agim Ceku]].  Ceku has won recognition for his outreach to minorities, but Serbia has been critical of his wartime past as military leader of the KLA and claims he is still not doing enough for Kosovo Serbs.  The Kosovo Assembly elected [[Fatmir Sejdiu]], a former LDK parliamentarian, president after Rugova's death. Slaviša Petkovic, Minister for Communities and Returns, was previously the only ethnic Serb in the government, but resigned in November 2006 amid allegations that he misused ministry funds.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.adnki.com/index_2Level_English.php?cat=Politics&amp;loid=8.0.363650179&amp;par=0 Kosovo: Serb minister resigns over misuse of funds] &quot;, Adnkronos international (AKI), November 27, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.reliefweb.int/rw/RWB.NSF/db900SID/LZEG-6VUQUS?OpenDocument Sole Kosovo Serb cabinet minister resigns: PM] &quot;, Agence France-Presse (AFP), November 24, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Kosovo Status Process ===
{{main|Kosovo Status Process}} {{see|Constitutional status of Kosovo}}
{{current event}}

A UN-led political process began in late 2005 to determine Kosovo's future status.  Belgrade has proposed that Kosovo be highly autonomous and remain a part of Serbia — Belgrade officials have repeatedly said that an imposition of Kosovo's independence would be a violation of Serbia's sovereignty and therefore contrary to international law. Pristina asserts that Kosovo should become independent, arguing that the violence of the Milosevic years has made continued union between Kosovo and Serbia not viable.  

UN Special Envoy [[Martti Ahtisaari]], former [[president of Finland]], leads the status process; [[Austria]]n diplomat Albert Rohan is his deputy.  Ahtisaari's office — the UN Office of the Special Envoy for Kosovo (UNOSEK) — is located in [[Vienna]] and includes liaison staff from [[NATO]], the [[European Union|EU]] and the United States.  

On [[February 2]], [[2007]], UN Special Envoy Martti Ahtisaari delivered to Belgrade and Pristina leaders a draft status settlement proposal.  The proposal covered a wide range of issues related to Kosovo's future, in particular measures to protect Kosovo's non-Albanian communities such as decentralization of government, protection of Serbian Orthodox Church heritage and institutional protections for non-Albanian communities.  While not mentioning the word &quot;independence,&quot; the draft included several provisions that were widely interpreted as implying statehood for Kosovo.  In particular, the draft Settlement would give Kosovo the right to apply for membership in international organizations, create a Kosovo Security Force and adopt national symbols.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.yahoo.com/s/afp/20070202/ts_afp/serbiakosovounstatusproposal_070202162726;_ylt=Ap9g4N..BOD23p6b5WY2sqsXxHcA;_ylu=X3oDMTBiMW04NW9mBHNlYwMlJVRPUCUl UN envoy seeks multi-ethnic, self-governing Kosovo] &quot;, ''Agence France-Presse'' (AFP), Vienna, February 2, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;  Ahtisaari intends to conduct consultations with the parties in Vienna to finalize the Settlement, after which he intends to present a final report to the UN Security Council by late March.

Most international observers believe these negotiations will lead to Kosovo's independence, although with certain conditions or temporary limitations placed on the exercise of its sovereignty.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.economist.com/displaystory.cfm?story_id=4489028 Kosovo's status — the wheels grind on]&quot;, ''[[The Economist]]'', [[October 6]], [[2005]]&lt;/ref&gt;  Nevertheless, Russian President [[Vladimir Putin]] stated in [[September]] [[2006]] that Russia may veto a [[UN Security Council]] proposal on Kosovo's final status that applies different standards than those applied to the separatist [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]]n regions of [[South Ossetia]] and [[Abkhazia]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2006/09/13/europe/EU_GEN_Russia_Kosovo.php Putin says world should regard Kosovo, separatist Georgian regions on equal footing]&quot;, ''[[International Herald Tribune]]'', [[September 13]] [[2006]].&lt;/ref&gt;  The Russian ambassador to Serbia has asserted that Russia will use its veto power unless the solution is acceptable to both Belgrade and Priština.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.b92.net/eng/news/politics-article.php?yyyy=2006&amp;mm=12&amp;dd=04&amp;nav_category=92&amp;nav_id=38392 Russian ambassador: Compromise or veto]&quot;, ''[[B92]]'', [[December 4]], [[2006]].&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Contact Group]] has said that regardless of status outcome a new International Civilian Office (ICO) will be established in Kosovo to supervise the implementation status settlement and safeguard minority rights.  NATO leaders have said that KFOR will be maintained in Kosovo after the status settlement.  The EU will establish a [[European Security and Defense Policy]] Rule of Law mission to focus on the police/justice sectors.''

== Economy ==

{{main|Economy of Kosovo}}
[[Image:Kosovo_stamp.jpg‎|thumb|100px| Postage stamp from Kosovo issued after the 1999 Kosovo war]]
Kosovo has one of the most under-developed economies in Europe, with a per capita income estimated at [[Euro|€]]1,565  (2004).&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/COUNTRIES/ECAEXT/KOSOVOEXTN/0,,contentMDK:20629286~menuPK:297777~pagePK:1497618~piPK:217854~theSitePK:297770,00.html]&lt;/ref&gt; Despite substantial development subsidies from all Yugoslav republics, Kosovo was the poorest province of Yugoslavia.&lt;ref&gt;Christian Science Monitor 1982-01-15, &quot;Why Turbulent Kosovo has Marble Sidewalks but Troubled Industries&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, over the course of the 1990s a blend of poor economic policies, international sanctions, poor external commerce and ethnic conflict severely damaged the economy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/COUNTRIES/ECAEXT/KOSOVOEXTN/0,,menuPK:297775~pagePK:141159~piPK:141110~theSitePK:297770,00.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

Kosovo's economy remains weak. After a jump in 2000 and 2001 [[GDP]] growth was negative in 2002 and 2003 and is expected to be around 3 percent 2004-2005, with domestic sources of growth unable to compensate for the declining foreign assistance. [[Inflation]] is low, while the budget posted a deficit for the first time in 2004. Kosovo has high external deficits. In 2004, the deficit of the balance of goods and services was close to 70 percent of [[GDP]]. Remittances from Kosovars living abroad accounts for an estimated 13 percent of [[GDP]], and foreign assistance for around 34 percent of [[GDP]].&lt;ref&gt;http://ec.europa.eu/economy_finance/publications/enlargement_papers/2005/elp26en.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

Most economic development since 1999 has taken place in the trade, retail and the construction sectors. The private sector that has emerged since 1999 is mainly small-scale. The industrial sector remains weak and the electric power supply remains unreliable, acting as a key constraint. Unemployment remains pervasive, at around 40-50% of the labor force.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.eciks.org/english/lajme.php?action=total_news&amp;main_id=386&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://ec.europa.eu/economy_finance/publications/enlargement_papers/2005/elp26en.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; 

UNMIK introduced ''de-facto'' an external trade regime and customs administration on September 3, 1999 when it set customs border controls in Kosovo. All goods imported in Kosovo face a flat 10% customs duty fee.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.buyusa.gov/kosovo/en/doingbusinessinkosovo.html&lt;/ref&gt; These taxes are collected from all Tax Collection Points installed at the borders of Kosovo, including those between Kosovo and  Serbia.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.seerecon.org/kosovo/documents/wb_econ_report/wb-kosovo-econreport-2-2.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; UNMIK and Kosovo institutions have signed Free Trade Agreements with [[Croatia]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.b92.net/eng/news/globe-article.php?yyyy=2006&amp;mm=10&amp;dd=02&amp;nav_category=123&amp;nav_id=37090 Croatia, Kosovo sign Interim Free Trade Agreement], [[B92]], 2 October 2006&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bosnia and Hercegovina]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.euinkosovo.org/upload_press/4.06%20-%20UNMIK%20and%20Bosnia%20and%20Herzegovina%20Initial%20Free%20Trade%20Agreement%2017.2.06.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Albania]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.kosovo-eicc.org/oek/index.php?page_id=64&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.buyusa.gov/kosovo/en/doingbusinessinkosovo.html&lt;/ref&gt;

FYROM is Kosovo's largest import and export market (averaging €220 million and €9 million respectively), followed by Serbia-Montenegro (€111 million and €5 million), Germany and Turkey.[http://siteresources.worldbank.org/INTKOSOVO/147270-1121700806276/20953280/Kosovo_Economic_Briefing_april.pdf]

The [[Euro]] is the official currency of Kosovo and used by UNMIK and the government bodies.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.euinkosovo.org/uk/invest/invest.php&lt;/ref&gt; The Serbian [[Dinar]] is used in the Serbian populated parts.

The economy is hindered by Kosovo's still-unresolved international status, which has made it difficult to attract investment and loans.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/business/4509781.stm Brussels offers first Kosovo loan]&quot;, BBC News Online, 3 May 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; The province's economic weakness has produced a thriving black economy in which smuggled petrol, cigarettes and cement are major commodities. The prevalence of official corruption and the pervasive influence of organised crime gangs has caused serious concern internationally. The United Nations has made the fight against corruption and organised crime a high priority, pledging a &quot;zero tolerance&quot; approach.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.kosovo.undp.org/Projects/TIK/tik.asp Transparency Initiative for Kosovo (TIK)&quot;, UN Development Programme in Kosovo&lt;/ref&gt;

== Demographics ==
{{main|Demographic history of Kosovo}}
[[Image:Kosovo ethnic 2005.png|right|thumb|270px|Ethnic composition of Kosovo in [[2005]] according to the [[OSCE]]]]
According to the Kosovo in Figures 2005 Survey of the Statistical Office of Kosovo,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ks-gov.net/esk/esk/pdf/english/general/kosovo_figures_05.pdf  &lt;/ref&gt; Kosovo's total population is estimated between 1.9 and 2.2 million in the following ethnic proportions:
* 88% [[Albanians]] (between 1,972,000 and 2,100,000) 
* 7% [[Serbs]] (between 126,000 and 140,000) 
* 1.9% [[Bosniaks]] (between 34,200 and 38,000) 
* 1.7% [[Roma people|Roma]] (between 30,600 and 34,000) (see also [[Roma in Mitrovica Camps]])
* 1% [[Turkish people|Turks]] (between 18,000 and 20,000)
* 0.5% [[Gorani (Kosovo)|Gorani]] (approx. 10,000)

However, the figures are highly disputable. Some estimates are that there is an Albanian majority well above 90 percent. The population census is set to take place in the near future. Others give much higher figures for Roma and Turks.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.salon.com/news/1999/03/31newsa.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.serbianunity.net/news/world_articles/Dragnich1098.html&lt;/ref&gt; There was also a small minority of [[Circassians]] in [[Kosovo Polje]] but they were repatriated to the [[Republic of Adygea]], in Southern [[Russia]]. The ethnic Albanian Kosovo Liberation Army is thought to have threatened the Adygs.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/143667.stm BBC News: ''Circassians flee Kosovo conflict''. Sunday, August 2, 1998 Published at 01:01 GMT 02:01 UK&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of the Albanians in Kosovo are [[Muslims]] and most Serbs are [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Eastern Orthodox]]. However, Kosovo Albanians do not define their national identity through religion, and most are non-practising. About 5% of the Albanians in Kosovo are [[Catholics]]. Atheism is also common among both Albanians and Serbs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crisisgroup.org/home/index.cfm?id=1591&amp;l=1 Religion in Kosovo] - International Crisis Group&lt;/ref&gt;

== Subdivisions ==

{{main|Subdivisions of Kosovo}}
Kosovo is divided into 7 districts:
*[[Prishtina District|Prishtina/Priština District]]
*[[Prizreni District|Prizreni/Prizren District]]
*[[Peja District|Peja/Peć District]]
*[[Ferizaji District|Ferizaji/Uroševac District]]
*[[Gjakova District|Gjakova/Đakovica District]]
*[[Mitrovica District|Mitrovica/Kosovska Mitrovica District]]
*[[Gjilani District|Gjilani/Gnjilane District]]

[[North Kosovo]] maintains its own government, infrastructure and institutions by its dominant ethnic [[Serb]] population in the [[Mitrovica District]], on the [[Leposavic]], [[Zvecan]] and [[Zubin Potok]] municipalities and the northern part of [[Kosovska Mitrovica]].
{{see also|Municipalities of Kosovo}}

== Cities ==
[[Image:Prishtina maj 2005.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Priština]]/[[Prishtina]].]]
List of largest cities in Kosovo (with population figures in 2006):&lt;ref&gt;http://www.world-gazetteer.com/wg.php?x=&amp;men=gcis&amp;lng=en&amp;dat=32&amp;srt=npan&amp;col=aohdq&amp;geo=-244&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Priština]]/[[Prishtina]] (562,686)
*[[Prizren]]/[[Prizreni]] (165,229)
*[[Uroševac]]/[[Ferizaji]] (97,741)
*[[Đakovica]]/[[Gjakova]] (97,156)
*[[Peć]]/[[Peja]] (95,190)
*[[Gnjilane]]/[[Gjilani]] (91,595)
*[[Kosovska Mitrovica]]/[[Mitrovica (Kosovo)|Mitrovica]] (86,359)
*[[Podujevo]]/[[Podujeva]] (48,526)

== Culture ==
===Music===
[[Music]] has always been part of the [[Albanian]] culture. Although in Kosovo music is diverse (as it got mixed with the cultures of different regimes dominating in Kosovo), authentic Albanian music (see ''[[World Music]]'') does still exist. It is characterized by use of ''[[çiftelia]]'' (an authentic Albanian instrument), ''mandolin'', ''mandola'' and ''percussion''.
In Kosovo, along with modern music, [[folk]] music is very popular. There are many folk [[singers]] and ensembles.  [[European classical music|Classical music]] is also well known in Kosovo.
The modern music in Kosovo has its origin from the Western countries. The main modern genres include: [[Pop (music)|Pop]], [[Hip hop music|Hip Hop]], [[Rock (music)|Rock]] and [[Jazz]]. The most notable rock bands are: Gjurmët, Troja, Votra, Diadema, Humus, Asgjë sikur Dielli, Kthjellu, [[Cute Babulja]], [[Babilon]], etc. Ilir Bajri is a notable [[jazz]] and [[Electronic Music|electronic]] musician. Most notable hip-hop performers are the rap-group called NR (urbaNRoots) who also introduced a new type of rap different to the G-Funk that was widely spread before. Other hip-hop artists include [[Unikkatil]] (who lives in the USA but represents Kosovo), Tingulli 3, Ritmi I Rrugës, Mad Lion, K-OS and many more.

[[Leonora Jakupi]], Jehona Sopi and [[Adelina Ismajli]] are three of the most popular commercial singers in Kosovo today.

There are some notable music festivals in Kosovo:
* ''Rock për Rock'' - contains [[Rock (music)|rock]] and [[Heavy Metal music|metal]] music
* ''Polifest'' - contains all kinds of genres (usually [[Hip hop music|hip hop]], commercal [[Pop (music)|pop]], unusually [[Rock (music)|rock]] and never [[Heavy Metal music|metal]])
* ''Showfest'' - contains all kinds of genres (usually [[Hip hop music|hip hop]], commercal [[Pop (music)|pop]], unusually [[Rock (music)|rock]] and never [[Heavy Metal music|metal]])
* ''Videofest'' - contains all kinds of genres
* ''Kush Këndon Lutet Dy Herë'' - contains [[christian music]]

Kosovo Radiotelevisions like ''RTK'', ''21'' and ''KTV'' have their musical charts.

:''See also: [[List of Albanians#Musicians|Kosovo's and Albania's musicians]]''

== List of Presidents ==
:''Main article: [[Rulers of Kosovo]]''
List of the presidents of Kosovo:&lt;ref&gt;http://www.worldstatesmen.org/Yugoslavia.html#Kosovo&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Ibrahim Rugova]], [[4 March]] [[2002]] - [[21 January]] [[2006]]
* [[Fatmir Sejdiu]], [[10 February]] [[2006]] - present

== List of Prime Ministers ==
* [[Bujar Bukoshi]]
* [[Bajram Rexhepi]], [[4 March]] [[2002]] - [[3 December]] [[2004]]
* [[Ramush Haradinaj]], [[3 December]] [[2004]] - [[8 March]] [[2005]]
* [[Bajram Kosumi]], [[23 March]] [[2005]] - [[10 March]] [[2006]]
* [[Agim Çeku]], [[10 March]] [[2006]]-present

== Gallery ==
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Kosovo_government.jpg|The building of the [[Government of Kosovo]] in [[Prishtina]]/[[Priština]].
Image:Prizen kosovo.jpg|[[Prizreni]]/[[Prizren]].
Image:Gjakova.jpg|[[Gjakova]]/[[Đakovica]].
Image:Gjerovica new.JPG|[[Gjerovica]]/[[Đeravica]].
Image:VeshjeKombetare.JPG|[[Albanians in Kosovo|Kosovo Albanian]] ethnic costume/dance.  
Image:Erzengelkloster2.jpg|[[Serbs in Kosovo|Serb]] monastery near river [[Bistrica]].
Image:Bibloteka Kombëtare e Kosovës.jpg|National Public Library in [[Prishtina]]/[[Priština]].
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== See also ==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
* [[Assembly of Kosovo]]
* [[Government of Kosovo]]
* [[Prime Minister of Kosovo]]
* [[President of Kosovo]]
* [[Albanians in Kosovo]]
* [[Serbs in Kosovo]]
* [[Post and Telecom of Kosovo]]
{{col-2}}
* [[National awakening and the birth of Albania]]
* [[Demographic history of Kosovo]]
* [[Unrest in Kosovo]] (during March 2004)
* [[Metohija]]
* [[North Kosovo]]
* [[Sexual trafficking in Kosovo]]
{{col-end}}

==References==
&lt;div class=&quot;references-small&quot; style=&quot;-moz-column-count:2; column-count:2;&quot;&gt;&lt;references/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

== External links ==
{{sisterlinks|Kosovo}}
* [http://www.ks-gov.net/pm/?menuid=&amp;subid=&amp;lingo=2 The office of Prime Minister of Kosovo] English version
* [http://www.assembly-kosova.org/?krye=home&amp;lang=en Kosovo Assembly (Kuvendi i Kosovës)] English version
* [http://visitkosova.org/english/ The Official Webportal of Tourism in Kosovo]
* [http://ec.europa.eu/economy_finance/publications/enlargement_papers/2005/elp26en.pdf EU Commission report on economic development in Accession countries, including Kosovo]
* http://www.unosek.org/unosek/index.html UN Special Envoy's Office Website
* {{wikitravel}}
* [http://www.rtklive.com  RTK - Kosovo's public television - news in Albanian, Serbian, Turkish and Roma]
* [http://www.kosovakosovo.com/ KosovaKosovo] A source of information reflecting both sides’ claims in the dispute
* [http://www.unmikonline.org/ UNMIK] [[UN]] led civilian administration in Kosovo.
* [http://www.euinkosovo.org/index.php EU] EU Pillar in Kosovo. 
* [http://www.otvoreno.org.yu/ Otvoreno] A place where Serbian politicians speak openly on the Kosovo issue. In Serbian language only.
* [http://www.kosovo.net/default4.html KIM-Info News Service, News from Kosovo in English and Serbian]
* [http://www.crisisgroup.org/home/index.cfm?id=1243&amp;l=1 (ICG)] International Crisis Group, a source of independent analysis on Kosovo issues.
* [http://www.csdbalkans.org/roma Kosovo Roma Oral History Project] An advocacy website for Kosovo's Roma/ Gypsies, with significant details on Kosovo's contested history.
* [http://www.eciks.org/english/index.php ECIKS] Economic Initiative for Kosovo, information on investment opportunities.
* [http://www.state.gov/www/regions/eur/rpt_990604_ksvo_ethnic.html US State Dept. fact sheet &quot;The Ethnic Cleansing of Kosovo&quot;]

=== Pro-Albanian ===
* [http://www.albanian.com/ Albanian.com] A Community portal where Albanians share information and ideas.
* [http://www.newkosovo.org/ Alliance for a New Kosovo] A Policy Resource on Kosovo Independence.
* [http://www.kosovaevidence.com KosovoEvidence.com] - movie about what happened in Kosovo during the war
* [http://www.eciks.org Economic Initiative for Kosovo] - &quot;...latest news, analysis and publications from the Kosovar economy&quot;
* [http://www.alb-shkenca.org/images/stories/Why%20Independence.pdf Why Independence for Kosovo?] A summary of the case for an independent Kosovo by two Priština intellectuals
* [http://www.newkosovo.org/news.htm Alliance for New Kosovo] A policy resource on Kosovo independence
* [http://www.alb-net.com/index.htm Kosova Crisis Center] A collection of articles on Kosovo, in [[English language|English]].
* [http://www.aacl.com/indexmain.html AACL] Albanian American Civic League.
* [http://www.kosovalive.com/?cid=2 KosovaLive] Kosovo Albanian independent news agency (this section in [[English language|English]]).
* [http://www.savekosova.org/ American Council for Kosova] - U.S. nonprofit organization dedicated to a better understanding of the issue of Kosova by the American public

=== Pro-Serbian ===
* [http://www.rastko.org.yu/kosovo/istorija/sanu/GrtAlb.html KOSOVO, SERBIAN ISSUE AND THE GREATER ALBANIA PROJECT] written by Slavenko TERZIC, Ph. D. - Historical Institute of Serbian Academy of Sciences and Arts
* [http://www.rastko.org.yu/kosovo/istorija/sanu/ethnic.html ALBANIAN ETHNIC CLEANSING OF THE OLD SERBIA] written by Slavenko TERZIC, Ph. D. - Historical Institute of Serbian Academy of Sciences and Arts
* [http://www.rastko.org.yu/kosovo/istorija/sanu/Kosovo.html KOSOVO AND METOHIA IN THE SERBIAN HISTORY] written by Slavenko TERZIC, Ph. D. - Historical Institute of Serbian Academy of Sciences and Arts]
* [http://www.srbija.sr.gov.yu/kosovo-metohija/ Serbian Government for Kosovo-Metohija] Website that focusses on the human rights situation of Serbian and other non-Albanian populations in Kosovo. (in [[English language|English]] and [[Serbian language|Serbian]])
* [http://www.rastko.org.yu/kosovo/crucified/default.htm Crucified Kosovo] Overview of destroyed Serbian Orthodox churches in Kosovo. (in [[English language|English]])
* [http://www.mfa.gov.yu/Policy/CI/kosovo-slike/index.html Terror in Kosovo] Terror in Kosovo (in [[English language|English]])
* [http://www.kc.gov.yu/ Coordination Center of SCG and the Republic of Serbia for Kosovo] (in [http://www.kc.gov.yu/D-ENGLISH/index-eng.html English], [http://www.kc.gov.yu/A-CIRILICA/index-cir.html Serbian] and [http://www.kc.gov.yu/C-ALBANSKI/index-alb.html Albanian])
* [http://www.kosovo.net/ Kosovo-The Land of the Living past] (in [[English language|English]])
* [http://www.b92.net/english/news/index.php?style=headlines&amp;nav_category=19 B92] Serbian Independent news agency (in [[English language|English]])
* [http://www.savekosovo.org Save Kosovo] - U.S. nonprofit organization dedicated to promoting a better American understanding of the Serbian province of Kosovo and Metohija and of the critical American stake in the province’s future. (in [[English language|English]])
* [http://www.kosovocompromise.com/ Kosovo 2006 Making of a Compromise] (in [[English language|English]])
* [http://www.eparhija-prizren.com/defaultE.asp Diocese Kosovo of Serbian Orthodox Church] (in [http://www.eparhija-prizren.com/defaultE.asp English], [http://www.eparhija-prizren.com/default.asp Serbian] and [http://www.eparhija-prizren.com/defaultR.asp Russian])

{{Kosovo}}
{{Autonomous Provinces of Serbia}}
{{Republics and autonomous provinces of the former Yugoslavia}}
{{Dependent and other territories of Europe}}

[[Category:Kosovo|*]]
[[Category:Proposed countries]]

[[als:Kosova]]
[[ar:قوصوه]]
[[frp:Kosovo]]
[[ast:Kosovo]]
[[zh-min-nan:Kosovo]]
[[bs:Kosovo]]
[[br:Kosovo]]
[[bg:Косово (област)]]
[[ca:Kosovo]]
[[cs:Kosovo]]
[[cy:Kosovo]]
[[da:Kosovo]]
[[de:Kosovo]]
[[et:Kosovo]]
[[es:Kosovo]]
[[eo:Kosovo]]
[[fr:Kosovo]]
[[ko:코소보]]
[[hsb:Kosovo]]
[[hr:Kosovo]]
[[io:Kosovo]]
[[id:Kosovo]]
[[it:Kosovo]]
[[he:קוסובו ומטוחיה]]
[[la:Ager merulensis]]
[[lv:Kosova un Metohija]]
[[lt:Kosovas]]
[[li:Kosovo]]
[[hu:Koszovó]]
[[mk:Косово]]
[[nl:Kosovo]]
[[ja:コソボ]]
[[no:Kosovo]]
[[nn:Kosovo]]
[[oc:Kosovë]]
[[nds:Kosovo]]
[[pl:Kosowo]]
[[pt:Kosovo]]
[[ro:Kosovo]]
[[ru:Косово и Метохия]]
[[sq:Kosova]]
[[simple:Kosovo]]
[[sk:Kosovo]]
[[sl:Kosovo]]
[[sr:Косово и Метохија]]
[[sh:Kosovo i Metohija]]
[[fi:Kosovo]]
[[sv:Kosovo]]
[[tr:Kosova]]
[[uk:Косово]]
[[zh:科索沃]]</text>
