      <text xml:space="preserve">{{otheruses}} {{seealso|Names of Kosovo}}
{{Infobox Kosovo}}&lt;!--

Please be very careful in editing the introduction of this article. The Arbitration Committee has placed this article on probation. If any editor makes disruptive edits, they may be banned by an administrator from this and related articles, or other reasonably related pages. See the talk page for more information.

--&gt;
'''Kosovo''' &lt;!--Please leave the following language order as Albanian followed by Serbian: this is alphabetical and as neutral as we can get. Serbian is listed first in the infobox as balance--&gt;([[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Kosova'' or ''Kosovë'', [[Serbian language|Serbian]]: {{lang|sr-Cyrl|Косово и Метохија}}, [[Transliteration|transliterated]] {{lang|sr-Latn|''Kosovo i Metohija''}}; also {{lang|sr-Cyrl|Космет}}, transliterated {{lang|sr-Latn|''Kosmet''}}) is a region in southern [[Serbia]] which has been under [[United Nations]] [[United Nations Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo|administration]] since [[1999]]. While Serbia's [[sovereignty]] is recognised by the international community, in practice Serbian governance in the province is virtually non-existent (see also [[Constitutional status of Kosovo]]). The province is governed by the [[United Nations Mission in Kosovo]] (UNMIK) and the local [[Provisional Institutions of Self-Government]], with security provided by the [[NATO]]-led [[Kosovo Force]] (KFOR). 

The Province of Kosovo borders [[Montenegro]], [[Albania]], and the [[Republic of Macedonia]]. It has a population of just over two million people, predominantly ethnic [[Albanians]], with smaller populations of [[Serbs]], [[Turkish people|Turks]], [[Bosniaks]], [[Romani people]], and other ethnic groups. [[Priština]] is the capital and largest city. 

The province is the subject of a long-running political and territorial dispute between the Serbian (and previously, the [[Yugoslavia|Yugoslav]]) government and Kosovo's largely ethnic-Albanian population. International negotiations began in [[2006]] to determine the final status of Kosovo (''See [[Kosovo status process]]'').

== Geography ==
{{for|the administrative division of Kosovo|Municipalities of Kosovo}}

[[Image:UTkosovo rel small 92.jpg|thumb|left|275px|Physical map of Kosovo.]]

With an area of 10,887 [[square kilometre]]s&lt;ref&gt;[http://webrzs.statserb.sr.gov.yu/axd/teritorija.htm Административно територијална подела Републике Србије на покрајине, округе, општине и Град Београд]&lt;/ref&gt; (4,203 [[square mile|sq&amp;nbsp;mi]]) and a population of over two million on the eve of the 1999 crisis, Kosovo borders [[Montenegro]] to the northwest, [[Central Serbia]] to the north and east, the [[Republic of Macedonia]] to the south, and [[Albania]] to the south west. The province's present borders were established in [[1945]]. The [[Republic of Serbia]] has one other autonomous province, [[Vojvodina]], located in the north of the country.

The largest cities are [[Priština]] ({{lang-sq|Prishtinë}}), the capital, with an estimated 600,000 inhabitants, [[Prizren]] ({{lang-sq|Prizreni}}) in the south west with a population of 165,000, [[Peć]] ([[Albanian language|Albanian]]: Peja) in the west with 154,000, and [[Kosovska Mitrovica]] ([[Albanian language|Albanian]]: Mitrovicë) in the north. Five other towns have populations in excess of 97,000. 

The climate in Kosovo is continental, with warm summers and cold and snowy winters.

There are two main plains in Kosovo. The [[Metohija]] basin (known as ''Rrafshi i Dukagjinit'' to ethnic Albanians) is located in the western part of the province, and the Plain of Kosovo occupies the eastern part.

Much of Kosovo's terrain is rugged. The [[Šar Mountain|Šar (or Sharr) Mountains]] are located in the south and south-east, bordering [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]]. This is one of the region's most popular tourist and skiing resorts, with [[Brezovica, Serbia|Brezovica]] and Prevalac as the main tourist centres. Kosovo's mountainous area, including the highest peak [[Deravica|Ðeravica]] (Gjeravica) (2656&amp;nbsp;m above sea level), is located in the south-west, bordering [[Albania]] and [[Montenegro]]. 

The mountain range dividing Kosovo from Albania is known in English as the [[Prokletije|Cursed Mountains]] or as the [[Dinaric Alps]]. The [[Kopaonik]] mountain is located in the north, bordering [[Central Serbia]]. The central region of [[Drenica]], Crnoljevo and the eastern part of Kosovo, known as [[Gollak]], are mainly hilly areas. 

There are several notable rivers and lakes in Kosovo. The main rivers are the [[White Drin]] (or Drini i Bardhe, running towards the [[Adriatic Sea]]), with the [[Erenik]] among its [[Tributary|tributaries]]), the [[Sitnica]], the [[South Morava]] in the [[Gollak]] area, and [[Ibar River|Ibar]] (or Ibri) in the north. The main lakes are Gazivoda (380 million m³) in the north-western part, Radoniqi (113 million m³) in the south-west part, Batllava (40 million m³) and Badovc (26 million m³) in the north-east part.

== History ==
{{main|History of Kosovo}}
{{see also|Demographic history of Kosovo}}

The last disputed region of the now defunct communist Yugoslavia, the Republic of Kosovo has an extensive and rich history. Inhabited by several different groups, it was initially (circa 1300 B.C.E.) an Illyrian region which became incorporated into the Roman empire and subsequently Byzantine empire. From c. 6th century AD it was settled by Slavs (Serbians) migrating from the north. It was conquered by the Ottoman empire during their take-over of south-eastern Europe. However, it was re-occupied by the Serbs in the late 19th century, and continued on as an autonomous province of modern Yugoslavia.

=== Kosovo in the Middle-Ages ===

{{see also|History of Medieval Kosovo}}

[[Image:Serbia boundaries CIA.jpg|thumb|righ|230px|Map: ''&quot;Kosovo: History of a Balkan Hot Spot&quot;'', 1998]]
The Kosovo region has been taken, retaken, and ruled by several empires. It lay both on the outer fringes of the [[Byzantine Empire]] and directly in the path of Slavic expansion. From about the [[850s]] until about [[1014]], it was ruled by [[Bulgaria]]. Byzantine control was subsequently reasserted by the forceful emperor [[Basil II]]. Serbia at this time was not a united empire: a number of small Serbian kingdoms lay to the north and west of Kosovo, of which [[Raška]] (central modern Serbia) and [[Duklja]] ([[Montenegro]] and northern Albania) were the strongest. In the [[1180]]s, the Serbian ruler [[Stefan Nemanja]] seized control of Duklja and parts of Kosovo. His successor, [[Stefan Prvovenčani]] took control of the rest of Kosovo by [[1216]], creating a state incorporating most of the area which is now Serbia and Montenegro.

During the rule of the [[Nemanjić]] dynasty, many [[Serbian Orthodox]] churches and monasteries were built throughout Serbian territory, usually upon the ruins of Catholic establishments. The [[Nemanjić]] rulers alternatively used both [[Prizren]] and [[Priština]] as their capitals. Large estates were given to the monasteries in Dukagjin (Western Kosovo) (which included parts of Albania and Montenegro). The most prominent churches in Kosovo - the [[Patriarchate]] at [[Pec]], the church at [[Gračanica]] and the monastery at [[Visoki Dečani]] near [[Dečani]] - were all adopted during this period.  Kosovo was economically important, as the modern Kosovo capital [[Priština]] was a major trading centre on routes leading to ports on the [[Adriatic Sea]]. As well, mining was an important industry in [[Novo Brdo]] and [[Janjevo]] which had its communities of émigré [[Saxons|Saxon]] miners and [[Republic of Ragusa|Ragusan]] merchants.

Ethnic identity from the [[Middle Ages]] was somewhat fluid throughout Europe, and people at that time do not appear to have defined themselves rigidly by a single ethnic identity. Those of Illyrian origin, particularly of the Albanian background, appear to have been the dominant population culturally and were probably a demographic majority as well.

In [[1355]], the Serbian state fell apart on the death of [[Tsar]] [[Stefan Dušan]] and dissolved into squabbling fiefdoms. The timing fell perfectly within the Ottoman expansion. The Ottoman Empire took the opportunity to exploit Serbian weakness and invaded.

===Ottoman Empire===
{{seealso|Vilayet of Kosovo}}
{{seealso|History of Ottoman Serbia}}

The [[Ottoman Empire|Ottomans]] brought [[Islamisation]] with them, particularly in towns, and later also created the [[Vilayet of Kosovo]] as one of the Ottoman territorial entities. Ottoman rule lasted for about 500 years, in which time the Ottomans were the absolute paramount power in the region. Many christians adopted Islam, particularly many Bosnians and Albanians, whose populations became predominantly Islamic. The Ottomans administered through a ''millet'' system- based on religion- whereby muslim subjects received more tax concessions and personal liberties compared to Christians and Jews &lt;ref&gt; The Balkans: from Constantinople to Communsim. Dennis P Hupchick &lt;/ref&gt;. 

Kosovo was taken temporarily by the Austrian forces during the War of [[1683]]&amp;ndash;[[1699]] with help of serbs. After the Austrians retreated, many Serbs had to flee from Kosovo to evade Ottoman reprisals. In [[1690]], the [[Serbian Patriarch of Peć]] [[Arsenije III]], who previously escaped a certain death, led 37,000 families from Kosovo, to evade [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] wrath. The people that followed him were mostly [[Serbs]] —but they were likely followed by Christians of other ethnic backgrounds. 

The Albanian people of the area also continued to intermitently struggle against occupation, yet suffered less reprisals at the hands of the Ottomans. Quite a few rose to prominence in the Turkish system, as administrators and as soldiers. During this time, many Albanians moved back into Kosovo, filling in lands and houses vacated by fleeing Christians &lt;ref&gt; the Balkans: from Constantinople to Communism &lt;/ref&gt;. Whilst relations between Serbs and Albanians were peaceful initially, this eventually deteriorated. At the outset, Christians and Muslim-converts celebrated each other's religious holidays together. However, later, many young Islamics participated in Turkish massacres of Christians &lt;ref&gt; Alex Dragnich and Slavko Todorovich. Serbs and Albanians Under Turkish Rule &lt;/ref&gt;, which in turn would be retaliated upon by the Serbs when they got the upper hand. This period has by many been identified as the catalyst of the subsequent deterioration of the relationship between Serbian and Albanian peoples. Apart from religious tensions, the subsequent political outlook changed for the two people. As the Ottoman empire began to collapse, Serbia aimed to re-incorporate Kosovo into the heart of its realm, whereas many Albanians were content with their new-found authority within the Ottoman system.

With ongoing oppression from the Ottomans, migrations of Christian people out of Kosovo continued until the Ottoman empire finally collapsed.

===Modern era===

{{seealso|History of Modern Kosovo}}

[[Image:SAP Kosovo.png|thumb|left|275px|[[Socialist Autonomous Province of Kosovo]] of [[Socialist Republic of Serbia|Socialist Serbia]] inside [[Socialist Yugoslavia]], 1974-1990]]
During the 19th Century part of modern Kosovo was reintegrated in to 'Old Serbia' following a Peace Accord of 1878 which brought the cities of Priština and Kosovska Mitrovica under Serbian control whilst leaving the remainder of Kosovo under Ottoman authority. An ethnic-Albanian Prizren League was formed which sought to unite all of the Albanian provinces of the Ottoman Empire, but which was ultimately defeated by Ottoman forces. During the [[First Balkan War]] of [[1912]] most of Kosovo was retaken by the [[Kingdom of Serbia]] while the region of Metohija (know as the Dukagjini Valley to ethnic-Albanians) was taken by the Kingdom of Montenegro. Populations of ethnic Serbs and Albanians tended to shift following territorial conquests.

During World War I, Kosovo was occupied by the Bulgarian and Austro-Hungarian forces following a serious defeat of Serbian and allied armies in 1914. Returning in 1918, the Serbian army pushed the central powers out of Kosovo as the war came to a close. Following WWI, the [[Kingdom of the Serbs, Croats and Slovenes]] was formed, bringing together Serbian Kosovo and Montenegrin Metohija within the new kingdom. The partition of Yugoslavia by the invading [[Axis Powers]] from 1941 and 1945 awarded most of the territory to the Italian-occupied [[Greater Albania]], and a smaller part of it to [[Nazi Germany|German]]-occupied Serbia and [[Greater Bulgaria]]. Both wars were occasions for inter-ethnic violence and both voluntary and forced population shifts.

Following the end of the war and the establishment of [[Tito]]'s [[Communist]] regime, Kosovo was granted the status of an autonomous region of Yugoslavia in [[1946]] and became an autonomous province in [[1963]]. With the passing of the [[1974]] Yugoslavia constitution, Kosovo gained self-government. Throughout the [[1980s]] tensions between the Albanian and Serb communities in the province escalated.&lt;ref name=&quot;reuters19860527&quot;&gt;Reuters 1986-05-27, &quot;Kosovo Province Revives Yugoslavia's Ethnic Nightmare&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;csm19860728&quot;&gt;Christian Science Monitor 1986-07-28, &quot;Tensions among ethnic groups in Yugoslavia begin to boil over&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The Albanian community favoured greater autonomy for Kosovo, whilst Serbs favoured closer ties with the rest of Serbia. There was little appetite for unification with Albania itself, which was ruled by a [[Stalinist]] government and had considerably worse living standards than Kosovo. Beginning in March [[1981]], Kosovo Albanian students organized protests seeking that Kosovo become a republic within Yugoslavia. Those protests rapidly escalated into violent riots &quot;involving 20,000 people in six cities&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt19810419&quot;&gt;New York Times 1981-04-19, &quot;One Storm has Passed but Others are Gathering in Yugoslavia&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; that were harshly contained by the Yugoslav government.

Serbs living in Kosovo complained at discrimination from the provincial Kosovo government (run by the ethnic-Albanian dominated Communist Party of Kosovo)&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt19820712&quot;&gt;New York Times 1982-07-12, &quot;Exodus of Serbians Stirs Province in Yugoslavia&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; and neglect from the Federal authorities in Belgrade.&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt19870627&quot;&gt;New York Times 1987-06-27, &quot;Belgrade Battles Kosovo Serbs&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; In August [[1987]], during the dying days of Yugoslavia's Communist regime, Kosovo was visited by [[Slobodan Milošević]], then a rising politician. Milošević capitalised on this discontent to consolidate his own position in Serbia. In a staged event, having drawn huge crowds to a rally commemorating the Battle of Kosovo, he pledged to Kosovo Serbs that &quot;No one should dare to beat you&quot;, and became an instant hero of Kosovo's Serbs.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cnn.com/SPECIALS/2000/kosovo/stories/past/milosevic/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Economist, June 05, 1999, U.S. Edition, 1041 words, What's next for Slobodan Milošević?&lt;/ref&gt;   By the end of the year Milošević was in control of the Serbian government.

In [[1989]], the autonomy of both Kosovo and of [[Vojvodina]] were drastically reduced by a new Serbian constitution which allowed a [[multi-party system]], introduced [[freedom of speech]] and promoted [[human rights]]. Though later subverted by [[Milošević]]'s abuses, the new constitution was a significant step forward from the previous Communist constitution. However, the new constitution 
also significantly reduced the rights of the two previously autonomous provinces, giving control of many areas directly to the Government of Serbia, including control of the police, the court system, the economy, the education system and language policies. Differing viewpoints see either an attempt to gain control of a crisis-ridden province or a cynical exploitation of nationalist politics&lt;ref name=&quot;reuters19880730&quot;&gt;Reuters 1988-07-30, &quot;Yugoslav Leaders Call for Control in Kosovo, Protests Loom&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;. When called to ratify the new constitution in March [[1989]], the assemblies of the provinces were met with tanks and armoured cars, effectively forcing the delegates to accept the amendments. Kosovo Albanians boycotted state institutions and elections and established separate Albanian schools and political institutions. On [[July 2]] [[1990]], an unofficial Kosovo parliament declared Kosovo independent, though this move was recognised only by [[Albania]]. In [[1992]], the parliament organised an unofficial referendum, observed by international organizations{{Fact|date=July 2007}} not recognized internationally, which saw a 98% vote of the Kosovo Albanian majority for independence. 

====Kosovo War====
{{main|Kosovo War}}

After the [[Dayton Agreement]] of 1995, the [[Kosovo Liberation Army]] (KLA) was formed as a means to stop the murder of Albanians by  [[Milosevic]]'s regime and employing guerilla-style tactics against Serbian police forces and civilians who engaged in paramilitary activities. Violence escalated in a series of KLA attacks and Serbian reprisals into the year 1999, with increasing numbers of civilian victims. In 1998 western interest in preventing Milosevic from committing the same sort of genocide and ethnic cleansing that Serbia committed in Bosnia increased and the Serbian authorities were forced to sign a unilateral cease-fire and partial retreat. Under an agreement led by [[Richard Holbrooke]], [[OSCE]] observers moved into Kosovo to monitor the ceasefire, while Yugoslav military forces partly pulled out of Kosovo; neither side kept the ceasefire fully. A massacre of Albanians by Serbian military at the town of [[Racak]] in January 1999&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/1812847.stm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hrw.org/press/1999/jan/yugo0129.htm&lt;/ref&gt; increased international concern at [[Milosevic]]'s actions. The subsequent [[Rambouillet]] conference fell apart after [[Milosevic]] refused to sign an [[Rambouillet Agreement|agreement]] which would give Kosovo equal status as a Republic and which purportedly would give [[NATO]] forces access rights to all of [[Yugoslavia]].

This triggered a 78-day [[NATO]] campaign in [[1999]]. At first limited to military targets in Kosovo itself, the bombing campaign was soon extended to cover military or related targets that supported military troops all over [[Yugoslavia]], including bridges, power stations, factories, broadcasting stations, post offices, hospitals, civil buildings, trains, and various government buildings. During the conflict roughly a million ethnic Albanians fled from Yugoslav forces or were forcefully driven by Yugoslav forces from Kosovo, several thousand were killed (the numbers and the ethnic distribution of the casualties are uncertain and highly disputed). An estimated 10,000 ethnic Albanians and 3,000 Serbs are believed to have been killed during the conflict. Some 3,000 people are still missing, of which 2,500 are Albanian, 400 Serbs and 100 Roma.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/781310.stm&lt;/ref&gt;

====Kosovo after the war====
[[Image:KFOR.jpg|thumb|220px|Ukrainian soldier on foot patrolling in Serbian village near [[Brezovica]]]]
The conflict ended with an agreement[http://www.nato.int/kosovo/docu/a990609a.htm] signed by both [[Yugoslavia]] and [[NATO]] at [[Kumanovo]] in Macedonia on 9 June 1999 and with [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 1244]] which, whilst recognising Serbian sovereignty, authorised an international civil and military presence in Kosovo, placing it under interim [[UNMIK|UN administration]] with a NATO-led peacekeeping force ([[Kosovo Force|KFOR]]). With the withdrawal of Serb forces, ethnic-Albanian refugees began returning from [[Albania]] and the [[Republic of Macedonia]]. In fear of their safety, perhaps up to 250,000 Serbs and other ethnic minorities fled their homes north&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.reliefweb.int/library/documents/2002/coe-kos-16oct.pdf Kosovo: The Human Rights Situation and the Fate of Persons Displaced from Their Homes (.pdf)] &quot;, report by [[Alvaro Gil-Robles]], [[Council of Europe]] Commissioner for Human Rights, Strasbourg, October 16, 2002, p. 30.&lt;/ref&gt;. Many displaced Serbs fear to return and around 120,000-150,000 Serbs remain in Kosovo, but remain in a difficult security and economic situation.

In 2001, UNMIK promulgated a Constitutional Framework for Kosovo which established the [[Provisional Institutions of Self-Government]] (PISG), including an elected Kosovo Assembly, Presidency and office of Prime Minister.  Kosovo held its first free, Kosovo-wide elections in late 2001 (municipal elections had been held the previous year).  UNMIK oversaw the establishment of a professional, multi-ethnic Kosovo Police Service.  

In March 2004, Kosovo experienced its worst inter-ethnic violence since the Kosovo War.  The [[2004 unrest in Kosovo|unrest in 2004]] was sparked by a drowning of Albanian children after they were chased into the Ibar river by Serbian military dogs [[http://www.mfa.gov.yu/FDP/nytimes180304_e.html]].  Taking advantage of the situation, anonymous Serbians burned their own houses, Serbian Orthodox Church sites (including some medieval churches and monasteries) and UN facilities, and then blamed the incidents on local Albanians. Kosovo Police established a special investigation team to handle cases related to the 2004 unrest and according to Kosovo Judicial Council by the end of 2006 the 326 charges filed by municipal and district prosecutors for criminal offenses in connection with the unrest had resulted in 200 indictments: convictions in 134 cases, and courts acquitted eight and dismissed 28; 30 cases were pending. International prosecutors and judges handled the most sensitive cases.&lt;ref&gt;U.S State Department Report, published in 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

==Politics and governance==
{{main|Politics of Kosovo}}
{{seealso|United Nations Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo|Provisional Institutions of Self-Government}}
{{Politics of Kosovo}}
UN Security Council Resolution 1244 placed Kosovo under transitional UN administration pending a determination of Kosovo's future status.  This Resolution entrusted the [[United Nations Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo]] (UNMIK) with sweeping powers to govern Kosovo, but also directed UNMIK to establish interim institutions of self-governance.  Resolution 1244 permits Serbia no role in governing Kosovo and since 1999 Serbian laws and institutions have not been valid in Kosovo.  NATO has a separate mandate to provide for a safe and secure environment.

In May 2001, UNMIK promulgated the Constitutional Framework, which established Kosovo's [[Provisional Institutions of Self-Government]] (PISG).  Since 2001, UNMIK has been gradually transferring increased governing competencies to the PISG, while reserving some powers that are normally carried out by sovereign states, such as foreign affairs.  Kosovo has also established municipal government and an internationally-supervised Kosovo Police Service.

According to the Constitutional Framework, Kosovo shall have a 120-member Kosovo Assembly.  The Assembly includes twenty reserved seats: ten for Kosovo Serbs and ten for non-Serb minorities (Bosniaks, Roma, etc.).  The Kosovo Assembly is responsible for electing a President and Prime Minister of Kosovo.  

The largest political party in Kosovo, the Democratic League of Kosovo (LDK), has its origins in the 1990s non-violent resistance movement to Milosevic's rule.  The party was led by Ibrahim Rugova until his death in 2006.  The two next largest parties have their roots in the Kosovo Liberation Army (KLA): the Democratic Party of Kosovo (PDK) led by former KLA leader Hashim Thaci and the Alliance for the Future of Kosovo (AAK) led by former KLA commander Ramush Haradinaj.  Kosovo publisher Veton Surroi formed his own political party in 2004 named &quot;Ora.&quot;  Kosovo Serbs formed the Serb List for Kosovo and Metohija (SLKM) in 2004, but have boycotted Kosovo's institutions and never taken their seats in the Kosovo Assembly.  

In November 2001, the [[OSCE]] supervised the first elections for the Kosovo Assembly.  After that election, Kosovo's political parties formed an all-party unity coalition and elected [[Ibrahim Rugova]] as President and Bajram Rexhepi (PDK) as Prime Minister.  

After Kosovo-wide elections in October 2004, the LDK and AAK formed a new governing coalition that did not include PDK and Ora.  This coalition agreement resulted in [[Ramush Haradinaj]] (AAK) becoming Prime Minister, while Ibrahim Rugova retained the position of President.  PDK and Ora were critical of the coalition agreement and have since frequently accused the current government of corruption.  

Ramush Haradinaj resigned the post of Prime Minister after he was indicted for war crimes by the International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia (ICTY) in March 2005.  He was replaced by Bajram Kosumi (AAK).  But in a political shake-up after the death of President Rugova in January 2006, Kosumi himself was replaced by former Kosovo Protection Corps commander [[Agim Ceku]].  Ceku has won recognition for his outreach to minorities, but Serbia has been critical of his wartime past as military leader of the KLA and claims he is still not doing enough for Kosovo Serbs.  The Kosovo Assembly elected [[Fatmir Sejdiu]], a former LDK parliamentarian, president after Rugova's death. Slaviša Petkovic, Minister for Communities and Returns, was previously the only ethnic Serb in the government, but resigned in November 2006 amid allegations that he misused ministry funds.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.adnki.com/index_2Level_English.php?cat=Politics&amp;loid=8.0.363650179&amp;par=0 Kosovo: Serb minister resigns over misuse of funds] &quot;, Adnkronos international (AKI), November 27, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.reliefweb.int/rw/RWB.NSF/db900SID/LZEG-6VUQUS?OpenDocument Sole Kosovo Serb cabinet minister resigns: PM] &quot;, Agence France-Presse (AFP), November 24, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Today two of the total thirteen ministries in Kosovo's Government have ministers from the minorities. Branislav Grbic, ethnic Serb, leads Minister of Returns and Sadik Idriz, ethnic Bosnjak, leads Ministry of Health&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ks-gov.net/pm/?menuid=2&amp;subid=20&amp;subs=56&amp;lingo=1&lt;/ref&gt;

===Kosovo status process===

{{main|Kosovo status process}}
{{seealso|Constitutional status of Kosovo}}
International negotiations began in 2006 to determine the final status of Kosovo, as envisaged under [[UN Security Council Resolution 1244]] which ended the [[Kosovo War|Kosovo conflict]] of 1999. Whilst Serbia's continued sovereignty over Kosovo is recognised by the international community, a clear majority of the province's population would prefer independence. 

The [[UN]]-backed talks, lead by UN Special Envoy [[Martti Ahtisaari]], began in February 2006. Whilst progress was made on technical matters, both parties remained diametrically opposed on the question of status itself.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/6034567.stm UN frustrated by Kosovo deadlock] &quot;, ''BBC News'', October 9, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; In Februrary 2007, Ahtisaari delivered a draft status settlement proposal to leaders in Belgrade and Pristina, the basis for a draft UN Security Council Resolution which proposes 'supervised independence' for the province. As of early July 2007 a draft resolution, backed by the [[United States]], the [[United Kingdom]] and other European members of the [[Security Council]], had been rewritten four times to try to accommodate Russian concerns that such a resolution would undermine the principle of state sovereignty.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.setimes.com/cocoon/setimes/xhtml/en_GB/newsbriefs/setimes/newsbriefs/2007/06/29/nb-07&lt;/ref&gt; Russia, which holds a veto in the Security Council as one of five permanent members, had stated that it would not support any resolution which was not acceptable to both Belgrade and Kosovo Albanians.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.setimes.com/cocoon/setimes/xhtml/en_GB/newsbriefs/setimes/newsbriefs/2007/07/10/nb-02&lt;/ref&gt; Whilst most observers had, at the beginning of the talks, anticipated independence as the most likely outcome, others have suggested that a rapid resolution might not be preferable.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ft.com/cms/s/985caa90-de5a-11db-afa7-000b5df10621.html&lt;/ref&gt;

After many weeks of discussions at the UN, the [[United States]], [[United Kingdom]] and other European members of the Security Council formally 'discarded' a draft resolution backing Ahtisaari's proposal on [[20 July]] [[2007]], having failed to secure Russian backing. Kosovo Albanian leaders have reacted by proposing unilateral independence for [[28 November]] [[2007]], though the UN would be required to overrule any such action.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.yahoo.com/fc/World/Kosovo | Kosovo pushes independence after UN action fails | accessdate=2007-07-20&lt;/ref&gt; Violence is feared in Kosovo should Kosovo Albanian demands for independence not be met.

== Economy ==
{{main|Economy of Kosovo}}

[[Image:Kosovo stamp.jpg‎|thumb|left|100px|[[Postage stamp]] from Kosovo issued after the 1999 Kosovo War.]]

Kosovo has one of the most under-developed economies in Europe, with a per capita income estimated at [[Euro|€]]1,565 (2004).&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/COUNTRIES/ECAEXT/KOSOVOEXTN/0,,contentMDK:20629286~menuPK:297777~pagePK:1497618~piPK:217854~theSitePK:297770,00.html worldbank.org]&lt;/ref&gt; Despite substantial development subsidies from all Yugoslav republics, Kosovo was the poorest province of Yugoslavia.&lt;ref&gt;Christian Science Monitor 1982-01-15, &quot;Why Turbulent Kosovo has Marble Sidewalks but Troubled Industries&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, over the course of the 1990s a blend of poor economic policies, international sanctions, poor external commerce and ethnic conflict severely damaged the economy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/COUNTRIES/ECAEXT/KOSOVOEXTN/0,,menuPK:297775~pagePK:141159~piPK:141110~theSitePK:297770,00.html worldbank.org]&lt;/ref&gt;

Kosovo's economy remains weak. After a jump in 2000 and 2001, growth in [[Gross Domestic Product]] (GDP) was negative in 2002 and 2003 and is expected to be around 3 percent 2004-2005, with domestic sources of growth unable to compensate for the declining foreign assistance. [[Inflation]] is low, while the budget posted a deficit for the first time in 2004. Kosovo has high external deficits. In 2004, the deficit of the balance of goods and services was close to 70 percent of GDP. Remittances from Kosovars living abroad accounts for an estimated 13 percent of GDP, and foreign assistance for around 34 percent of GDP.&lt;ref&gt;http://ec.europa.eu/economy_finance/publications/enlargement_papers/2005/elp26en.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

Most economic development since 1999 has taken place in the trade, retail and the construction sectors. The private sector that has emerged since 1999 is mainly small-scale. The industrial sector remains weak and the electric power supply remains unreliable, acting as a key constraint. Unemployment remains pervasive, at around 40-50% of the labor force.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.eciks.org/english/lajme.php?action=total_news&amp;main_id=386&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://ec.europa.eu/economy_finance/publications/enlargement_papers/2005/elp26en.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; 

UNMIK introduced ''de-facto'' an external trade regime and customs administration on [[September 3]], [[1999]] when it set customs border controls in Kosovo. All goods imported in Kosovo face a flat 10% customs duty fee.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.buyusa.gov/kosovo/en/doingbusinessinkosovo.html&lt;/ref&gt; These taxes are collected from all Tax Collection Points installed at the borders of Kosovo, including those between Kosovo and  Serbia.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.seerecon.org/kosovo/documents/wb_econ_report/wb-kosovo-econreport-2-2.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; UNMIK and Kosovo institutions have signed Free Trade Agreements with [[Croatia]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.b92.net/eng/news/globe-article.php?yyyy=2006&amp;mm=10&amp;dd=02&amp;nav_category=123&amp;nav_id=37090 Croatia, Kosovo sign Interim Free Trade Agreement], [[B92]], 2 October 2006&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.euinkosovo.org/upload_press/4.06%20-%20UNMIK%20and%20Bosnia%20and%20Herzegovina%20Initial%20Free%20Trade%20Agreement%2017.2.06.pdf euinkosovo.org]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Albania]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.kosovo-eicc.org/oek/index.php?page_id=64&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.buyusa.gov/kosovo/en/doingbusinessinkosovo.html&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]] is Kosovo's largest import and export market (averaging €220 million and €9 million, respectively), followed by Serbia-Montenegro (€111 million and €5 million), Germany and Turkey.&lt;ref&gt;[http://siteresources.worldbank.org/INTKOSOVO/147270-1121700806276/20953280/Kosovo_Economic_Briefing_april.pdf Kosovo Economic Briefing (April)], worldbank.org&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Euro]] is the official currency of Kosovo and used by UNMIK and the government bodies.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.euinkosovo.org/uk/invest/invest.php&lt;/ref&gt; The Serbian [[Dinar]] is used in the Serbian populated parts.

The economy is hindered by Kosovo's still-unresolved international status, which has made it difficult to attract investment and loans.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/business/4509781.stm Brussels offers first Kosovo loan]&quot;, BBC News Online, 3 May 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; The province's economic weakness has produced a thriving black economy in which smuggled petrol, cigarettes and cement are major commodities. The prevalence of official corruption and the pervasive influence of organised crime gangs has caused serious concern internationally. The United Nations has made the fight against corruption and organised crime a high priority, pledging a &quot;zero tolerance&quot; approach.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kosovo.undp.org/Projects/TIK/tik.asp ''Transparency Initiative for Kosovo (TIK)''], UN Development Programme in Kosovo.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Demographics ==
[[Image:Kosovo ethnic 2005.png|right|thumb|180px|Ethnic composition of Kosovo in [[2005]] according to the [[OSCE]].]]
{{main|Demographic history of Kosovo}}

According to the Kosovo in Figures 2005 Survey of the Statistical Office of Kosovo,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ks-gov.net/esk/esk/pdf/english/general/kosovo_figures_05.pdf &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/4385768.stm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/country_profiles/3524092.stm&lt;/ref&gt; Kosovo's total population is estimated between 1.9 and 2.2 million in the following ethnic proportions. The estimate from 2000-2002-2003 goes (a 1,900,000 strong population):
* 90% [[Albanians]]  
* 5% [[Serbs]]  
* 3% [[Bosniaks]] and [[Gorani|Gorans]]
* 1% [[Roma people|Roma]] (see also [[Roma in Mitrovica Camps]])
* 1% [[Turkish people|Turks]] 

However, the figures are highly disputable. Some estimates are that there is an Albanian majority above 90 percent. The population census is set to take place in the near future. Others give much higher figures for Roma and Turks.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.salon.com/news/1999/03/31newsa.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.serbianunity.net/news/world_articles/Dragnich1098.html&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of the Albanians in Kosovo are [[Muslims]],&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/4385768.stm&lt;/ref&gt; and most Serbs are [[Serbian Orthodox Church|Serbian Orthodox]]. About 3% of Kosovo's population are [[Catholics]], and a large population of [[Atheists]] and [[Agnostics]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crisisgroup.org/home/index.cfm?id=1591&amp;l=1 Religion in Kosovo] - International Crisis Group&lt;/ref&gt;

== Administrative divisions ==
{{main|Subdivisions of Kosovo}}
{{see also|Municipalities of Kosovo}}
Kosovo is divided into seven districts:
*[[Priština District|Priština/Prishtina District]]
*[[Prizren District|Prizren/Prizreni District]]
*[[Peć District|Peć/Peja District]]
*[[Uroševac District|Uroševac/Ferizaji District]]
*[[Đakovica  District|Đakovica/Gjakova District]]
*[[Kosovska Mitrovica District|Kosovska Mitrovica/Mitrovica District]]
*[[Gnjilane District|Gnjilane/Gjilani District]]

[[North Kosovo]] maintains its own government, infrastructure and institutions by its dominant ethnic [[Serb]] population in the [[Mitrovica District]], viz. in the [[Leposavic]], [[Zvecan]] and [[Zubin Potok]] municipalities and the northern part of [[Kosovska Mitrovica]].

== Cities ==
[[Image:Prishtina maj 2005.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Priština]]/[[Prishtina]].]]

List of largest cities in Kosovo (with population figures for 2006):&lt;ref&gt;http://www.world-gazetteer.com/wg.php?x=&amp;men=gcis&amp;lng=en&amp;dat=32&amp;srt=npan&amp;col=aohdq&amp;geo=-244&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Priština]]/[[Prishtina]] (271,532)
*[[Prizren]]/[[Prizreni]] (165,229)
*[[Uroševac]]/[[Ferizaji]] (97,741)
*[[Đakovica]]/[[Gjakova]] (97,156)
*[[Peć]]/[[Peja]] (95,190)
*[[Gnjilane]]/[[Gjilani]] (91,595)
*[[Kosovska Mitrovica]]/[[Mitrovica (Kosovo)|Mitrovica]] (86,359)
*[[Podujevo]]/[[Podujeva]] (48,526)

== Culture ==
===Music===
: ''See also: [[List of Albanians#Musicians|Albanian and Kosovo Albanian musicians]], [[Music of Kosovo]], [[Music of Serbia]], [[List of Serbian musicians]]
[[Music]] has always been a part of the [[Culture of Albania|Albanian]] and [[Serbian culture]]. Although in Kosovo music is diverse (as it got mixed with the cultures of different regimes dominating in Kosovo), authentic Albanian music (see ''[[World Music]]'') and [[Serbian music]] do still exist. The Albanian one is characterized by use of ''[[çiftelia]]'' (an authentic Albanian instrument), ''mandolin'', ''mandola'' and ''percussion''.
In Kosovo, along with modern music, [[folk]] music is very popular. There are many folk [[singers]] and ensembles (both Albanian and Serbian). [[European classical music|Classical music]] is also well known in Kosovo and has been taught at [[universities]] (at the [[University of Pristina#Albanian university|University of Prishtina Faculty of Arts]]  and the [[University of Pristina#Serbian university|University of Priština at Kosovska Mitrovica]]  [[Faculty of Arts of Priština|Faculty of Arts]]) and several pre-[[college]] [[List of pre-college music schools|music school]]s
The modern music in Kosovo has its origin from the Western countries. The main modern genres include: [[Pop (music)|Pop]], [[Hip hop music|Hip Hop]], [[Rock (music)|Rock]] and [[Jazz]]. The most notable rock bands are: Gjurmët, Troja, Votra, Diadema, Humus, Asgjë sikur Dielli, Kthjellu, [[Cute Babulja]], [[Babilon]], etc. Ilir Bajri is a notable [[jazz]] and [[Electronic Music|electronic]] musician. Most notable hip-hop performers are the rap-group called NR (urbaNRoots) who also introduced a new type of rap different to the G-Funk that was widely spread before. Other hip-hop artists include [[Unikkatil]] (who lives in the USA but represents Kosovo), Tingulli 3, Ritmi I Rrugës, Mad Lion, K-OS and many more.

[[Leonora Jakupi]] and [[Adelina Ismajli]] are two of the most popular commercial singers in Kosovo today.
|
There are some notable music festivals in Kosovo:
* ''Rock për Rock'' - contains [[Rock (music)|rock]] and [[Heavy Metal music|metal]] music
* ''Polifest'' - contains all kinds of genres (usually [[Hip hop music|hip hop]], commercial [[Pop (music)|pop]], unusually [[Rock (music)|rock]] and never [[Heavy Metal music|metal]])
* ''Showfest'' - contains all kinds of genres (usually [[Hip hop music|hip hop]], commercial [[Pop (music)|pop]], unusually [[Rock (music)|rock]] and never [[Heavy Metal music|metal]])
* ''Videofest'' - contains all kinds of genres
* ''Kush Këndon Lutet Dy Herë'' - contains [[christian music]]
* ''[[North Kosovo|North]] [[Kosovska Mitrovica|City]] [[Jazz]] &amp; [[Blues]] [[festival]]'', an international [[music festival]] held annually in [[Zvecan]]
Kosovo Radiotelevisions like ''RTK'', ''21'' and ''KTV'' have their musical charts.

== Gallery ==
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Kosovo_government.jpg|The building of the [[Government of Kosovo]] in [[Priština]].
Image:Prizen kosovo.jpg|[[Prizren]].
Image:Erzengelkloster2.jpg|[[Serbs in Kosovo|Serb]] monastery, St Archangel, near river [[Bistrica]].
Image:Pamje_kacaniku.JPG|[[Kačanik]].
Image:Gjakova.jpg|[[Đakovica]].
Image:VeshjeKombetare.JPG|[[Albanians in Kosovo|Kosovo Albanian]] ethnic costume/dance.  
Image:Bibloteka Kombëtare e Kosovës.jpg|National Public Library in [[Priština]].
Image:Pec 001.jpg|Serbian monastery in [[Peć]].
Image:Prizren 004.JPG|Serbian monastery in [[Prizren]].
Image:Kosovo Polje sized.jpg|[[Kosovo Polje]].
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== See also ==
{{columns |width=280px
|col1 =
* [[Assembly of Kosovo]]
* [[Government of Kosovo]]
* [[Prime Minister of Kosovo]]
* [[President of Kosovo]]
* [[Serbs in Kosovo]]
* [[Albanians in Kosovo]]
* [[Post and Telecom of Kosovo]]
|col2 =
* [[National awakening and the birth of Albania]]
* [[Demographic history of Kosovo]]
* [[Unrest in Kosovo|Unrest in Kosovo during March 2004]]
* [[Metohija]]
* [[North Kosovo]]
* [[Flag of Kosovo]]
* [[Vidovdan]]

}}

==References==
&lt;div class=&quot;references-small&quot;&gt;&lt;references/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!--Please keep as single column as long URLs otherwise cause display problems on smaller windows/screens; thanks.--&gt;

==External links==
{{sisterlinks|Kosovo}}
* [http://www.ks-gov.net/pm/?menuid=&amp;subid=&amp;lingo=2 The office of Prime Minister of Kosovo] English version
* [http://www.unhcr.org/cgi-bin/texis/vtx/balkans-country?country=kosovo UNHCR - Balkans: Kosovo]
* [http://www.osce.org/kosovo/ OSCE Mission in Kosovo]
* [http://www.assembly-kosova.org/?krye=home&amp;lang=en Kosovo Assembly (Kuvendi i Kosovës)] English version
* [http://visitkosova.org/english/ The Official Webportal of Tourism in Kosovo]
* [http://ec.europa.eu/economy_finance/publications/enlargement_papers/2005/elp26en.pdf EU Commission report on economic development in Accession countries, including Kosovo]
* http://www.unosek.org/unosek/index.html UN Special Envoy's Office Website
* {{wikitravel}}
* [http://www.rtklive.com  RTK - Kosovo's public television - news in Albanian, Serbian, Turkish and Roma]
* [http://www.kosovakosovo.com/ KosovaKosovo] A source of information reflecting both sides’ claims in the dispute
* [http://www.unmikonline.org/ UNMIK] [[UN]] led civilian administration in Kosovo.
* [http://www.euinkosovo.org/index.php EU] EU Pillar in Kosovo. 
* [http://www.otvoreno.org.yu/ Otvoreno] A place where Serbian politicians speak openly on the Kosovo issue. In Serbian language only.
* [http://www.kosovo.net/default4.html KIM-Info News Service, News from Kosovo in English and Serbian]
* [http://www.crisisgroup.org/home/index.cfm?id=1243&amp;l=1 (ICG)] International Crisis Group, a source of independent analysis on Kosovo issues.
* [http://www.csdbalkans.org/roma Kosovo Roma Oral History Project] An advocacy website for Kosovo's Roma/ Gypsies, with significant details on Kosovo's contested history.
* [http://www.eciks.org/english/index.php ECIKS] Economic Initiative for Kosovo, information on investment opportunities.
* [http://www.state.gov/www/regions/eur/rpt_990604_ksvo_ethnic.html US State Dept. fact sheet &quot;The Ethnic Cleansing of Kosovo&quot;]
* [http://www.xhakli.com/2004/05/25/kosovo-search-challenge-helping-people-find-information-from-kosovo.php Kosovo Blog Online&quot;] Kosovo Search Challenge: Helping people find information for Kosovo, the positive side of Kosovo.
* [http://www.nato.int/kfor/ KFOR] Kosovo Forces (KFOR) NATO peacekeeping forces

===Pro-Albanian===
* http://www.ess.uwe.ac.uk/kosovo/contents.htm
* [http://www.albanian.com/ Albanian.com] A Community portal where Albanians share information and ideas.
* [http://www.newkosovo.org/ Alliance for a New Kosovo] A Policy Resource on Kosovo Independence.
* [http://www.kosovaevidence.com KosovoEvidence.com] - movie about what happened in Kosovo during the war
* [http://www.eciks.org Economic Initiative for Kosovo] - &quot;...latest news, analysis and publications from the Kosovar economy&quot;
* [http://www.alb-net.com/index.htm Kosovo Crisis Center] A collection of articles on Kosovo, in [[English language|English]].
* [http://www.aacl.com/indexmain.html AACL] Albanian American Civic League.
* [http://www.kosovalive.com/?cid=2 KosovaLive] Kosovo Albanian independent news agency (this section in [[English language|English]]).
* [http://www.savekosova.org/ American Council for Kosova] - U.S. nonprofit organization dedicated to a better understanding of the issue of Kosovo by the American public

===Pro-Serbian===
* [http://www.srbija.sr.gov.yu/kosovo-metohija/?change_lang=en Kosovo and Metohija] - Serbian Government Website
* [http://www.kosovo-metohija.com/ News from Kosovo]
* [http://www.kosovocompromise.com/ Kosovo Compromise] Presentation on Kosovo issue of ''4S Institute'', Brussels
* [http://www.rastko.org.yu/kosovo/ Rastko Project] - dedicated to Serbia and Serb-related arts, humanities and Orthodox religion (in [[English language|English]])
* [http://www.mfa.gov.yu/Policy/CI/kosovo-slike/index.html Terror in Kosovo] Terror in Kosovo (in [[English language|English]])
* [http://www.kc.gov.yu/ Coordination Center of SCG and the Republic of Serbia for Kosovo] (in [http://www.kc.gov.yu/D-ENGLISH/index-eng.html English], [http://www.kc.gov.yu/A-CIRILICA/index-cir.html Serbian] and [http://www.kc.gov.yu/C-ALBANSKI/index-alb.html Albanian])
* [http://www.kosovo.net/ Kosovo-The Land of the Living past] (in [[English language|English]])
* [http://www.savekosovo.org American Council for Kosovo] - U.S. nonprofit organization dedicated to promoting a better American understanding of the Serbian province of Kosovo and Metohija and of the critical American stake in the province’s future. 
* [http://www.eparhija-prizren.com/defaultE.asp Diocese Kosovo of Serbian Orthodox Church] 
* [http://rs-icty.org/frontpage.htm Republic Secretariat for Relations with International Criminal Tribunal in The Hague and War Crimes Research]

{{Template group
|title = Geographic locale
|list  =
{{Kosovo}}
{{Autonomous Provinces of Serbia}}
}}
{{Template group
|title = International membership and history
|list  =
{{Non-sovereign territories of Europe}}
{{Central European Free Trade Agreement (CEFTA)}}
{{Republics and autonomous provinces of the former Yugoslavia}}
}}

&lt;!--Categories--&gt;
[[Category:Kosovo]]

&lt;!--Other languages--&gt;

[[als:Kosovo]]
[[ar:قوصوه]]
[[frp:Kosovo]]
[[ast:Kosovo]]
[[zh-min-nan:Kosovo]]
[[bs:Kosovo]]
[[br:Kosovo]]
[[bg:Косово (област)]]
[[ca:Kosovo]]
[[cs:Kosovo]]
[[cy:Kosovo]]
[[da:Kosovo]]
[[de:Kosovo]]
[[et:Kosovo]]
[[es:Kosovo]]
[[eo:Kosovo]]
[[fr:Kosovo]]
[[gl:Kosovo]]
[[ko:코소보]]
[[hsb:Kosovo]]
[[hr:Kosovo]]
[[io:Kosovo]]
[[id:Kosovo]]
[[it:Kosovo]]
[[he:קוסובו ומטוחיה]]
[[la:Ager merulensis]]
[[lv:Kosova un Metohija]]
[[lt:Kosovas]]
[[li:Kosovo]]
[[hu:Koszovó]]
[[mk:Косово]]
[[nl:Kosovo]]
[[ja:コソボ]]
[[no:Kosovo]]
[[nn:Kosovo]]
[[oc:Kosovë]]
[[nds:Kosovo]]
[[pl:Kosowo]]
[[pt:Kosovo]]
[[ro:Kosovo]]
[[ru:Косово и Метохия]]
[[sq:Kosova]]
[[simple:Kosovo]]
[[sk:Kosovo]]
[[sl:Kosovo]]
[[sr:Косово и Метохија]]
[[sh:Kosovo i Metohija]]
[[fi:Kosovo]]
[[sv:Kosovo]]
[[th:คอโซโว]]
[[tr:Kosova]]
[[uk:Косово]]
[[zh:科索沃]]</text>
