      <text xml:space="preserve">{{sprotected}}
{{otheruses}}
{{Kosovo-InfoBox}}
&lt;!-- Please be very careful in editing the introduction of this article. It has been the subject of a lot of discussion on the talk page and has been the target of several revert wars. Please discuss any major changes on the talk page first. --&gt;

'''Kosovo''' ([[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Kosovë''/''Kosova'', [[Serbian language|Serbian]]: Косово и Метохија/''Kosovo i Metohija'') is a province in southern [[Serbia]]. While it is legally a part of Serbia it has been administered by the [[United Nations]] since the end of the 1999 [[Kosovo War]]. Security is provided by the [[NATO]]-led peacekeeping force, [[Kosovo Force]] (KFOR).  

Kosovo borders [[Montenegro]], [[Albania]] and the [[Republic of Macedonia]]. The mountainous province's capital and largest city is [[Priština]]. Kosovo has a population of around two million people, predominately ethnic [[Albanians]], with smaller populations of [[Serbs]], [[Turkish people|Turks]], [[Bosniaks]] and other ethnic groups.

The province is the subject of a long-running political and territorial dispute between the Serbian (and previously, the [[Yugoslavia|Yugoslav]]) government and Kosovo's majority Albanian population. Kosovo has been under Serbian sovereignty since [[1912]] but since the end of the Kosovo War in [[1999]] it has been administered by the United Nations with little direct involvement from the Serbian government. International negotiations began in [[2006]] to determine the final status of Kosovo; it is widely expected that the talks will lead to some form of independence. &lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.economist.com/displaystory.cfm?story_id=4489028 Kosovo's status - the wheels grind on]&quot;, ''The Economist'', October 6, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

== Geography ==
''For administrative divisions, see [[Municipalities of Kosovo]]''
[[image:UTkosovo rel small 92.jpg|thumb|left|275px|Physical map of Kosovo]]
With an area of [[1 E10 m²|10,912]] [[square kilometre]]s (4,213 [[square mile|sq.&amp;nbsp;mi]]) and a population of over two million on the eve of the 1999 crisis, Kosovo borders [[Montenegro]] to the northwest, [[Central Serbia]] to the North and East, the [[Republic of Macedonia]] to the south and [[Albania]] to the southwest. The province's present borders were established in [[1945]]. The republic of [[Serbia]] has one other autonomous province, [[Vojvodina]], located in the far north of the country.

The largest cities are [[Pristina]], the capital, with an estimated 600,000 citizens, and [[Prizren]] in the southwest with 120,000 citizens; five other towns have populations in excess of 50,000. The climate in Kosovo is continental with warm summers and cold and snowy winters. .

There are two main plains in Kosovo. The [[Metohija]]/Rrafshi i Dukagjinit basin is located in the western part of the province, and the Plain of Kosovo ([[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Rrafshi i Kosovës, [[Serbian language|Serbian]]: ''Kosovska Dolina'') occupies the central area.

Much of Kosovo's terrain is rugged. The [[Sar Mountain]] (Albanian: ''Mali i Sharrit'', Serbian: ''Šar Planina'') is located in the south and south-east, bordering [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]]. It is one of the region's most popular tourist and skiing resorts, with [[Brezovica]] and Prevalac/Prevallë as the main tourist centres. Kosovo's mountainous area, including the highest peak Deravica/Gjeravica (2656 m above sea level), is located in the south-west, bordering [[Albania]] and [[Montenegro]]. 

The mountain range dividing Kosovo from Albania is known in English as the [[Cursed Mountains]] or Albanian Alps (Albanian: ''Bjeshkët e Nemuna'', Serbian: ''Prokletije''). The Kopaonik mountain is located in the north, bordering [[Serbia proper]]. The central region of [[Drenica]], Carraleva/Crnoljevo and the eastern part of Kosovo, known as Gallap/Golak, are mainly hilly areas. 

There are several notable rivers and lakes in Kosovo. The main rivers are the [[Drin River]] (Albanian: ''Drini i Bardhë'', Serbian: ''Beli Drin''). Several other waterways flow into it, including the</text>
