      <text xml:space="preserve">{{otheruses}}
{{POV-check}}

{| {{prettyinfobox}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
&lt;big&gt;'''Kosovo'''&lt;br/&gt;
|- style=&quot;border-top: 2px solid gray;&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Image:LocationKosova.PNG|300px|LocationKosova]] 
|-
| [[Official language]]s
| [[Serbian language|Serbian]], [[Albanian language|Albanian]]
|-
| [[Capital]]
| [[Priština]]/[[Prishtinë]]
|-
| [[President of Kosovo|Transitional President]]
| [[Fatmir Sejdiu]]
|-
| [[Prime Minister of Kosovo|Transitional Prime Minister]]
| [[Agim Çeku]]
|-
| [[Area]]&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; Total&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; % water
| &lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;[[1 E10 m²|10,912]] km²&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;4,213&amp;nbsp;[[square mile|sq.&amp;nbsp;mi]]&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;n/a
|-
| valign=top | [[Population]]&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; Total ([[2003]])&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; [[Population density|Density]]&lt;br/&gt;
| &lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;2.1 million (est.)&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;220/km² (approx)&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;570/sq.&amp;nbsp;mi
|-
| valign=top | [[List of ethnic groups|Ethnic groups]]&lt;br/&gt;([[2003]])
| [[Albanians]]: ''88%''&lt;br/&gt;[[Serbs]]: ''7%''&lt;br/&gt;Others: ''5%''
|-
| [[Time zone]]
| [[Coordinated Universal Time|UTC]] +1
|-
| [[Currency]]
| [[Euro]] and [[Serbian dinar]]
|-

|
|}
'''Kosovo''' ([[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Kosovë'' / ''Kosova'', [[Serbian language|Serbian]]: Косово и Метохија / ''Kosovo i Metohija'') is a territory in South Eastern Europe. By the UN resolution 1244 (adopted in 1999), Kosovo is defined as autonomous territory within former [[Federal Republic of Yugoslavia]] under UN administration. Whether this will remain the case is still unclear, as the final status of Kosovo is the subject of an ongoing dispute between government of Serbia and Kosovo's government. Talks on this issue started in Vienna, on February 20, [[2006]] [http://www.unmikonline.org/news.htm#1703].

== Geography ==
[[image:UTkosovo rel small 92.jpg|thumb|right|275px|Physical map of Kosovo]]

With an area of [[1 E10 m²|10,912]] [[square kilometre]]s (4,213 [[square mile|sq.&amp;nbsp;mi]]) and a population of over two million on the eve of the 1999 crisis, Kosovo borders [[Montenegro]] to the northwest, [[Serbia]] to the North and East; [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]] to the south, and [[Albania]] to the southwest. The largest cities are [[Prishtinë]]/[[Pristina]] the capital, with an estimated 500,000 inhabitants, and [[Prizren]] in the southwest with 120,000: five other towns have populations in excess of 50,000. The name [[Metohija]] is used by mostly [[Serbs]] for the western part of the land. [[Albanians]] refer the area as ''Rrafshi i Dukagjinit''.

== History ==
{{main|History of Kosovo}}
It is likely that the region of Kosovo has been inhabited by [[Illyrians|Illyrian tribes]] since the [[Bronze Age]]. In ancient times the area has been known as [[Dardania (Europe)|Dardania]] and was settled by a tribe with the same name. The [[Dardani]] were of Illyrian and Thracian stock and some (notably Albanians) claim that Albanians are direct descendants of Illyrians. Illyrians organised resistance against [[Greeks]] and [[Ancient Rome|Romans]] for hundreds of years but after the long wars of Illyrian tribes against intruders, the region was later occupied by the [[Roman Empire]] under Emperor [[Augustus]]. When the Roman Empire split in [[Anno Domini|A.D.]]&amp;nbsp;[[395]], the Kosovo region came under the [[Byzantine Empire|Eastern Roman Empire]], later known as the Byzantine Empire.

==Disputes over language, culture and citizenship==
The territory is most widely known as 'Kosovo' and this has become the standard in international and United Nations usage. In [[Albanian language|Albanian]] this name becomes 'Kosova', which is more often found within Kosovo and in official use by the Provisional Institutions, though both Albanian and [[Serbian language|Serbian]] are official languages. Wherever political and cultural sensitivity are particularly important, the international community will use 'Kosovo/Kosova' to describe the province and adopt a similar standard for many place names. While the formal title 'Republic of Kosova' has fallen out of use with the integration of Kosovo Albanian politics into the UNMIK system, the formal Serbian title 'Kosovo i Metohija' remains in colloquial and official use in parts of Kosovo and in Serbia proper, where parallel institutions for Kosovo remain until final status is resolved.

The question of what to call the inhabitants of Kosovo collectively has also aroused debate. The two words accepted by the [[Oxford English Dictionary]] are &quot;Kosovar&quot; (borrowed from Albanian), the most widely used variant in English, by far, and &quot;Kosovan&quot; (using the English rules for [[demonym]]s) much less used. As Kosovo has no formal [[state]]hood, current international usage is to refer to Kosovo [[Serbs]] and Kosovo [[Albanians]]. Most of the Albanian-descended community in Kosovo would prefer the use of Kosovar or Kosovan because of the attendant political overtones, while the Serb minority continue to think of themselves as Serb or Serbian (from Kosovo).

As for language and citizenship, so for cultural and political symbols. Kosovo had its own flag, when it used to have a province status within former Yugoslavia. The former province of Kosovo was identified with a flag similar to the one of Albania, but had a large star on the right-handside. The [[Flag of Albania|Albanian flag]] is used unofficially by the Kosovo Albanian-dominated administration and the vast majority of Kosovo Albanians; although recently the [[:Image:Kosovo Presidential Flag.gif|flag of the presidency]] is being used as an unofficial flag of Kosovo, as could be seen during [[Ibrahim Rugova]]'s funeral [http://sq.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ibrahim_Rugova].

The Serb-inhabited area of north Kosovo uses only the [[flag of Serbia]], which is formally the flag of Serbia, although this usage is rejected by virtually all Kosovo Albanians and other smaller minorities apart from Serbs and some Roma.

== Politics and international status ==
Kosovo's international status is anomalous. The administration is presently conducted by the [[United Nations]] with little or no involvement on the part of the Serbian government (under Security Council resolution 1244 of [[10 June]] [[1999]]; see [http://www.un.org/Docs/scres/1999/sc99.htm Security Council Resolutions 1999]).  The supervision of the government of Kosovo is the responsibility of the [[United Nations Mission in Kosovo]] (UNMIK). Under the terms of the [[Kumanovo agreement]] and subsequent UN [[Security Council]] [[Resolution 1244]], which ended the [[Kosovo War]], security is provided by the Kosovo Force (KFOR), which is led by [[NATO]] and is answerable to UNMIK.

{{Politics of Kosovo}}
UNMIK has so far established a provisional assembly, provisional government and the office of provisional president, which are legislative and executive bodies under UNMIK's control. Control of security, justice and external affairs are still under full UNMIK control. Elections for the [[Assembly of Kosovo]] were held in November [[2001]] and again in [[2004]] and were qualified as the most democratic elections in the Balkans. [[Ibrahim Rugova]] was elected as president in March [[2002]]. The seat of the assembly, government and president is in [[Prishtina]]/[[Pristina]]. So far, the parliament has enacted and UNMIK approved a constitutional framework, customs code, two criminal codes and some 200 laws.

The Constitutional Framework enacted by the Kosovo Assembly (with UN Security Council approval) has adopted a policy of [[affirmative action]] in the assembly to ensure that Kosovo's minorities are properly represented. Out of 120 seats, 10 are reserved for Serbs and another 10 for non-Albanian minorities, while the remaining 100 seats are elected through direct voting. UNMIK does not take account, though, the Serbs and other non-Albanians who have left Kosovo as a result of interethnic tension, many of whom are unable to reclaim lost property or safely to attend elections. The process of 'returns' of these displaced persons has yet to begin in earnest, as a result of insufficient funding and a perceived inability of the UN to control violence against minority groups, as well as a concern on the part of Kosovo Albanians that an increased number of Serbs will undermine the chances for an independent Kosovo.

Kosovo is still recognised internationally as a part of former Yugoslavia. Its final status has not yet been resolved, (talks on the subject started on 20 February 2006), and considerable difficulties lie ahead in balancing the irreconcilable Kosovo Albanian, Kosovo Serb and Belgrade positions. The Kosovo Albanians reject Serbian sovereignty and demand secession from the country. On the other side, Serbia is opposed to yielding any of its territory, and domestic opinion, supported by the existence of a centuries-old written, material and architectural history, continues to see the province as the heartland of Serbian culture.

The international community is becoming less and less reluctant to see Kosovo become independent, as the last Contact Group and UN Security Council meetings showed. The [[NATO]] countries insisted on the republican borders as the only acceptable solution during the wars in [[Croatia]] and [[Bosnia-Herzegovina]] in the 1990s, but this does not rule out that they might revisit this in the case of Kosovo vis-à-vis Serbia and Montenegro. Questions have also been raised about whether an independent Kosovo would be politically or economically viable, given its small populationa and the state of its economy. However the population of Kosovo is larger than several European countries including Estonia, Iceland, Luxembourg and Malta. But once its status is resolved and Kosovo has access to international monetary institutions the economic development will be possible. In early 2006, Western diplomats have come out clearly in support of an independent Kosovo, with guarantees for the minorities. 

UNMIK is issuing travel documents which serve instead of [[passport]]s in countries which recognise them, and issues identity cards and car plates, which again are valid only in certain countries[http://www.unmikonline.org/misc/traveldocs.htm]. UNMIK has created a police force (the [[Kosovo Police Service]]) with employees from all ethnic communities (Albanian, Serbian, Roma, Bosniac, etc) and manages the province's railways and airline ([[Kosova Airlines]]). The airspace and borders of Kosovo are controlled by KFOR.

The European Union runs the Kosovo economy in cooperation with the Kosovo institutions. The EU has initiated the [[Stabilisation Tracking Mechanism]], a special and separate track of EU integration for Kosovo. 

On [[January 21]], [[2006]], the President of Kosovo, Dr.[[Ibrahim Rugova]], died at age 61.  On [[February 10]], 2006, [[Fatmir Sejdiu]] was elected to be the second President by an 80-12 vote in parliament. On [[March 10]], 2006, [[Agim Çeku]] was appointed as the Prime Minister of Kosovo, during a voting by the Assembly of Kosovo.

== Economy ==
[[UNMIK]] declared the [[euro]] to be the official currency of the province in [[2001]] in the course of implementing a currency reform. This was undertaken to replace the previous widespread use of the [[Deutschmark]], which had become the ''de facto'' currency even before the 1999 war. However, the [[Serbian dinar]] remains an official currency, used principally in the [[Kosovo Serb enclaves]]; it is only used sporadically outside of them. Most trade is conducted using the euro; Kosovo's administration uses the euro exclusively, and all commercial banks use the euro as the primary currency. Of other international currencies, the [[United States dollar]] and [[Swiss franc]] are the most widespread.

== Demographics ==
Ethnic Albanians comprise almost 90% of the population of the province. In the aftermath of the conflict some one thousand non-Albanians, particularly [[Serbs]] and [[Roma]] either followed Serb soldiers as they withdrew, were forcibly expelled by the Albanian majority or fled the province to escape perceived threats of revenge by Albanians. The non-Albanian population of Kosovo has continued to fall since the arrival of NATO and the UN as a result of violence, perceived intimidation, and economic hardship. Many still live in communal camps in [[Serbia]] or [[Macedonia]] cared for by international relief agencies. However, there have been many attempts by Kosovo's government to resettle non-Albanians in the region which have largely been successful, including the resettlement of well over one thousand Serbians and Roma from 2004 - 2005. The Kosovo government has been widely praised for paying for the rebuilding of Serb houses in the aftermath of the 2004 riots. This has been marked as the first case of reparations in the history of the Balkans. 

According to the 2000 Living Standard Measurement Survey of the Statistical Office of Kosovo[http://www.sok-kosovo.org/pdf/population/Kosovo_population.pdf], Kosovo's total population is estimated between 1,8 and 2,0 million in the following ethnic proportions:
* 88% [[Albanians]] (between 1,584,000 and 1,733,600) 
* 7% [[Serbs]] (between 126,000 and 140,000)	
* 3% [[Muslims by nationality|Muslims]] and [[Bosniaks]] (54 to 60 thousand) 
* 2% [[Roma people|Roma]] (36 to 40 thousand) [[Roma in Mitrovica Camps]]
* 1% [[Turkish people|Turks]] (18 to 20 thousand)
However, the figures are highly disputable and may presently include an Albanian majority well above 90 percent.

==Presidents==
*[[Ibrahim Rugova]], [[1992]]-[[2006]] (deceased)
*[[Fatmir Sejdiu]], [[2006]]-present

==Prime Ministers==
*[[Bajram Rexhepi]], [[2002]]-[[2004]]
*[[Ramush Haradinaj]], [[2004]]-[[2005]]
*[[Bajram Kosumi]], [[2005]]-[[2006]]
*[[Agim Çeku]], [[2006]]-present

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Gjakova.jpg|[[Gjakova]]/[[Đakovica]]
Image:French Peugeot P4 dsc06852.jpg|[[KFOR]]
Image:Prishtina.jpg|[[Prishtina]]/[[Priština]]
Image:Prizen kosovo.jpg|[[Prizreni]]/[[Prizren]]
Image:Rahoveci.jpg|[[Rahovec]]/[[Orahovac]]
Image:Skenderbeuinprishtina.jpg|[[Skenderbeg]]
Image:Slava2005 6.jpg|[[Visoki Dečani monastery]]/[[Deçan monastery]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
* [[Assembly of Kosovo]]
* [[Government of Kosovo]]
* [[Prime Minister of Kosovo]]
* [[President of Kosovo]]
* [[Post and Telecom of Kosovo]]
* [[Battle of Kosovo|Battle of Kosovo (1389)]]
* [[Municipalities of Kosovo]]
* [[National awakening and the birth of Albania]]
* [[Subdivisions of Kosovo]]
* [[Metohija]]
* [[Unrest in Kosovo]] (about the March 2004 unrest)
&lt;!--It appears that this is an actual article, but it was removed * [[Sexual trafficking in Kosovo]] --&gt;

==External links==
{{sisterlinks|Kosovo}}
* [http://www.balkanforums.com Kosovo and the Balkans] - Discussion Forum
*[http://digital.library.unt.edu/govdocs/crs/search.tkl?q=kosovo&amp;search_crit=fulltext&amp;search=Search&amp;date1=Anytime&amp;date2=Anytime&amp;type=form  Congressional Research Service (CRS) Reports regarding Kosovo]
* {{wikitravel}}
* [http://www.rtklive.com  RTK - Kosova's public television - news in Albanian, Serbian, Turkish and Roma]
* [http://www.xixonline.com  Restaurant in Kosovo - Restaurant in Kosova]
*[https://www.osce.org/documents/mik/1999/11/1620_en.pdf Human Rights in Kosovo: As Seen, As Told. Volume I, October 1998 - June 1999].
* [http://www.lib.utexas.edu/maps/kosovo.html Kosovo maps from the Perry-Castañeda Library Map Collection]
* [http://www.chmouel.com/geeklog/gallery/gallery_individual.php/mkosovo/ A collection of photos from Kosovo]
* [http://www.otvoreno.org.yu/ A place where Serbian politicians speak openly of Kosovo issue] 
* [http://www.kosovakosovo.com/ A source of information reflecting both sides’ claims in the dispute]

===Pro-Albanian===
* [http://BalkanUpdate.blogspot.com Balkan Update]- A blog with news, analysis and the lates updates from Balkans
* [http://www.eciks.org Economic Initiative for Kosovo] - &quot;...latest news, analysis and publications from the Kosovar economy&quot;
* [http://www.albanian.com/main/countries/kosova Albanian.com] - general information
* [http://www.kosovaelire.com/ Kosova e lirë] (Free Kosova) -- Material about Kosovars and Albanians in Albanian language. 
* [http://beqiraj.com/kosova/de/ General information from Beqiraj.com] (in German)
* [http://beqiraj.com/kosova/al/ General information from Beqiraj.com] (in Albanian)
* [http://www.alb-shkenca.org/images/stories/Why%20Independence.pdf Why Independence for Kosovo?] A summary of the case for an independent Kosova by two Prishtina intellectuals

===Pro-Serb===
*[http://www.kosovo.com/sk/history/kosovo_origins/default.htm  Hugo Roth, ''Kosovo Origins'']: a historian's comprehensive overview
* [http://www.kosovo.com/ Kosovo.com] Serbian Orthodox Church's official website on Kosovo
* [http://www.rastko.org.yu/kosovo/crucified/default.htm Account of destroyed Serbian Orthodox churches in Kosovo and Metohija]
* [http://groups.yahoo.com/group/decani/ Kosovo Newsgroup archive]
* [http://www.kc.gov.yu/ Coordination Center of SCG and the Republic of Serbia for Kosovo]
* [http://www.srbija.sr.gov.yu/kosovo-metohija/ Serbian Government Kosovo-Metohija site]
* [http://www.tserkovnost.org/srbija/ Eastern Orthodox Resource Centre]
* [http://www.axisglobe.com/article.asp?article=689 Southern Serbia: The second Kosovo?]

[[Category:Disputed territories]]
[[Category:Kosovo| ]]
[[Category:United Nations]]

[[ar:قوصوة]]
[[ast:Kosovo]]
[[bg:تîٌîâî]]
[[zh-min-nan:Kosovo]]
[[bs:Kosovo]]
[[ca:Kosovo]]
[[cs:Kosovo]]
[[da:Kosovo]]
[[de:Kosovo]]
[[et:Kosovo]]
[[es:Kosovo]]
[[eo:Kosovo]]
[[fr:Kosovo]]
[[ko:ؤع¼ز؛¸]]
[[hr:Kosovo]]
[[id:Kosovo]]
[[it:Kosovo]]
[[he:קוסובו ומטוחיה]]
[[lt:Kosovas]]
[[hu:Koszovó]]
[[mk:Косово]]
[[nl:Kosovo]]
[[nds:Kosovo]]
[[ja:コソボ]]
[[no:Kosovo]]
[[nn:Kosovo]]
[[pl:Kosowo]]
[[pt:Kosovo]]
[[ro:Kosovo]]
[[ru:Косово]]
[[sq:Kosova]]
[[sr:Косово]]
[[fi:Kosovo]]
[[sv:Kosovo]]
[[tr:Kosova]]
[[uk:Косово]]
[[zh:科索沃]]</text>
